<articles>
	<article>
		<title>JNU row: What is the outrage all about? </title>
		<body> With the Jawaharlal Nehru University issue taking several twists and turns, The Hindu takes a look at how the issue started and where.

The debate around Afzal Guru

Earlier, students from the Jawaharlal Nehru University organised an event on Parliament attack convict Afzal Guru who was hanged in 2013. This was to be done the day after Guru’s third death anniversary.

The event organisers had pasted posters across the campus inviting students to gather for a protest march against “judicial killing of Afzal Guru and Maqbool Bhat” and in solidarity with the “struggle” of Kashmiri migrants at the Sabarmati dhaba in the campus.

Afzal Guru, the mastermind behind the Parliament attacks in 2001, was hanged in 2013.

The programme called “A country without a post office — against the judicial killing of Afzal Guru and Maqbool Bhatt”, was supposed to showcase the protest through poetry, art and music.

This set off the row, with the Members of the Akhil Bharatiya Vidyarthi Parishad (ABVP) staging a protest to demand expulsion of the organisers.

The university administration ordered a “disciplinary” enquiry and said the event organisers “went ahead without permission.”

‘Anti-India’ slogans

ABVP members alleged that the protest march consisted of students shouting ‘anti-India’ slogans. A purported video from the event shows students shouting anti-India and pro-Pakistan slogans. Students in the video are heard saying slogans like: “Kashmir ki azai tak bharat ki azadi tak, janh rahegi jari”.

Students say:

The students who were part of the committee that organised an event to mark the death anniversary of Afzal Guru said that none of them were part of the group that was shouting slogans.

A student who was a part of the event organising committee, told The Hindu: “The programme was a cultural evening organised to question the working of the Supreme Court. It was also meant to bring the grievances of the Kashmiri citizens to light. The struggles of ‘self-determination’ must be openly spoken about. Considering this is a democratic republic, why should dissent be suppressed?”

Members of the ABVP protest against JNU's event on Afzal Guru. Photo: AP

Sedition charges

A case of sedition against several unknown students was lodged at Vasant Kunj (North) police station. It was registered under IPC Sections 124A (sedition), 120B (criminal conspiracy) and 34 (acts done by several persons with a common intention).

The university also initiated action, barring eight students from academic activity pending an enquiry, though they would be allowed to stay as guests in the hostels.

Arrest of Kanhaiya Kumar

JNU Students Union president Kanhaiya Kumar was arrested on sedition charges after allegations of ‘anti-national’ sloganeering against him surfaced. He was ordered to three days of police custody.

JNUSU president Kanhaiya Kumar. Photo: Sandeep Saxena

Why did the police take action?

The police struck after videos of the alleged protest went viral. Home Minister Rajnath Singh talked to Delhi Police Commissioner B.S. Bassi and released a statement: “If anyone raises anti-India slogans, tries to raise questions on the country’s unity and integrity, they will not be spared.”

Students protest ‘police raj’ within campus

Students of JNU gave a shutdown call, saying that they will not allow classes to be held on the campus till students’ union president Kanhaiya Kumar is released. JNU teachers too, joined the students in boycotting classes and said they would take classes on “nationalism” in the varsity lawns.

The university teachers had earlier rallied behind its protesting students and questioned the administration’s decision to allow the police crackdown on the campus even as they appealed to the public not to “brand” the institution as “anti-national” but they had not joined the strike earlier.

Police personnel guard the entrance of JNU. Photo: PTI

‘Fake’ Twitter handle

Rajnath Singh alleged that JNU students had the backing of Jamaat-ud-Dawah (JuD) chief Hafiz Saeed. But, his statement was based “fake tweet” from an unverified Twitter account. The account has posted funny messages in the past, with many on the social media considering it as a parody account. The account @HafeezSaeedJUD is no longer in use.

When contacted, a senior officer who handles the Delhi Police Twitter account said, “What proof is there that it was a parody account? Our domain is not to check parody accounts but to red-flag any incendiary content on social media. The law is very clear on this, Internet is just a medium of communication. Idea was to caution young people and students to not get carried away by such messages.”

Journalists, activists attacked in front of Patiala Court

A student gets assaulted at the Patiala House court complex on February 15. Photo: PTI
On February 14, the Patiala House courts witnessed violence as a mob, wearing lawyer’s robe, slapped and kicked supporters of Kanhaiya Kumar. The attacks began when Mr. Kumar was scheduled to appear before metropolitan magistrate Loveleen and continued for about 45 minutes during which whoever ran into the mob looking young and carrying a mobile was slapped, kicked and chased away from the premises. Journalists and students bore the brunt of the violence, while the older men and women were intimidated by the mob.

O.P. Sharma’s comments

The BJP MLA O.P. Sharma who was also in Patiala House Courts during the scuffle, got embroiled in the controversy when a video of him started surfacing. The video showed Mr. Sharma beating up a CPI worker outside the court’s gate number 4.

“As I was leaving the court I saw a man raising anti-India and pro-Pakistan slogans. I lost my cool, like any patriot, and asked him to shut up. And when I turned, he attacked me with an object.”

Mr Sharma doesn’t know what he was hit with, but the people around him got “offended seeing the MLA being attacked” and started beating up the attacker, read “anti-national”. “The problem of this country at present is that terrorism and being anti-national are considered being progressive. And JNU is promoting this kind of ideology and producing anti-nationals. JNU should be sealed,” Mr. Sharma said.

Rahul Gandhi’s role

Congress vice-president Rahul Gandhi criticised the BJP government, accusing it of “bullying” the prestigious institution. Soon after visiting the JNU campus Mr. Gandhi called an emergency meeting at his residence where he discussed ways to “tie up” every compelling issue the students are facing in India today and place them in its anti-BJP narrative.

Rahul Gandhi met President Pranab Mukherjee over the JNU row and the alleged targeting of students in various parts of the country. Accompanied by senior leaders and also the young MPs of the party, the Congress vice president highlighted the “lawlessness” in Delhi in the wake of Patiala House court attacks and the way the government has handled the JNU row.

Kanhaiya Kumar thrashed

In a shocking sequel to the incidents of February 15 in the Patiala House courts complex, violence was unleashed barely moments before a hearing on sedition charges against JNUSU president Kanhaiya Kumar was to start at 2 p.m.

The Delhi Police again filled the role of a “silent spectator” as attackers defied the Supreme Court’s order for restricted entry to the trial court complex, bashed up Mr. Kumar en route to his court hearing and hurled the choicest abuse, gravel and a jagged end of a flowerpot piece at a six-member team of senior advocates, including Kapil Sibal, hand-picked by the Supreme Court to verify and report back on the ground situation in the court complex.

Three ABVP members resign

Three members of the RSS student wing, Akhil Bharatiya Vidhyarti Parishad (ABVP), have resigned from their positions in the Jawaharlal Nehru University (JNU) unit of the party, citing ideological differences. In a letter jointly issued by the three students, they have “dissociated themselves” from any further activity of ABVP. The letter adds that they cannot be the “mouthpiece” of a government that has unleashed oppression on student community.

Kanhaiya Kumar released from Tihar

A court in New Delhi ordered release of the JNUSU president from the Tihar jail after he furnished bail bond of Rs. 10,000 in the sedition case, a day after he was granted six months’ interim bail by the Delhi High Court.

Mr. Kumar was granted interim bail for six months by high court which had observed that FIR lodged in connection with an on-campus event that led to his arrest on sedition charge suggested it “is a case of raising anti—national slogans which do have the effect of threatening national integrity“.

'We want freedom in India, not freedom from India'

Addressing a huge gathering of students on the campus, soon after release from Tihar Jail, Mr. Kumar said: “It is not azadi from India, it is azadi in India [we want]... from the corrupt practices that are going on inside the country.” Mr. Kumar made his fiery speech at the same place where he had addressed students just a day before his arrest.

Here's what The Hindu has published over the years about Sedition laws:

Why our universities are in ferment

The Sangh Parivar’s student wing across campuses has been given the responsibility of raising the slogan of anti-nationalism wherever democratic aspirations are expressed.
Sedition and the government

Section 124-A of the IPC, pertaining to sedition, negates the right to dissent, which is an essential condition of any reasonable government. Viewed thus, it is Section 124-A that is ‘anti-India’.
Editorial: State overreach on the campus

The Delhi Police seemed to have taken the cue from a remark made by Rajnath Singh that “anti-national activities” would not be tolerated.
What is a university?

Vice chancellors hold charge of the university in trust. To give the police a free hand militates against the very spirit of the university as a space for critical engagement
Editorial: Revisit the sedition law

The government would do well to review such outdated penal provisions. Legislation exists to deal with unlawful activities and armed movements.
Render sedition unconstitutional

Sedition, defined as “incitement to violence” or “disorder”, is a legislation meant to suppress the voice of Indian people and has no place in a 21st century democracy.

Landmark sedition cases in India

Sedition was not a part of the original Indian Penal Code(IPC) enacted in 1860 and was introduced in 1870. Since then, the law has been applied several times and has undergone several interpretations. Here are some of the sedition cases that have made an impact.

Queen Empress Vs. Bal Gangadhar Tilak (1897)
This was the first instance where the law on sedition, specifically the Section 124 (a) from the Indian Penal Code was defined and applied. The Privy Council was of the view that acts like incitement to violence and insurrection were immaterial while deciding the culpability of a person charged with sedition.
Niharendu Dutt Majumdar Vs. King Emperor (1942)
The Federal Court held that “public disorder or the reasonable anticipation or likelihood of public disorder is the gist of the offence”. These judges were of the view that sedition implies resistance or lawlessness in some form. If there is no incitement to violence, there is no sedition.
Kedar Nath Singh vs State Of Bihar (1962)
This was the first case of sedition tried under independent India. The Constitution Bench of the Supreme Court interpreted the law in line with the 1842 case - a person can be charged with sedition only if there is incitement to violence in his speech or writing or an intention to create disorder.
Shreya Singhal vs U.O.I on (2015)
The court ruled that a person could not be tried for sedition unless their speech, however offensive, annoying or inconvenient, had an established connection with any incitement to disrupt public order.

Offences against the State, 2014

- Total 512 cases against the state

- As many as 872 persons were arrested

A. Sedition (under Section 124A IPC)

- Of 512, 47 cases were reported under sedition

- 58 arrested

- 73% of cases in two states: Jharkhand (18) and Bihar (16)

Kerala (5), West Bengal (2), Odisha (2), Andhra Pradesh (1), Assam (1), Chhattisgarh (1), Himachal Pradesh (1)

B. Waging war/collecting arms to wage war (under Sections 121, 121A, 122  123)

- 129 cases

- 166 persons arrested

- 75% of cases in three states: Assam (55), Meghalaya (32) and Manipur (10)

Keywords: Sedition, Jawaharlal Nehru University, JNU, sedition cases, Kanhaiya Kumar, ABVP
</body>
</article>
<article>
	<title>Make freedom in India: Translated excerpts of Kanhaiya Kumar’s speech at JNU </title>
	<body>We have faith in the Constitution, in this country’s law and the judiciary, and that change is truth. And there will be change, we are standing on the side of change. I have faith in our Constitution. As is written in the preamble, we stand by socialism, secularism and equality.

The first thing is, I don’t want to say anything about proceedings that are sub judice. I only want to say the entire country truly believes in the Constitution and wants to make Babasaheb Ambedkar’s dreams come true.

The PM has tweeted “satyamev jayate”. I may have a lot of ideological differences with you, PMji; but this slogan is not his, it’s in our Constitution. So I, too, will say satyamev jayate. Truth will win. I want to tell all those who are part of this fight that I will share my experience. So don’t believe that sedition has been used as a political tool against students, understand it like this:

I come from a village. In railway stations, there are magicians. The magician shows magic and sells rings, all kinds of rings, and he will tell you the ring will fulfil all your dreams. Similarly, we have some policy pundits in our country who say black money will come back, Har Har Modi, price rise will come down. Indians have a tendency to forget such things quickly but this time, the “jumla” is so big that we can’t forget these phrases. So their idea is that we should forget these “jumlas”. And how will they make us forget? They will stop fellowships to all research scholars. And what will people say? “Please give the fellowship, please give the fellowship.” Then they will say, okay, the fellowship of Rs 5,000 and Rs 8,000 will continue. So the question of raising the fellowship grant will never arise. And who will oppose this? JNU.

So when you get abused, don’t worry. In this country, whoever speaks against this anti-people government, what will its cyber cell department do? Make a doctored video. Abuse you. And count the number of condoms in your dustbin. These are solemn times and we need to seriously understand that the attack on JNU is an organised attack because they want to delegitimise the Occupy UGC movement and also because they want to end the ongoing fight to ensure justice for Rohith Vemula.

nationalism-759I want to tell you one thing: Getting admission to JNU is not easy. So it’s not easy to forget JNU students either. If you try to ensure that we forget things, we’ll remind you again and again. Whenever the political establishment has committed atrocities, JNU has stood up against it. You cannot dilute our fight.

What do they say? On one side, soldiers are dying at the borders. I salute those soldiers. But I have a question. A BJP leader said in Lok Sabha that young men are dying at the borders. I want to ask him, are they your brothers? Or the millions of farmers committing suicide, those who grow wheat for the country and the soldiers, the soldier’s father; what will you say to them? The farmer who works in the fields is my father, the soldier at the border who dies is my brother. So do not try to create a binary and false debate in the country. Who is responsible for deaths of soldiers? And in Parliament, who are you playing politics with? Who will take responsibility for those dying? Not the ones who are fighting, but rather the people making us fight.

So who is responsible for war? And who is responsible for making people fight? How my father is dying and how my brothers die? I want to ask those making these binary arguments on primetime television: Is it wrong to ask for freedom from problems in the country. Is that wrong? They ask, who do we want freedom from? You tell us. Is anyone a slave in India? No. So obviously we are not asking for freedom from India, my brothers, but we are asking for freedom in the country. And there is a clear difference between the two. We are not asking for freedom from the English. That freedom the people of this country fought for, and have already won.

I will now speak of my experiences. The police would take me for food and for medical tests. They’d ask how I survive without talking. So I started talking to them. And it turned out that the policeman was someone like me. In this country, who works in the police? Whose father is a farmer or a labourer or from a weaker section of society? I am also from one of the country’s backward states, Bihar. I also come from a poor family of farmers. And those who work in the police come from such families. I spoke to constables, head constables and inspectors; I did not interact much with IPS officers.

So I spoke to the policemen. They asked me, why do you say “lal salaam”? So I told them, lal means revolution, and salaam is to salute the revolution. So he said, “I do not understand.” And I asked, “Inquilab zindabad?” He said he knew this. So I said revolution in Urdu is inquilab. And he said even the ABVP raises this slogan. Now he understood. Theirs is a fake slogan and ours is real. Please tell me this, the policeman asked, “You people get everything cheap in JNU?” So I asked him why this has not happened with him. He works for 18 hours a day and without overtime. So I asked where he gets the money from? What they call corruption.

They get Rs 110 for their uniform. For this much, you cannot even buy undergarments. The policeman said this. And I told him, this is what we want freedom from. From hunger, from corruption. By this time, the agitation in Haryana had begun. A lot of personnel in Delhi Police come from Haryana. I salute people from Haryana, they work very hard. He said this caste politics is very bad. So I replied that this is what we want freedom from. So he said there is nothing wrong or seditious with this. I asked him who has the most power in the system. He said his baton. I asked if he could use the baton on his own. He said no. So who has all the power? He said the man who makes statements on fake tweets. I told him we wanted freedom from such Sanghi people who make statements on false tweets.

The policeman, like me, is from a common family. He also wanted to do a PhD. But he did not get a JNU. Like me, he wanted to fight the system. He wanted to understand the difference between sakshar and shikshit. But he is now in the police. That’s why you want to stamp us down. Because you don’t want a poor man to do a PhD. Because education being sold is expensive and he will not have the money to pursue it. You want to drown out those voices who can unite. Whether they are on the border or dying in the fields or are asking for freedom in JNU.

Babasaheb had said political democracy alone would not work, we will work towards social democracy. That’s why we speak of the Constitution. Lenin said democracy is indispensable to socialism. That’s why we speak of democracy, freedom of expression, equality and socialism. Because a peon’s son and the son of the president can study in the same school. You want to drown such voices.
</body>
</article>
<article>
	<title>Kanhaiya Kumar, we don’t need this exhausting diet of shrill from a kid who should be in class </title>
	<body>On 8 February, 2016 I did not know who Kanhaiya Kumar was and what he was engaged in. He was not even an incoming blip on my radar.

On 4 March, 2016, I don’t particularly want to know. Let him go back into anonymity. Do whatever he wishes to without his face being plastered all over the media. I am up to here with that overused set of pictures slamming into my life if I pick up a paper, switch on a TV, go to a website. Enough already!

That’s the beauty of, the glory of India… You can come out of jail and badmouth the Prime Minister and rabble rouse hours later and go home for lunch to be garlanded as a crusader.

Not even in America. By now the FBI and Homeland Security would have begun tracking you. Not even United Kingdom where MI5 and 6 and 7 would have opened a file on the guy.
And we dare talk of freedom being in peril?

Not only does he get to slag of the Indian Prime Minister but also now is the guide, mentor and philosopher to the nation. His words are golden and he reaps in mountains of publicity… The media cannot get enough of that scrunched up expression of zeal.

Do we need this? An exhausting diet of shrill from a kid who should be in class?

Now he can go round the country giving his fiery speeches, appear on talk shows, become rich, for doing absolutely nothing.

He is not a celebrity or an icon or someone I particularly want my children or their children to emulate. That he has been thrust into a sort of absurd greatness and been given a major boost is more an exercise in media's morality (or lack of it) where hellions are made into heroes and nobodies are consecrated as symbols of the democratic endeavor.

He leaves me stone cold. And the only reason I am prattling upon about it is in the hope that there will be enough folks out there who will say, yes, stop already, bahuth ho gaya.
He did not change the world for the better. He did not find a cure for AIDS or cancer. He did not even save anyone from a stormy sea or a burning building, no act of even mini-heroism. He has not enhanced the arts, excelled in sport, made a breakthrough in science or engaged in any travail of value. Not even a commercial enterprise where he got people jobs and created an empire. Absolutely nothing of worth and yet he is the most famous face in the country.

Good luck to him if he can exploit the system to his advantage but I don’t want to know anything more about his thoughts or his leanings or his opinion on anything. He is just not that important and it is time we stopped anointing him as some sort of a messiah. I am not interested in his philosophy or his leftist leanings or whether or not he has signed a pledge to be a good boy. I don’t want to see that face every morning.
Kanhaiya Kumar at JNU after his release on bail. PTI

Kanhaiya Kumar at JNU after his release on bail. PTI

He is just a student in a liberal university who has yet to start earning a living and paying his bills. A dependent. That his release on bail is being seen as some triumphant victory borders on the absurd and, frankly, I don’t even want to read about that or view it on TV. You want to dance in celebration, go ahead, so did the dervishes and the witches of Macbeth.
Our modern media is often slagged off for ignoring a story and down playing it. If ever there was a report worthy of being downplayed (or not played at all) this is it. Send it back to oblivion and let’s get on with life.

By that token I don’t give a damn whether he is poor or lives in a castle by the sea, what he ate for dinner or what his experiences in jail were. There are over 400,000 people in Indian jails and 68  percent of them are undertrials so really it is a no-brainer.

I can almost visualize this poster child for the student power vote bank being lifted up on high and flung into the higher rungs of political power… More’s the pity.
Believe me, somewhere here in this judgement is a kernel of the future of this JNU issue. It has not gone away and there will be another chapter. The grant of bail is merely a breather.

Till the next round, the less profile Mr Kumar shows the better for him. No one is your friend, mate. They will use you and abuse you and walk away. Just be sure you do not do the same.

</body>
</article>
<article>
	<title>Kanhaiya Kumar Better Patriot Than BJP Leaders: Nitish Kumar</title>
	<body>Patna:  JNU Students' Union president Kanhaiya Kumar is more of a 'deshbhakt' (patriot) than the BJP leaders who have dubbed him anti-national, Bihar Chief Minister Nitish Kumar said on Friday.

Nitish Kumar made the remarks after ending a two-day visit to Nepal, and a day after Kanhaiya Kumar was released after being in jail for 20 days on sedition charges.

The Janata Dal-United leader said Kanhaiya Kumar, who is from Begusarai in Bihar, had been framed.

Nitish Kumar praised Kanhaiya Kumar's hour-long speech at the Jawaharlal Nehru University (JNU) campus on Thursday night in which he attacked the government of Prime Minister Narendra Modi and raised issues of intolerance, hunger and poverty.

Nitish Kumar said the Modi government did not like the outspoken students of JNU who questioned the government's policies and raised issues that embarrassed it.

Student leaders like Kanhaiya Kumar will strengthen democracy in the country, the chief minister said. 
</body>
</article>
<article>
	<title>Full Speech: Kanhaiya Kumar, Out On Bail, Speaks Of 'Azadi' On JNU Campus</title>
	<body>New Delhi:  Jawaharlal Nehru University student leader Kanhaiya Kumar who was released from jail today on bail received a hero's welcome at the campus on Thursday evening. In a defiant speech, he took shots at the government tearing into charges of sedition against him and said he had faith in India's Constitution and democracy. Here are the highlights of his address:
 

    I want to thank everyone who has stood with JNU.
    I want to thank the people sitting in Parliament deciding what is right and what is wrong.
    I want thank their police and some media channels.
    I have no hatred towards anybody, especially towards ABVP.
    Because the ABVP we have on campus is more rational than the ABVP outside.
    There will be no witch hunt against them.
    We have no ill feelings towards ABVP because we truly believe in democracy and the Constitution.
    We don't look at ABVP as the enemy, we look at them like the Opposition.
    The best thing about how JNU has stood up in one voice was that it was spontaneous
    They had all of it planned but we were spontaneous.
    We stand up for all parts of Constitution - socialism, secularism and equality.
    I don't want to comment on the case. It is sub judice.
    I have many differences with the PM but I agree with his tweet - Satyameva Jayate - truth will triumph.
    In railway stations you will find a guy who shows you magic tricks. We have some people like that in our country.
    They say black money will come back, sabka saath sabka vikas, equality and all that.
    Yes we Indians forget things too soon but this time the tamasha is too big. These jumlas wont be forgotten.
    But what will happen if you speak up?
    Their cyber-cell will release doctored videos and count condoms in your dustbins.
    This is a planned attack to delegitimise the UGC protests, to prevent justice to Rohith Vemula.
    But let me just say it is not easy to get admission in JNU neither it is easy to silence those in JNU.
    You cannot dilute our struggle.
    They say soldiers are dying on the borders - I salute them.
    I want to ask the BJP lawmaker who said in Parliament that soldiers are dying on the border - is he your son or brother?
    He is the son or father of the farmer who is dying of drought.
    Do not create a false debate in this country.
    Who is responsible for their deaths?
    We will not rest till everybody has an equal right to prosperity.
    We are not asking for freedom from India because India has not colonised anyone.
    The man fighting on the border, perhaps he wanted to study but he couldn't get to JNU.
    You want to silence one Rohith, today look how big that revolution has become.
    I realised one thing in jail. We people of JNU speak in civilised voices, but we use heavy terminologies.
    Perhaps it doesn't reach the common man. We have to establish communication with the common people.
    We will bring Sabka Saath Sabka Vikaas for real.
    Today the honourable PM was talking about Stalin, I say Modi ji speak about Hitler too sometimes. Or maybe Mussolini?
    He speaks of Mann Ki Baat but doesn't listen.
    What is happening today in the country is very dangerous.
    It is not about one party, one news channel.
    I have never told this to anybody but my family makes Rs. 3,000. Can you imagine somebody like me doing a PhD in any other college?
    And they are calling anybody who stands up for this, traitor?
    What kind of a self-proclaimed nationalism is this?
    I want to remind our government that 69 per cent voted against you.
    Just 31 per cent voted for you and some of them were caught up in your jumlas.
    And today they are running a distraction campaign so that people don't ask them the real questions.
    RSS mouthpiece The Organiser did a cover story on JNU.
    If they can reason in a debate why JNU should be shut for four months, I will agree with them.
    They want to suppress the voice of dissent but I want to tell them, you will never be able to do that.
    Once again let's raise slogans for freedom - not from India, but within India.
    Freedom from hunger, poverty, the caste system - all of that.
</body>
</article>
<article>
	<title>Kanhaiya Kumar Returns To JNU With Call For Azaadi: 'Freedom IN India'</title>
	<body>
Kanhaiya Kumar Returns To JNU With Call For Azaadi: 'Freedom IN India'

Click to Play

Kanhaiya Kumar was arrested by the Delhi Police on February 12. (PTI photo)
New Delhi: 
Highlights

    Kanhaiya Kumar released from jail, gives powerful speech at JNU
    Hour-long speech demanded 'Azaadi' from corruption, backwardness, hunger
    Kumar: 'We want freedom, not from India, but within India'

Close to midnight at the Jawaharlal Nehru University (JNU), Kanhaiya Kumar, released from jail just hours before, repeatedly shouted 'Azaadi' - the word that led to sedition charges against him. Hundreds of students cheered.

"We are not asking for Bharat se Azaadi but Bharat me Azaadi (We want freedom - not from India, but within India)," said the 28-year-old to his captivated audience.

In the hour-long speech that trended worldwide and drew strong political reactions, Kanhaiya Kumar hit out at Prime Minister Narendra Modi and his government.

"When Modiji spoke about Stalin-Khrushchev, I felt like getting into the TV, grabbing him by his suit and saying 'let's talk about Hitler," he said to a roar of applause.

He began with slogans of "Azaadi  (freedom)" from hunger, corruption, discrimination and backwardness.

Mr Kumar said: "If there is a problem in the country, is it wrong to ask for azaadi from it? They say who is he demanding azaadi from? You tell me. Has India made anyone a slave? No. Then obviously not from India."
 

Kanhaiya Kumar received a rousing welcome at the campus. (PTI photo)
The student leader was released from Tihar Jail 21 days after his arrest on sedition charges for allegedly making anti-national statements at an event held on February 9 in support of Parliament attack convict Afzal Guru, who was hanged in 2013. One of the allegations against him is that he repeatedly called for "freedom from India".

As he returned to the JNU campus last night, a large crowd of students was waiting at the same place where he made the speech called "seditious" by the police. The atmosphere was electric.

"I come from a village where there are magic shows. People show magic tricks and sell rings that fulfill all wishes...We have some people like that in our country, who say black money will come back, sabka saath sabka vikas (development for all)," Mr Kumar said taking a dig at the BJP.

"We Indians forget too soon but this time the tamasha (show) is too big and these jumlas (gimmicks) won't be forgotten," he said to applause and laughter.

Throwing in plenty of one-liners to make his point, Mr Kumar quipped: "Some got swayed by your Har Har slogan. These days people are upset about Arhar (dal)."

He said he has "serious political differences with Mr Modi but will agree with his tweet in which he said Satyamev Jayate (truth will win)."

He also took a swipe at Education Minister Smriti Irani, who defended action against the JNU students. "My child, my child... she says. For the first time I saw her acting. Is it the Lok Sabha TV or Star Plus?"

Smriti Irani had repeatedly referred to Hyderabad student Rohith Vemula as a "child" while accusing opposition parties of politics over his suicide.

While he was speaking, reactions had started pouring in. Delhi Chief Minister Arvind Kejriwal was among the first to tweet his praise.
</body>
</article>
<article>
	<title>How BJP Student Wing Reacted To Kanhaiya Kumar, Who Trended Worldwide</title>
	<body>
How BJP Student Wing Reacted To Kanhaiya Kumar, Who Trended Worldwide


Kanhaiya Kumar, President of the Left-affiliated JNU Students Union, was arrested on sedition charges last month.
New Delhi: 
Highlights

    Saurabh Verma of BJP youth wing, JNU, reacts to Kanhaiya Kumar's bail
    Verma: We are not enemies but will react to slogans against country
    Verma: Kanhaiya's bail is conditional, waiting for final court verdict

Kanhaiya Kumar's speech, delivered last night at the Jawaharlal Nehru University or JNU, where he pledged his commitment to fighting for "azaadi (freedom) not from, but in India" catalyzed him into a worldwide trend on Twitter. The nearly one-hour-long address was fiercely critical of Prime Minister Narendra Modi and his government. Unsurprisingly, students from the ABVP, the youth wing of the ruling BJP, aren't impressed.

Mr Kumar, President of the Left-affiliated JNU Students Union, was arrested on sedition charges last month, forging an international debate on whether the government is using the charge of "anti-national" as a fig leaf for cracking down on dissent and free speech.

Mr Kumar has denied making anti-India remarks at a rally at JNU in February, after which he was arrested. Footage of Mr Kumar that was televised by some news channels has been declared doctored by a forensic lab that was asked to examine the video by the Delhi government.
 

Saurabh Verma said that the Delhi government's inquiry, which clears Kanhaiya Kumar of making inflammatory remarks, is not the last word on the case.

"Nobody is anyone's enemy here, everybody sits together and has tea as we discuss our ideologies, but if anyone is going to do sloganeering against our country we would react," said Saurabh Verma, General Secretary of the BJP's student wing at JNU. It was on the basis of an ABVP complaint that a BJP parliamentarian filed a police case last month, leading to the jailing of Mr Kumar after a controversial police raid on campus to find him. Two other students from JNU are still in prison.  

Mr Kumar, 28, has been given bail by the Delhi High Court with a list of conditions that include a commitment to not participating "actively or passively in any activity which may be termed anti-national".  

Mr Verma said that the Delhi government's inquiry, which clears Mr Kumar of making inflammatory remarks, is not the last word on the case. "Kanhaiya Kumar has got conditional bail; we believe in the workings of the court, we are waiting for the final result," he said. 
</body>
</article>
<article>
	<title>Timeline: What happened at JNU</title>
	<body>Here's a look at the sequence of events:

- There was a protest meeting on the third anniversary of the execution of Afzal Guru, a terrorist involved in 2001 Parliament attack.

- The protesting students and some outsiders shouted anti-India slogans and called Afzal Guru a martyr.

- The ABVP protested it, leading to a fight.

- The police were informed, following which they charged some unknown students with sedition.

- Union Home Minister Rajnath Singh has warned that no anti national activity will be tolerated.

- The Jawaharlal Nehru University Students Union (JNUSU) distanced itself from the alleged "undemocratic slogans" and attacked ABVP for trying to malign the university's democratic traditions.

- A day after JNU vice-chancellor M Jagadeesh Kumar initiated a disciplinary inquiry into the incident, the campus saw protests by JNUSU and ABVP against each other.

- The JNUSU has two members from the Left-backed All India Students Association (AISA), one from All India Students Federation (AISF) and one from RSS-affiliated Akhil Bharatiya Vidyarthi Parishad (ABVP).

- ABVP also burnt effigies of JNU administration for their inaction in the incident even though the Left-backed groups accused the administration of acting on the behest of ABVP.

- The event on Tuesday was organised by a group of students some of who were formerly with the leftist Democratic Students' Union.

- Delhi Police on Friday arrested JNUSU president.

- Delhi University professor SAR Geelani has also been booked for sedition after addressing an event at the Press Club in Delhi, condemning Afzal Guru's hanging.
</body>
</article>
<article>
	<title>Kanhaiya And An Electric Moment Close To Midnight At JNU</title>
	<body> It is often hard to assess how successful a political speech really is. Journalists use turnout, crowd response and their own formulations to gauge, but on Thursday night, the press pack at Jawaharlal Nehru University was unusually unanimous.

Hanging around the edges of the cheering JNU crowd, they were all drawn by the voice they had last heard on a cell-phone recording pleading his case in front of a Supreme Court panel. That voice which almost seemed broken by police brutality, was now transformed. Kanhaiya Kumar, fresh and energetic at close to midnight, made the crowds chant his name, made them laugh, spoke of freedom and shouted "Azaadi," again and again, in a span of 45 minutes.
 
"I saw Modiji on TV today,'' he said, the crowd by now hooked to his words, "I heard him talk about Kruschev and Stalin, I really wanted to get inside the TV." Loud laughter.

"I wanted to get in there and say, Modiji, let's talk of Hitler a little.'' Roar of approving laughter.
 
As someone who's covered political speeches for the last 17 years, this one was a little different, if only for the setting. After the last few weeks of much hate and suspicion directed at JNU, entering the campus was like entering a war zone. Barricades prevented broadcast vans from driving in, while a posse of policemen stood guard. But once inside, it was just the kind of idyllic island that universities are meant to be.
 
At one end of the famous Ganga Dhaba protesters had gathered; on the other end students sat on stone benches, grabbing dinners of paneer rolls and parathas. They weren't too exercised by the presence of so many media crews, even though the media had behaved abominably.

Even a single negative story has often led to beatings and bans from other campuses, but in JNU, I saw a reporter from a particular TV channel moving freely around campus displaying his mike ID; this despite a Delhi government inquiry having just established that his channel had first aired tampered footage which led to so much trouble for Kanhaiya and company.
 
No, the jibes towards our fraternity were only limited to the speech. Otherwise, there was no pushing, shoving, no threats. The students did what they had to do - decry their opponents, whether the media or the Modi government, in their speeches.

The students were also conscious perhaps that were many women present. Women of all ages - faculty and their families, students, were all gathered at the administrative block to listen to Kanhaiyya speak. When you saw some faculty members or ex-students carrying children on their shoulders or holding their hands, you knew it was a hatke crowd. It was impossible to see this campus as the hotbed of anti-nationalism when you witnessed a woman handing over her sleeping baby to her husband, so she could move closer to get a better view of Kanhaiya speaking?
 
Yes, maybe the press is swayed because the bougainvilleas on campus make it picture perfect, and the March evening feels just right to be out and about. Maybe, the press is only viewing the swooning when Kanhaiya's preaching to his own crowd.

"I salute those soldiers dying at the borders. But what about farmers committing suicides in abject poverty? Those farmers are the fathers of majority of those soldiers. My father is a farmer, my brother is a soldier. And who is responsible for those wars where they make the supreme sacrifice? People making them fight are responsible. Don't create these false binaries.''
 
Maybe the problem is a giant misunderstanding. As Kanhaiya explained, those in JNU speak in academic terms, which many outside failed to understand. But on Thursday night, Kanhaiya was able to make sure that he was understood by all.
</body>
</article>
<article>
	<title>Afzal Guru event: Anti-India slogans at JNU campus; ‘disciplinary’ enquiry ordered </title>
	<body>“The permission for the programme was sought by giving incomplete information, so it is an act of indiscipline. A committee headed by the Chief Proctor will examine the footage of the event and speak to the witnesses. It is on basis of the report, the varsity will take appropriate action,” JNU Vice-Chancellor Jagdeesh Kumar said.

Briefing about the “incomplete information”, the varsity Registrar Bhupinder Zutshi said, “There was nowhere mentioned in the permission request that the event will be on Afzal Guru, they just said that they wanted to organise a cultural event. How can any talk about disintegration of nation be national?”

The student organisers of the event had pasted posters across the campus inviting them to gather for a protest march against “judicial killing of Afzal Guru and Maqbool Bhatt” and in solidarity with “struggle of Kashmiri people for their democratic right to self determination” at varsity’s Sabarmati dhaba on Tuesday.

Members of the ABVP objected to the event and wrote to the Vice-Chancellor that such kind of marches should not be held on campus of an educational institution, prompting the university administration to order cancellation of the march as they “feared” that it might “disrupt” peace on campus.

But the organisers went ahead with the programme despite the cancellation of the permission and held a cultural programme, art and photo exhibition on the issue rather than a protest.

Agitated over the issue, ABVP members gathered outside VC office and shouted slogans demanding expulsion of the students who contributed to the “anti-national” activity.

JNU students’ union joint secretary Saurabh Kumar, who is the only ABVP member in the union, said, “How can an event on Afzal Guru, who attacked the temple of democracy, be held here? We are demanding expulsion of those who organised it”.

“This was an anti-national event. When we tried to stop them from holding a march, I was shown a gun. They raised anti-India slogans and for freedom of Kashmir,” he alleged.

However, this is not the first time that JNU students have organised an event on death anniversary of Afzal Guru.

The varsity registrar said, “if once a ‘wrong’ thing has happened it does not mean it has to happen again and again. We had denied the permission earlier too and those who were found “defying instructions” by the probe committee were penalised.”

The decision of ordering an enquiry was taken by the VC after he met the agitating students.

“The VC has told us that an enquiry has been ordered and based on the report action will be taken. But we will approach the HRD ministry as well as the Home Ministry demanding that the students who contributed to this “anti-national” activity be expelled,” said Alok Singh, President of ABVP’s JNU unit.

The organizers alleged ABVP terms everything controversial and against their own ideology as anti-national.

“This is a set pattern where we get permission but then ABVP comes right on the day of programme and administration cancels it last moment. Even screening of movies on controversial issues are considered anti-national.

“This is replication of what happened in Hyderabad University where ABVP’s actions forced Rohit to commit suicide,” said Anirban Bhattacharya, one of the organizers.

Meanwhile, police officials said that a complaint in this regard has been received from the agitating students and the matter is being looked into.
</body>
</article>
<article>
	<title>JNU Students March To Parliament, Demand Repeal Of Sedition Law</title>
	<body>

CPI(M) leader Brinda Karat addresses Jawaharlal Nehru University students taking part in protest march in support of Umar Khalid and Anirban Bhattacharya. (PTI photo)
New Delhi:  Jawaharlal Nehru University (JNU) students today marched to Parliament demanding repeal of the sedition law and enactment of a 'Rohith Act' to end caste based discrimination in educational institutions.

The students began their march from Mandi House around noon. They shouted slogans against the government over handling of the row at JNU and were stopped by police near Parliament Street police station where they camped for rest of the evening.

"Sedition is a very archaic law and imposing them upon students for a campus debate is just splitting the hair too much. Academicians across the globe believe that there is no place for such laws in a democracy, this should go. We appeal the government to repeal it," JNUSU vice president Shehla Rashid Shora said, while addressing the agitating students.

"We also demand that the government formulates a Rohith Vemula Act to end caste based discrimination in educational institutions," she added.

The march was joined by students and teachers from universities across Delhi including DU, Jamia and Ambedkar University.

Families of Mr Vemula, who was found hanging in Hyderabad University hostel as well as JNU
student Umar Khalid who is in custody in a sedition case, were also present at the march.

Addressing the gathering Umar Khalid's father Syed Qasim Ilyas said, "Our kind of nationalism teaches human beings to love each other. They will not understand our idea of nationalism".

Umar Khalid's sister Kulsum Fatima narrated how she is sick of hiding ever since the incident happened and how government "chose to target him" considering his "popularity" among JNU students.

CPI(M) politburo member Brinda Karat, said, "Sedition is like a badge of honour if the charge is applicable to those who raise their voices of dissent. Our leaders have been threatened, allegations have been raised on our party being 'seditious' but we take it all with pride if that is what costs to not accept their definition of nationalism".

The agitators keenly waited for the Delhi High Court's order on Kanhaiya Kumar's bail plea.

Kanhaiya Kumar, was arrested on February 12 in a sedition case in connection with an event on campus against hanging of Parliament attack convict Afzal Guru during which anti-national slogans were allegedly raised.

He was today granted interim bail for six months by the Delhi High Court which said that he has to cooperate in the ongoing investigation and has to present himself before the investigators as and when required. 
</body>
</article>
<article>
	<title>JNU Row: Rahul Gandhi, Arvind Kejriwal Among 9 Booked For Sedition</title>
	<body>Hyderabad: 
Highlights

    JNU row: Rahul Gandhi, Arvind Kejriwal among 9 booked for sedition
    Hyderabad lawyer, claiming no political affiliations, files charges
    JNU students Kanhaiya Kumar and Umar Khalid also named in FIR

A case of sedition has been registered in Hyderabad against Congress vice president Rahul Gandhi, Delhi Chief Minister Arvind Kejriwal, CPI leader D Raja, CPM General Secretary Sitaram Yechury and five others in connection with the JNU row.

A local lawyer, Janardhan Goud, who claims to not have any political affiliations, filed a complaint in court after which a case was registered in the Saroornagar police station.

Others named in the First Information Report include Congress leaders Anand Sharma and Ajay Maken, JD(U) Spokesperson KC Tyagi, JNUSU president Kanhaiya Kumar and JNU research scholar Umar Khalid.

"It is a court-referred matter. Following the court's directive, a case under section 124A of the IPC (sedition) has been registered yesterday against nine persons, including Rahul Gandhi, Arvind Kejriwal, Sitaram Yechury, JNUSU president Kanhaiya Kumar and others," Inspector S Lingaiah said.

The court has posted the matter for hearing on March 4.

In his petition, Goud said Rahul and other leaders, despite being aware that Delhi Police had registered a case against Kanhaiya on charge of sedition had visited JNU campus and knowingly supported them and hence it "amounted to sedition".

Kanhaiya and Khalid, who have earlier been arrested in Delhi on sedition charge, have also been booked again on the same charge.

Mr Goud had filed a complaint in the court of Metropolitan Magistrate here on Thursday, seeking its direction to police for registration of a case against Kanhaiya and Khalid for allegedly raising anti-India and pro-Afzal Guru slogans on JNU campus and others. 
</body>
</article>
</articles>
