<articles>
	<article>
		<title>
			As it happened: RS descends into chaos as Smriti Irani raises Mahishasura martyrdom day issue
		</title>
		<body>
			20:32 (IST)

Rajya Sabha adjourned

As the Mahishasura martyrdom day issue rocked the House, the Rajya Sabha was adjourned for the day.

20:31 (IST)

Mahishasura martyrdom day issue now disrupts Rajya Sabha

"I am compelled to read a few things," said Smriti Irani.

"There is an accusation that Mehmood ki topi Ahmed par hai. Pata nahi kiski topi kiske sar pe hai...main bina topi ke hoon," she said.

Irani then quoted a JNU document which, according to Irani's speech, said that "the execution of Afzal Guru was a nervous attempt by Congress."

"And it (the JNU document) also speaks about a public meeting that they have the right to hold a festival called Mahishasura martyrdom day," she said.

Irani then said that some minority students who were protesting against this festival were beaten up by Left-leaning JNU students.

"What is Mahishasura martyrdom day?" Irani said. She then again quoted the document.

"The document said that Durga Puja is a controversial, racist festival where a fair-skinned goddess is depicted killing a dark demon," Irani said.

She also said that document described Durga as a "sex worker called Durga who enticed Mahishasur into marriage. Every year, thousand of Durga puja pandals are erected showing her in a bad light, in a sexual position."

As soon as Irani finished reading this out, a huge uproar erupted in the Parliament.

"What is happening here? It is highly objectionable!" thundered Anand Sharma. "Tomorrow, if any of the ministers bring in any derogatory reference, what are we reducing this House to?"

20:16 (IST)

Irani counters charge of saffronisation of education

"There are many who have said that history is being distorted and all Sanghis are being put in ICHR," said Smriti Irani. She then pointed out that there was a member of ICHR who was not, in fact, a Sanghi. "If there was an intention to saffronise education, why would I pick a scholar who is not aligned to my organisation?" she said.

20:02 (IST)

"I am grateful for the anomalies which Azad sahab corrected in his speech today," Irani said.

20:02 (IST)

Uproar erupts in Rajya Sabha in the middle of Smriti Irani's speech

Opposition members began shouting as Smriti Irani tried responding to the allegations made against her.

19:56 (IST)

"What are we as a united House telling this generation of ours?" Irani said.

"Do we say to them that if you are a Dalit child belonging to an ideology not favourable to us, you can die for all we care?" she said.

Sitharam Yechury lashed out in the House and asked Smriti Irani to focus on the point at hand.

19:50 (IST)

Many can be accused of identifying Rohith as a vote bank: Smriti Irani

"I have been told not to get agitated," said Smriti Irani as she began her speech by quoting lines from Macbeth.

"I publicly pay homage to him. What I never publicly disclose that I also spoke to his mother," said Irani. "There are many who can be accused of identifying him as a vote bank," she said.

17:43 (IST)

We are undeterred by these attempts: Naidu

"Instead of running for photo opportunities, the political leadership should ponder over why incidents like the Rohith Vemula suicide happened. The entire country should think seriously. This is not the first case," Venkaiah Naidu said.

"The Prime Minister is very clear. The country has to go forward. We are undeterred by these attempts," Naidu said, as he targeted the Opposition over its criticism of the government.

17:36 (IST)

Don't express solidarity with divisive forces: Naidu

"We are only requesting you not to express solidarity with divisive forces," said Naidu.

17:33 (IST)

"We cannot tolerate such activities in our universities. We cannot allow the students to be influenced by fringe elements," said Venkaiah Naidu in Lok Sabha.

17:31 (IST)

Some people are eulogising Yakub Memon: Naidu in Lok Sabha

"In the Yakub Memon case, Supreme Court held a session in the middle of the night. Some people are eulogising Yakub Memon," Venkaiah Naidu said.

17:29 (IST)

Venkaiah Naidu takes a dig at Chidambaram over his remark on Afzal Guru

"A former Finance Minister has said that perhaps there are doubts about Afzal Guru's involvement in the Parliament attack," Naidu said. "Nobody has the right to say this after the Supreme Court verdict."

17:15 (IST)

Nobody has fought against the ultra Left like we have: Yechury

Before he was told by the Deputy Chairman to sit down, Sitharam Yechury said, "Nobody has fought against the ultra Left like we have."

17:12 (IST)

Don't camouflage this issue: Jaitley

"I would only urge this: The accused have been arrested. The investigations are on. The Home Minister has said the police will be more than fair. Please don't camouflage the offence which has taken place," said Jaitley.

"You should be more vigorous in speaking against terror than we are," the Finance Minister also told the Congress.

17:09 (IST)

Purpose of this debate is not to point fingers at each other: Anand Sharma to Jaitley

An angry Anand Sharma, in response to Jaitley accusing Opposition parties of supporting 'anti-nationals', said, "The purpose of this debate is not to deepen the fissures and point fingers at each other. Let's not distort the facts...Was the JNU faculty responsible for the anti-national slogans?"

17:07 (IST)

Should the police have remained a mute spectator while anti-national slogans were raised? asks Jaitley

"Without thinking, don't give respectability to those who talk about breaking the nation," said Jaitley. "Should the police remain a mute spectator if anti-national slogans are raised in the heart of India?" he added.

"I think the JNU is an integral part of India. And therefore, the Indian law applies. And if the Indian Penal Code is violated, the police has the right to enter the university," Jaitley said.

"The tragedy is not only that anti-national slogans were raised. It's also a tragedy that national parties were supporting those people," he said.

17:01 (IST)

At this point, Ghulam Nabi Azad interrupted and said, "The sedition charge should only be against those who did something wrong. Don't make this debate about who is anti-national."

17:00 (IST)

'Vandalism is condemnable but sedition is free speech?'

"Of course, what happened in Patiala House is condemnable. But vandalism is condemnable. And sedition is free speech?" said Jaitley.

"Vandalism is condemnable. But here's what the leftist philosophy is in this case: 'Let us concentrate on vandalism, which is condemnable. But at the same time, sedition must become a part of free speech.' Can hate speech become free speech?" he said.

"The question is: Does the Indian constitutional order allow this? To say that this kind of act must be ignored by the state is wrong. It is an issue over the geography and territory of India which is under attack today," he said.

16:53 (IST)

No academic freedom will ever be in peril in this country: Jaitley

"The pamphlet (at JNU) is more against the government which the UPA led. It said: 'Kashmir did not belong to Nehru. Nor does it belong to Manmohan or Modi.' All of the accused belong to an ultra-Left philosophy. I won't say anything against the accused because it might prejudice the trial against them," said the Finance Minister.

"Some other people came with masks. Maoists and separatists came to the event. And these people said, 'Kashmir ki azaadi tak, Bharat ki barbaadi tak jang chalegi jang chalegi.' What was the police supposed to do?" he said.

16:49 (IST)

Pamphlet at JNU event was titled 'a country without a post office': Jaitley

"Our fairness of the system was that not only did the accused (Afzal Guru) get a fair trial, but he also got several rounds of petitions with the Supreme Court. The system went out of the way to accommodate a person aganst whom there was a grave charge," Jaitley said.

"Can anyone say that his martyrdom should be celebrated? Let us be clear about the kind of functions that were organised in Hyderabad and JNU," he said. "The Congress has had a history of never supporting the fringe. Here is a group of people who call for this cultural programme on 9 February. The pamphlet was titled 'A country without a post office'...The pamphlet said the 'judicial killing' of Afzal Guru," he said.

16:40 (IST)

'Are we going to give respectability to those whose primary ideology is that they're going to break this country?'

"If some student belonging to a weaker section of society suffers mental distress, that issue has to be discussed," said Jaitley. "The core issue does not relate to the amount of academic license that exists," he said.

"Youngsters do many things and when they grow up, they realise they shouldn't have done many of those things," said the Finance Minister.

"Some amount of radical romancing can also take place in institutions," he said.

"But are we going to give respectability to those whose primary ideology is that they're going to break this country?" he said.

16:35 (IST)

We are missing or side-tracking the real issue: Jaitley

"Should we have universities where there is openness and freedom? Can there ever be an argument in a democracy like ours that there should be only one ideology?" Finance Minister Arun Jaitley said, in response to Ghulam Nabi Azad in Rajya Sabha.

"Let us settle this debate. Neither the NDA nor the UPA says only one idea must grow," Jaitley said. "We are entitled to be criticised. I have no difficulty with that," he added.

16:25 (IST)

They were supporting a terrorist at that university: Najma Heptulla

"This temple of democracy exists today because soldiers have given their lives for their nation," said Najma Heptulla, in response to Ghulam Nabi Azad's speech. "At that university (JNU), they were supporting a terrorist," she said.

16:22 (IST)

'Deal with those who actually made anti-national slogans in a different way'

"What is happening today is like a war. We are telling people some of them are more nationalist than others," Ghulam Nabi Azad said. "Deal with those who actually made anti-national slogans in a way different from those who did not make any anti-national slogans," he added.

"In the Patiala House court complex attack, the government was trying to save the BJP MLA," he further said. He also called for a House committee to probe this issue.

16:16 (IST)

Take action against those behind doctored videos: Ghulam Nabi Azad

"Action should be taken against those people behind the doctored videos who are trying to break the nation. Those are the people against whom a sedition case should be filed," Azad said. "And the media was encouraged by the ruling party to make these videos," he added.

Azad also mentioned the journalist who resigned from Zee News over this issue.

16:11 (IST)

Let there be a debate on nationalism, thunders Ghulam Nabi Azad in Parliament

"These institutions (like JNU) were made by organisations under Jawaharlal Nehru. And you are trying to ruin these institutions," said Azad.

16:07 (IST)

We don't have HRD Ministry's energy: Ghulam Nabi Azad

"We are explaining everything to you with a lot of love. Please don't react," said Ghulam Nabi Azad as the BJP MPs in the House began getting restless after his speech. "After all, we don't have the kind of energy which the HRD Ministry has," he added, after which even Smriti Irani erupted in laughter.

16:04 (IST)

'Why has ABVP come on the centre stage in Delhi?'

"The ruling party is making an issue out out of who is an anti-national and who is not. I want to tell them, 'Sheeshe ke mehel mein rehne waale doosron par pathar nahi pheka karte' (Those who live in glass palaces should not throw stones at others)," said Ghulam Nabi Azad.

16:00 (IST)

(Updates begin for 25 February)

Ghulam Nabi Azad criticises Smriti Irani over Rohith Vemula suicide issue in Rajya Sabha

"You can imagine how much the boy was harassed...He was called an anti-national and thrown out of college," Leader of Opposition in Rajya Sabha Ghulam Nabi said as he criticised HRD Minister Smriti Irani over the Rohith Vemula suicide issue.

20:02 (IST)

Dissussion on the suicide of Rohith Vemula and JNU row ends in Lok Sabha. Question Hour begins.

20:01 (IST)

Our govt believes JNU is a centre of excellence: Rajnath Singh

"Our government believes that JNU is a centre of excellence, not centre of ati-national activities," says Home Minister Rajnath Singh. 

"Under no circumstances police would be allowed harass any inncocent students. Regarding the incidents in the Patiala House Court the police has already upon it and I assure the House the guilty will given exemplary punishment," Singh said.  

19:58 (IST)

Meanwhile, students begin a rallying cry at JNU's administrative block. Slogans include: "Jo Kashmir hamara hai sara ka sara hai...Indian army zindbad," "Kashmir se le kar kanya kumari Bharat mata hai humari" and "Doodh mangoge to kheer denge...Kashmir mangoge tow cheer denge".

19:56 (IST)

Wish Rahul Gandhi helped me to tackle tensions in JNU, says Irani

"If we make education a battleground, if we make children vote banks then the country would be in the path of self-destruction. Had Rahul Gandhi requested me to accompany him to JNU and jointly appealed to the students to remember what nationalism is I would have happily gone. But he did not do that. My request is help me build this not destroy it from within," says Irani while concluding her speech. 

19:47 (IST)

19:42 (IST)

19:32 (IST)

JNU executive council not appointed by NDA, says Irani

"Executive council that ousted Rohith Vemula was appointed by UPA, not NDA," Smriti Irani tells Lok Sabha.

"I look at the poster of Rohith Vemula and think that he never knew that he was used," Irani says. 

She refers to a post on Mahisasur Martyrdom Day. It refers to Goddess Durga as "sex worker" who tricked Mahisasur, a dark skinned man and killed him later. 

"Is this freedom of speech? I want to know if Rahul Gandhi, Saugata Roy or Saugata Bose would like to discuss this freedom of speech. I fail to understand the depravity of these so-called students," the minister said pointing to the empty Congress benches as the largest party has staged a walkout.     

 

19:30 (IST)

19:09 (IST)

An angry Smriti Irani rises to speak; is she trying to fight off tears?

"I am disturbed by the fact some people are questioning my integrity as a minister. I have solved thousands of issues that have come to me in my capacity as a minister,” says a rather fiery looking Union HRD Minister Smriti Irani in Lok Sabha. 

She challenges Congress MP V Hanumantha Rao as to why he asked on what authority she wrote to the Hyderabad Central University. Irani shows all the letters that Rao as a MP addressed to the minister seeking her intervention in the HCU.

Uneasy prevails in the Opposition benches as the minister flashes letter after letter written by the parliamentarians seeking her intervention on different matters. From Kerala CM Oommen Chandy to former HRD minister and Congress leader Shashi Tharoor she spares none. 

"Today you are accusing me of biasness. Had I wanted to use the ocassion to put counter allegations I would have done that in the press conference I did the other day," Irani tells Lok Sabha. 

"Meri naam Smriti Irani hain. Meri jaati kya hain bataon," says a teary Irani in Lok Sabha. 

Allegations and counter-allegations fly between TRS MPs and the Union HRD minister.

"No doctor was permitted to go near Rohith Vemula. No attempt was made to revive the child. Even the police was allowed next morning. If the vertebrate does not break and even if the pulse falls down to 30 or 40 he can be revived. Who declared him dead?" says Irani.

"I am not certifying your idea of India. But do not demean mine," the minister says. 

 

 

 

18:52 (IST)

Point to ponder!

"Haathi ke daant khane ki aur, dikhane ki aur. Very well said by my friend Jyotiraditya Scindia. But I am confused if he was referring to the UPA or NDA?" says Anupriya Patel from Apna Dal.

18:36 (IST)

Where was your patriotism when PDP termed Afzal's hanging as travesty of justice? asks Asaduddin Owaisi 

"Where were you when the present Punjab CM burned down the Indian Constitution? Where were you when the PDP with whom you are partners in J&K said that the hanging of Afzal Guru was travesty of justice? Where was your patritism then? Whatever is happening in JNU is wrong. Had (Union Minister) Bandaru Dattatreya did not write that letter, had HRD Minister Smriti Irani not ordered action Rohith Vemula would have been alive," says All India Majlis-e-Ittehadul Muslimeen MP Asaduddin Owaisi. 

18:30 (IST)

18:29 (IST)

18:26 (IST)

Mr Rahul Gandhi. Are you serious?

Firstpost senior editor Akshaya Mishra says: Congress vice-president Rahul Gandhi says the BJP-led government won't allow him to speak because they are scared of what he will say. Well...well, want to have a smiley here but cannot find one. Actually, the Congress is doing rather well in the House debate even without him speaking. Jyotiraditya Scindia was quite impressive in his attack on the government. Seniors leaders sure would do fine given their experience in debating. So Rahul’s skills won’t be missed much. He should keep the powder dry for another day, another occasion. As for the government getting scared about what he might say, we are curious.   

18:22 (IST)

Remember our martyrs, says Venkaiah Naidu

"Who is innocent? Afzal Guru? Maqbul Bhat? Remember the jawans who gave their lives. If Kashmir is negotiable why should these people lay down their lives?" asks Union Minister Venkaiah Naidu in Lok Sabha.

18:19 (IST)

Some laughs in Lok Sabha after hours serious debate

Union Minister Venkaiah Naidu addresses the Chair as "Madam'' and suddenly stops finding Hukmdev Narayan Yadav in the Chair.

"Oh! Madam covert ho gaya. Sir, aa gaye," he quipped forcing the House into peels of laughter.

 

18:04 (IST)

We cannot compromise India, says Venkaiah Naidu

"Disappointed with many speakers again as many are trying to score political points.Since 2006 nine students apart from Rohith Vemula committed suicide in the Hyderabad Cenral University. The university administration should probe why this was happening? The main issue is what are the circumstances that forced these students to commit suicide," Naidu said while commenting on the Rohith Vemula suicide.

"It is wrong to connect the Rohith Vemula suicide with whatever happend in JNU. In JNU, Maoists have made entry into the campus but in a different form," he said.  

"Some of my colleagues without knowing what was happening in JNU went an expressed solidarity. They should have enquired before expressing solidarity. Who is Afzal Guru? Had the terrorists succeeded on that day none of us from this generation of parliamentarians would have been alive. I was in Parliament that day. Afzal Guru is a Pakistan backed terrorist," the minister said.

"We cannot compromise India," sais Naidu.

17:56 (IST)

When parliamentarians make you happy

Firstpost senior editor Akshaya Mishra says: We berate our parliamentarians too much. We keep complaining that they waste public money through pointless disruptions and they have no real concern for the country and its people. The fact is our parliamentarians can get serious about work when the situation demands. And contrary to the popular perception there’s a lot of knowledge and wisdom going around in both Houses. The debates, particularly those coming from senior leaders, make you sit and wonder, and pinch yourself. The back-benchers sometimes make you squirm though. When the front benches empty out and the back benchers replace them, would the quality of debate remain the same? The talent is yet to reveal itself.

17:54 (IST)

Sleepy already? Blame yourself

Firstpost senior editor Akshaya Mishra says: If the debate is making you feel sleepy don’t blame anyone. You choose to watch it and you always had the remote around. Don’t tell me you did not know beforehand what would be spoken in Parliament. Of course, you knew what the Congress is going to say and how the BJP would respond. You also have decided which side to take. What you wanted was some real, blistering action. It’s not happening. Come on, for that you need to go to theatre near you or perhaps a bar. Parliament is a place for sober, serious and life-changing debates. You are waiting for excitement in the wrong place. 

17:52 (IST)

If his background caused Rohith's death, we need to introspect: Chirag 

LJP MP from Jamui constituency in Bihar Chirag Kumar Paswan displays the corporate look and focusses on youth power in flawless Hindi. 

"If students from the JNU or any other university try to get their agenda in focus by indulging in anti-national activities then it should be dealt with sternly. My politics is completely different. I represent the sentiments of the students and not of any caste and creed," Paswan said in Lok Sabha. 

"Can anyone from this House say whatever happened with Rohith Vemula was correct? These are all sensitive matters and should be dealt with sensitivity. If Rohith's suicide happened due to his background then it is high time for us to introspect."

Is this the quote of the day?

"If the students fight it is a storm in the cup. Why do you react?"

Venkaiah Naidu intervenes

Union Minister Venkaiah Naidu intervenes and objects to branding of the entire JNU fraternity as anti-national by Palakkad MP from Kerala MB Rajesh in Lok Sabha.

"No fool on earth can brand the entire university as anti-national," Naidu said.  

"We want the university to flourish. There is no morphing of photographs. Those who are involved have changed their stand now," the minister said.


TRS MP Konda Vishwashrar Reddy

Speaking on the Rohith Vemula suicide TRS MP Konda Vishwashrar Reddy said, "Institutions have become insensitive. The VCs of Central universities say that they are not accountable to anybody but to the HRD ministry. This has to change. The autonomy of the insitutions are being destroyed. This happened during the last government's tenure as well. My constituency has become a hub of political tourism." 

The MP represents Chevella seat to which the deceased Rohith Vemula belonged. 

"Just as secularism cannot be patent of the Congress, nationalism cannot be patented to BJP. When two elephants fight, it is the grass which suffers. But we are not grass. We are the voice of this country."

Samajwadi Party chief Mulayam Singh Yadav

Participating in the debate on the JNU row, SP supremo Mulayam Singh Yadav said, "Leaders like Sitaram Yechury, Prakash Karat have passed out of the JNU. We cannot allow anti-national sloganeering in a prestigious university like the JNU. But we also should not harass innocent students."

"There should be a thorough investigation whether anti-national sloganeering or activities happened in the campus. If someone is found guilty, the person should be punished strictly
		</body>
	</article>
	<article>
		<title>
			JNU Row: Umar Khalid, Anirban Bhattacharya get 6 month bail, return to warm welcome
		</title>
		<body>
			New Delhi: A court here on Friday granted six months interim bail to JNU students Umar Khalid and Anirban Bhattacharya, arrested on charges of sedition, triggering celebrations in the varsity and a warm welcome when then two reached the campus in the late evening.

Meanwhile, Jawaharlal Nehru University Students Union president Kanhaiya Kumar, who had earlier been arrested on the same charges before being released on bail, said at the Indian Today conclave that Kashmir was an integral part of India and therefore Indians could discuss the issues pertaining to Kashmiris at any forum.
Umar Khalid. AFP

Umar Khalid. AFP

Granting Khalid and Bhattacharya bail, Additional Sessions Judge Reetesh Singh asked them to furnish a personal bond of Rs.25,000 with one surety of the like amount respectively, not to leave Delhi without the court's permission and to make themselves available before the investigating officer as and when required for the purpose of the probe.

Both had sought bail on the ground of "parity", Kanhaiya Kumar had already been granted interim bail by the Delhi High Court.

Granting six month interim bail to them on parityr, the court noted that there was no previous criminal record against them and "nothing has been brought on record which could indicate that they are likely to abscond from jurisdiction of the court".

"Although the allegations levelled against Umar Khalid and Anirban Bhattacharya are per se serious in nature, but as claimed by police themselves, the video footage of the incident has been sent to the forensic science laboratory. Its analysis and final report will certainty take some time," it added.

Delhi Police had opposed the bail plea saying their case was different from that of Kanhaiya Kumar as they were the organisers of a controversial event on the varsity campus on February 9 where anti-national slogans were raised. Both the students surrendered before police last month.

A case was registered against Khalid and Bhattacharya at the Vasant Kunj police station in south Delhi, soon after Kanhaiya was arrested on the same charges on February 12.

As the news reached the varsity, there were celebrations in the campus with students shouting slogans, putting gulal (colours) on each other's face and dancing.

Khalid and Bhattacharya reached the varsity campus here late in the evening to a spirited welcome.

Hundreds of their supporters gathered near the administrative block to celebrate their release. Kanhaiya Kumar and union vice president Shehla Rashid were among those raising slogans in their favour.

Around 250 people, including students and teachers, had earlier gathered at Ganga dhaba, close to the varsity's main gate to welcome them and then march with them in a procession towards the administration block, where an estimated 2,000 people were present in anticipation of speeches by Khalid and Bhattacharya.

JNU Teachers' Association president Ajay Patnaik was among those present.

Meanwhile, Kanhaiya Kumar said at the India Today conclave that there "is no doubt that Kashmir is an integral part of India. And since Kashmiris are Indians, we can always discuss their issues".

He denied supporting Kashmiri militant Afzal Guru, who was hanged for his role in the terror attack on the Indian parliament, but said he opposed capital punishment.

"Our protest (on February 9) was against capital punishment, not in support of Afzal," he said, adding that even if an ABVP activist was given capital punishment, he would oppose it.

Asked why he did not stop people from raising anti-India slogans at the JNU campus on February 9, he said neither he or nor his All India Students Federation (AISF) supported anti-India slogans or Kashmir's secession.

However, Bollywood actor Anupam Kher slammed the welcome to the two students.

"Only those can be considered as heroes who talk in favour of the country. How can they be hailed as heroes who talk against the country. Look how they (Khalid and Bhattacharya) are being greeted.. They haven't won some Olympic medal... They have been granted bail today," Kher said at in the varsity where his latest venture "Buddha in a traffic jam" was premiered.
		</body>
	</article>
	<article>
		<title>
			Beyond 'collective conscience': SC had deliberated on Afzal Guru's guilt in detail
		</title>
		<body>
			On Legal Assistance

Counsel for Afzal Guru said he was denied proper legal aid. He argued that counsel appointed by the court as amicus curiae was thrust on him against his will, that the first amicus made concessions without his knowledge, and the counsel who conducted the trial did not diligently cross-examine the witnesses. As such, Afzal’s right of legal aid flowing from Articles 21 (Protection of life and personal liberty) and 22 (Protection against arrest and detention in certain cases) was violated.

Court view: The Bench said it found “no substance in this contention”, and gave specific reasons for its view. It ruled that the trial judge had done his best to help Afzal with legal aid, and the counsel who defended him was not inexperienced, ineffective, or casual in his job. The court backed the High Court’s view that the criticism against the counsel appeared to be an afterthought raised at the appellate stage. It agreed that the appellant was without a lawyer from the time of his arrest until May 17, 2002, but said no proceedings besides the extending of remand and furnishing of documents had taken place during this period.

Watch video on the JNU row (App users click here)

On Afzal’s Confession

The Bench considered Afzal’s confessional statement to Delhi Police Special Cell ACP Rajbir Singh — who took over the investigation on December 19, 2001, the same day that POTA was brought against the accused — which detailed Afzal’s joining the JKLF in 1989-90, arms training in PoK, and subsequent return to India. According to the statement, he was motivated to join the jihad for Kashmir’s liberation by one Tariq of Anantnag, who also introduced him to proclaimed offender Ghazibaba, who, according to the confession, apprised him of the mission to carry out attacks on institutions like Parliament and embassies, and asked him to find a safe hideout for the fidayeen in Delhi. Afzal came to Delhi with Mohammed, one of the Jaish-e-Mohammad fidayeen, and on the night of December 12, he and co-accused Shaukat Guru and SAR Geelani visited the five Pakistani terrorists at their hideout. Mohammed told them about the plan to attack Parliament the following day, and gave Afzal Rs 10 lakh for Shaukat, Geelani and him, and a laptop to deliver to Ghazibaba. According to the confession, Afzal and Mohammed remained in touch, and on December 13, Afzal got a call on his mobile phone 98114-89429 from Mohammed’s phone 98106-93456 asking him to watch TV and inform him about the presence of VVIPs at Parliament House.

COURT VIEW: The court considered in detail the “crucial question… whether the confessional statement… could be safely acted upon”. It concluded that a delay by Afzal in refuting and retracting the confession could not in itself impart credibility to the confession. It also rejected the contention that inconsistencies in the grounds for Afzal to retract could give rise to “an inference that the confessional statement was true and voluntary”.

On Circumstantial Evidence

Circumstantial evidence against Afzal included the following: he knew the dead terrorists and identified their bodies; he was in frequent telephonic contact with the terrorist Mohammed, including three calls that the latter made to him minutes before the attack; the various locations used by the fidayeen in Delhi before the attacks; the various purchases made by them, including chemicals, dry fruit, a Yamaha motorcycle and mobile phones; and the laptop (along with its contents) that was found in Afzal’s custody.

COURT VIEW: The court said these circumstances clearly established Afzal’s association with the terrorists “in almost every act done by them in order to achieve the objective of attacking the Parliament House”. “Short of participating in the actual attack,” Afzal, the court said, “did everything to set in motion the diabolic mission”.

The Verdict

“The gravity of the crime… is something which cannot be described in words. The incident, which resulted in heavy casualties, had shaken the entire nation and the collective conscience of the society will only be satisfied if the capital punishment is awarded to the offender. The challenge to the unity, integrity and sovereignty of India… can only be compensated by giving the maximum punishment… The appellant, who is a surrendered militant and who was bent upon repeating the acts of treason against the nation, is a menace to the society and his life should become extinct. Accordingly, we uphold the death sentence.”

CRIME & PUNISHMENT

Dec 13, 2001: Five terrorists enter Parliament House complex and open indiscriminate fire, killing nine people and injuring over 15

Dec 15, 2001: Delhi Police pick up Afzal Guru from Jammu & Kashmir. SAR Geelani of Delhi University’s Zakir Husain College is picked up and later arrested. Two others, Afsan Guru and her husband Shaukat Hussain Guru, picked up later

Jun 4, 2002: Charges framed against Afzal Guru, Geelani, Shaukat Hussain Guru and Afsan

Dec 18, 2002: Trial court sentences Afzal, Geelani and Shaukat to death, lets off Afsan

Aug 30, 2003: Jaish-e-Mohammad leader Ghazi Baba, prime accused in the attack, is killed in an encounter with the BSF in Srinagar. Three other militants too are killed in the encounter

Oct 29, 2003: Delhi High Court uphold death for Afzal, acquits Geelani

Aug 4, 2005: Supreme Court confirms death for Afzal, commutes Shaukat’s sentence to 10 years’ rigorous imprisonment

Sep 26, 2006: Delhi court orders Afzal to be hanged

Oct 3, 2006: Afzal’s wife Tabasum Guru files a mercy petition with President APJ Abdul Kalam

Jan 12, 2007: Supreme Court dismisses Afzal’s plea seeking review of his death sentence, saying “there is no merit” in it

May 19, 2010: Delhi government endorses capital punishment awarded to Afzal by the Supreme Court

Dec 30, 2010: Shaukat Guru released from Delhi’s Tihar Jail

Dec 10, 2012: Home Minister Sushilkumar Shinde says he would examine Afzal Guru’s file after Parliament’s winter session concludes on December 22

Feb 3, 2013: President Pranab Mukherjee rejects Afzal Guru’s mercy petition

Feb 9, 2013: Afzal Guru hanged
— Based on Supreme Court judgment delivered on Aug 4, 2005, upholding the death sentence for Afzal Guru
 711  89
 
</body>
	</article>
	<article>
		<title>
			'Intolerance' comments taken out of context: Aamir Khan 'never wants to leave India'
		</title>
		<body>
			Bollywood star Aamir Khan says his statements on 'intolerance' last year which stirred more zing into an existing storm may have been taken out of context. At an awards night last year, Aamir Khan spoke about how his wife Kiran shared her worry about status quo in India and his quotes from that evening went on to roil the winter session of Parliament and never really died down.
Aamir Khan clarifies

Aamir Khan clarifies

Most recently, Amitabh Bachchan has replaced Aamir Khan as the brand ambassador of the Incredible India campaign.

Speaking at the 10 anniversary of “Rang De Basanti”, Aamir Khan attempted to clarify his statements on “growing intolerance”, reports The Indian Express.

“Some could understand me and some couldn’t. And those who are hurt, I can understand their feelings. I would have been hurt had I been in their place because they were told something that was not true,” Aamir Khan said.

Khan said his comments were taken out of context.

"I was hurt and along with me many people have been hurt because of this misunderstanding. I give this credit to you all (media) because you all have twisted my words. I request you all that please don't do this," Aamir said.

“Our country is a beautiful example of unity in diversity. Take my family for instance. My wife is Hindu. My two sisters are married to Hindus — Farhat is married to Rajeev while Nikhat to Santosh. My cousin Mansoor Khan has married a Catholic. I have three kids and they are half-Hindu and half-Muslim,” he said. “Both Kiran and I never bring our religions into the picture. I am an Indian first and always will be an Indian,” Khan said.

“Let me tell you that I never said that. I was born in India and I will die in India. I never thought about leaving the country. Neither Kiran nor will I think about it. In fact when I stay away from the country for two weeks I get homesick,” The Indian Express quotes Aamir as saying.

Aamir says his statement was not a generalization but more specifically certain people who are polarizing opinion one way or the other.

“Our Prime Minister has said unity is our strength and that one shouldn’t spread poison. I love my country and people who are spreading negativity, I with folded hands ask them not to do not. Unity in diversity is our main aim,” said Aamir.

“Why should I do Satyamev Jayate? It’s because I love my country. I feel happy that I am lending a hand in nation building. I belong to a freedom fighter’s family. My great grand uncle is Maulana Abul Kalam Azad,” he said.

Barely a week ago, senior bureaucrat Amitabh Kant, a key driver of the Incredible India campaign during his stint in the Ministry of Tourism, took a swipe at actor Aamir Khan saying that he is damaging India's brand image when he calls India "intolerant".

After speaking to television channels in Ahmedabad, Kant reportedly repeated his statement on Twitter Tuesday. “Being a Brand Ambassador imposes responsibilities. U can’t run down what u’re promoting. That’s damaging d brand,” he tweeted, reports The Indian Express.

Kant referred to Khan’s remarks at the Ramnath Goenka Awards night last November where Aamir Khan had said: “(Wife) Kiran and I have lived all our lives in India. For the first time, she said, should we move out of India? That’s a disastrous and big statement for Kiran to make to me. She fears for her child.

She fears about what the atmosphere around us will be. She feels scared to open the newspapers everyday. That does indicate that there is a sense of growing disquiet.”

“A brand ambassador must be the best ambassador for promoting and marketing India, he cannot be the destroyer of the brand… If the brand ambassador of India promotes it as Incredible India, then people will come here for sightseeing and tourist inflow will increase. But if the brand ambassador of Incredible India says that India is intolerant, then he is not working as the brand ambassador, he is damaging the brand entity of the nation, then people won’t come here,” Kant
		</body>
	</article>
	<article>
		<title>
			Incredible Intolerance? Debate rages on after Aamir Khan is 'purged' from tourism campaign
		</title>
		<body>
			Aamir Khan is no longer the brand ambassador of the government's 'Incredible India' campaign.

And the decision has ruffled some feathers.

But, consider this: The government has a contract with an agency. In due course of time, the contract has expired. So what does the government do?

a) Unilaterally, arbitrarily extend the contract with the said agency in violation of its own rules and regulations?
b) Float a tender for a new contract?

Too easy. The answer is option B, right? Wrong.
Aamir Khan in a file photo. AFP

Aamir Khan in a file photo. AFP

According to India's card-carrying "liberal" brigade and the Indian National Congress that has a copyright on secularism, the Centre should have flouted its own rules and continued with Aamir as the brand ambassador for its Incredible India campaign.

Incredible!

As we all know, scratching not only provides relief from an itch but also induces a pleasurable sensation. Scientists who have examined our brain activity tell us that there is an award system associated with scratching. That may explain why our "liberals" find such pleasure in periodically scratching the 'intolerance' carbuncle.

They seemingly have a special 'intolerance sensor' that gets triggered automatically when encountered with a perceived act of intolerance.

But the problem lies in the fact that this extra-sensory organ works only in select cases where our "liberals" think they have a stick with which to beat Narendra Modi and his government. Did the government ask the advertising agency, McCann Worldgroup, to remove Khan before the expiry of his contract? Did the Centre discontinue the agency's service midway through the contract?

Not even the ad agency is saying so.

According to ministry officials, the government didn't even deal directly with Khan. The contract was between the actor and Prasoon Joshi's agency. So where is the question of "dropping him" when he wasn't even hired by the government in the first place?

The Centre, of course, could have handled the issue a lot better instead of appearing to speak in many voices that gave rise to speculation. But it is interesting that a routine, non-controversial, perfectly legit move has suddenly become 'controversial'. It is apparently indicative of the "intolerance wave that is sweeping the country", a perception that is unsupported by data and loosely bandied about in the echo-chambers of Indian "liberal" corridors.

Congress's Randeep Surjewala, chief of the communication department, believes the latest decision to "purge" Khan from Incredible India campaign is a reflection of "continued intolerance" being practiced by the BJP-led government.

His statement is truly incredible.

Not only does it reflect the Congress' casual attitude towards the rulebook, but the statement also seeks to gloss over instances of real intolerance shown by his party when in power.

During the Emergency, Congressman VC Shukla, the then Information and Broadcasting minister, banned Kishore Kumar's songs from All India Radio and Doordarshan because the singer once refused to perform at a Congress rally in Mumbai.

In 2004, the UPA government removed Anupam Kher as the censor board chief at the behest of CPI(M) general secretary Harkishan Singh Surjeet as part of a 'desaffronisation' drive.

Even if, for arguments' sake, we consider that the government has decided to "discontinue" with Aamir Khan's services, as the actor put it on Thursday, it isn't an unheard-of move. The relationship between brands and brand ambassadors isn't cast in stone. Celebrity endorsements are subject to variable conditions and ambassadors are often dropped from campaigns for strategic reasons.

The Indian Air Force, for instance, has dropped cricket legend Sachin Tendulkar as its brand ambassador.

L'Oreal Paris dropped Aishwarya Rai and replaced her with Freida Pinto instead.

Nike, the US sportswear giant, has said it will drop Real Madrid superstar Cristiano Ronaldo in favour of Barcelona striker Neymar Jr.

In fact, Amitabh Bachchan, who is touted to be the frontrunner as Aamir's replacement, was dropped as brand ambassador for the International Indian Film Academy (IIFA) Awards.

So while you consider the mischievousness of the phony intolerance debate, consider this: Would Coca Cola have persisted with Aamir Khan as its celebrity endorser had the actor revealed in a public statement that he and his family members dislike Coke and drink Pepsi at home
		</body>
	</article>
	<article>
		<title>
			India is good again! Aamir Khan comments on intolerance debate after it's been done and dusted
		</title>
		<body>
			One early morning last week, on the way to the airport, I received this shared message on my mobile phone that read:

‘The Bihar results came out on 8 November. Today is 21 November. In the two weeks, not one award has been returned, there has been no controversy over any religious commitments, no talks about beef or any other kind of meat anymore. No one is rioting, no one is screaming intolerance, and there is peace in India. We are now discussing pay commissions and other routine stuff. Just sit back and think how the media and Congress manipulated the minds of the nation in the run up to the elections over those six weeks. Good to see that India has once again magically become tolerant and secular."

While this might be a bit too clever and the sudden absence of hostility in the air could well be due to public indifference or exhaustion with the subjects (after all, look how the reaction to the arrest of Peter Mukherjea pales in comparison that of Indrani, his wife) the thought that mass communications can be used as a mechanism to create an atmosphere for or against an individual, an institution or even an event, will not disappear.

Yes, it’s not just WhatsApp chatter. That thought did come to my mind, even before that viral message. It must have crossed your mind, too. Where is the intolerance debate? We did hear Aamir Khan refer to it on Monday, but he hardly made a ripple on the electronic waves. (Ed--This article was first published early morning on November 24. Subsequently, through the day, Aamir did rule the waves). He said that at the peak of the intolerance debate his wife Kiran asked him if they should leave India, suggesting that we are good again as a country.
File image of Aamir Khan and Kiran Rao. Reuters

File image of Aamir Khan and Kiran Rao. Reuters

Simple as that?

In a chapter by American journalist John Perry on the power of ‘Masscomm’ to generate and feed a mob mentality, the possibility of this mobile message being a reality finds some credence... or at least, a pause for thought.

He writes of an American election in which the two-party system’s candidates are manufactured out of cardboard and smoke and mirrors and sculpted by the media. The gap between what they are and what is projected is made irrelevant.

“Newspaper chains, the clutter of segmented magazines, motion picture studios, television channels, even the cacophony of music and radio and TV anchors, the innumerable channels, the Internet providers, the smart phones, the endless inescapable presence of news and opinion outlets, including social media of every imaginable stripe and stain.... they make for a massive machine to brainwash the human mind. Masscomm gives any innovation the green signal or junks it. It promotes harmony or encourages backdoor rage and suspicion. It determines who will win and who will lose… In the age of Masscomm, the new President of the United States will be ‘printed’ out by Masscom, he will be an unreal alien whose persona will be totally scripted."

Not possible? Why not? As technology advances thought becomes submissive and subjugated. Add to the social media platforms the froth and boil brought to an issue by the thousands of trolls who use the veneer of anonymity to foment rage, fury and venom with so much dedication that they add to the image or detract from it.

If enough trolls are put on the job to create a mural and throw upon it lashings of vividly poisonous colour, you will end up with a canvas in prejudice.

So, let’s take the Bihar elections and scan them under the lens of Masscom Unlimited.

An entity decides that it will finance a campaign that is inimical to the BJP.

The money is spent creating a high-octane sense of fear which is predicated entirely to communal suspicion as being the one issue guaranteed to ignite passion in a country where even rapists get a free pass.

Gradually, in incremental steps the pressure is increased and the target audience fed a certain diet drenched in bigotry. Every incident is magnified into a nationwide epidemic. The unwitting media is signposted and led like sheep to the scenes of the crimes. The atmosphere is seeded with doubt and fear. The ‘them’ and ‘us’ divide is pulled apart and everyone, regardless of colour or creed, begins to  believe they are under threat.

After a volley of half lies comes the second part. A thousand individuals, much like a call centre, are co-opted to begin trolling canned and homogenised hatred. They feed websites and social media platforms with endless programming against a specific individual... in this case, Prime Minister Narendra Modi himself.

In the beginning there are few takers for the aggressive campaign. But with every display of synthetic evidence in the truth ‘window’, disbelief begins to melt like a heated candle. The ill wind is blowing support into the sails.

By the time the BJP realises there is a campaign out there bedrocked in communalism, intolerance, posturing and negative media publicity, it joins the race and tries to play catch up.

If you stay within the parameters of the Perry paradigm the prey has fallen for the trap. It is on the defensive and tries to counter the poisoned arrows flung at it. The Machiavellian mind behind the the whole plot wants exactly this. The lead is so vast he knows they can never catch up so he takes each feeble defence tactic from the BJP, who cannot understand what has hit them and twists it into an indictment.

Look at them! Anti-Dalit. Anti-Muslim. Even anti-Hindu. Anti-Bihar.

In its panic, the BJP frontline feeds the frenzy by being clumsy and giving ammunition to the plotters. Its frontline motormouths make stupid knee-jerk comments. This is normal human nature in that when you do not know what has hit you, what you do is strike back without any plan — just flailing in the dark. These comments balloon into major indictments. The trolls across the board are pushed into action, to turn these indictments into hardcore watertight evidence of the BJP’s perfidy.

Perry explains the most dramatic way to exploit those now playing on the back foot to a bouncer: Their honesty must be interpreted as heresy, as a dangerous deviation that must be discredited, then damned, then destroyed.

Did Bihar follow this road map? Everyone of us has to come to his or her own conclusion. The interesting element is that it could be we are reduced to zombies in an experiment in social psychology and behaviour.

Lemmings follow each other over the cliff. Humans do the same.

This is where it gets intricate. The battle is over. It has been won by parochialism and plan, however diabolical.

The election is over and the crimson tide rolls back. Suddenly, there is peace in the valley and normality has returned. Is this a coincidence? Will Masscomm continue to rule and choose our leaders by controlling our decisions in the future by telling us how and what we should think?

Possible? Probable? Already happening.
		</body>
	</article>
	<article>
		<title>
			Stray incidents do not mean there is intolerance in India, says Jaitley
		</title>
		<body>
			There could be "stray" incidents of people on either side of the political spectrum making irresponsible statements but this could not be generalised as prevalence of a climate of intolerance in the country, Union Minister Arun Jaitley has said.

The Finance Minister is currently on a week-long tour of the US primarily to attend the annual Spring meeting of the International Monetary Fund and the World Bank.
Finance Minister Arun Jaitley.

Finance Minister Arun Jaitley.

Dubbing such incidents as "terrible", the senior BJP leader, however, said that they are "rare" in a large country like India.

"There could be stray incidents of irresponsible statements by individuals on either side of the political spectrum, that does not mean that zamin per koi iss tarah ki activity hai (intolerance exists)," Jaitley said during a media roundtable with Indian reporters here.

"These are bad incidents. These are terrible incidents, but these are extremely rare in a large country. Historically stray incidents have taken place," he said when his attention was drawn towards some of the specific such incidents.

Responding to a question on alleged prevalence of intolerance in the country, Jaitley described this as a creation of media.

"On the ground, my own understanding of the subject is, are there a lot of things happening that show this (intolerance)? The answer is no.

"There could be in a large country like India some incident or the other, which takes place one time, which could be considered highly improper and condemnable," he said.

When asked if there is any introspection within the party, he said: "Actually neither in the party agenda nor on the ground there is any such activity wherein in a large country like India it (incidents of intolerance) is happening state after state."

"A news channel can show same four people giving irresponsible statements and build a story around it. That seems to be more of what is happening.

"What gets projected is in a large body of politics there would always be three or four people who would react aggressively and disproportionally to events," he observed.

"So loose comments, loose statements, improper statements, when the television camera confronts you, you say what you should not say, aise char, panch, chhe log hai (there are four, five, six such people), usko aap environment of intolerance kah do? (and you describe them as an environment of intolerance)?" the minister asked.

He also had the annual India US Economic and Financial Dialogue on Thursday and bilateral meetings with his counterparts from China, Luxembourg and Bangladesh.

Over the weekend, he would travel to New York to interact with the business community there and address a meeting at the United Nations.
		</body>
	</article>

	<article>
		<title>
			Uday Prakash, poet who touched off award-wapsi tsunami, slammed for praising PM Modi’s speech
		</title>
		<body>
			“The speech given by our Prime Minister Narendra Modi today in Parliament on Constitution has importance of a historical inscription, an important stately document. I have not heard in my life such a democratic, inclusive, liberal and polite speech in my life, at least in such an effective manner. He spoke without any bias, so transparently accepted contributions of public leaders who preceded him and the way he praised nation’s first Prime Minister’s democratic tolerance, honesty and argumentative maturity. Besides the way he gave his acceptance and support to the original preamble as also to later amendment, which included secular, socialist and talked about need for reservations, he transcended boundaries of ruling and opposition benches, will go a long way in establishing him as a unanimously accepted statesman with all its emotive connotations.”
Image courtesy: Facebook page

Uday Prakash. Image courtesy: Facebook page

These words are not from a Modi bhakt. This is the opening paragraph of a Facebook post by Uday Prakash, noted poet and writer who had recently hit the headlines for being the first to return his Sahitya Akademi award on 3 September, a move which sparked off the raging “intolerance” debate in the country.

Uday Prakash had returned his award three days after the killing of famous Vachna Sahitya scholar MM Kalburgi. What subsequently followed was award-wapsi charade with a political overtone – read a movement against the Modi government for rising intolerance during his 16-month regime at the Centre.

But see the irony of being Uday Prakash! If he was criticised and called names then (when he publicly returned his award) by Right wingers and hailed by liberals and Left wingers, today he is accused of being “sold out to Modi” and attacked by those who till the other day considered him a hero. The author, however, is keeping his cool and not getting carried away by either category of responses.

Has Uday Prakash changed sides by hailing Modi’s statesmanship? Not really. He says he writes and speaks what he thinks is correct and is not guided by any bias or motivated thoughts and opinions. Speaking to Firstpost, Prakash said he was not a political person.

“I am a writer and express through words what I feel. When I had returned Sahitya Academy award, I had not discussed about it with anyone. I was agitated because there was no reaction from the Sahitya Academy on Kalburgi’s killing. The least which the Sahitya Academy could do, something which is practiced in armed forces, that the chief and the institution give dignity and honour to the departed. They go and console the bereaved family and stand by them in their difficult moments.

“Sahitya Academy did nothing to console Kalburgi’s family or something that could posthumously honour him. But when I gave vent to my feelings I was criticised and targeted by sections of people. I had no idea that the whole thing would turn into a political debate.

“I am being targeted again when I expressed my feeling by writing on Facebook on Modi’s November 27 speech in Parliament. Art and literature should not be analysed from perspective of religion or politics. I genuinely felt Modi that day delivered a great speech. We live in an age, which is speech-centric and speeches define course of events”, he said.

The day Modi had delivered his speech Firstpost had noted that his speech was statesmanlike and had responded to the three accusations made by his political rivals and critics.

Uday Prakash says in his Facebook post he had said it before and would repeat it again that Modi has gone several steps ahead of maestro Atal Bihari Vajpayee in oratory. Despite some factual and funny mistakes on facts relating to history, time and place, he is by far the best orator prime minister that the country has seen. In one stroke he distanced himself from the partisan speeches given by Rajnath Singh and Arun Jaitley. His speech is to respect the diversity and multiplicity of faiths and values that represent India.

Like several other political analysts and commentators, he too has his concern about longevity of spirit of the message which Modi tried to deliver – is it guided by compulsions of parliamentary number imbalance of GST or by the receding graph of BJP’s image due to irresponsible statements made by his party and Sangh Parivar leaders?

Modi surely has succeeded sending a message that he can stand tall as a statesman, leader of the country. It’s also time for him to show through his deeds that he means what he says. His government, party and ideological Parivar will have to internalise the messages that he gave while commemorating 125th birth anniversary BR Ambedkar.

There is thus a need to dispassionately see Uday Prakash’s passionate writing on the issue.
		</body>
	</article>
	<article>
		<title>
			Returning an award will not solve the problem: Kareena Kapoor Khan
		</title>
		<body>
			Kareena Kapoor Khan has disapproved of the trend of writers and filmmakers returning their awards to protest “growing intolerance in the country” and advised them to instead address the issues bothering them.

“Returning an award would not solve any problem. We should learn to address the issue (of intolerance) rather that getting it upon ourselves. It is not a personal issue, it is the issue of entire nation,” she said in a press meet today.
Courtesy: ibn live

Kareena Kapoor Khan. Courtesy: ibn live

The Bajrangi Bhaijaan star said she was inspired by the firm stand taken by youths on issues facing the country. “I haven’t returned any awards. But whatever is going on (in the country), the retaliation of youths (over different issues) that is what really inspired me,” the 35-year-old said when asked to comment on filmmakers returning awards to protest “rising intolerance” under the present Government.

Kareena was in Raipur to take part in a series of programmes based on children organised by Unicef, School Education and Women and Child Development Departments of Chhattisgarh Government. The popular star is Unicef India’s “celebrity advocate” for education. She also appreciated the efforts of Unicef and State Government to promote education among children, especially those residing in the remote areas of Chhattisgarh.

Earlier, addressing a programme held to mark the culmination of Child Right Convention Week, Kareena stressed on improving the standard of education and simultaneously increasing enrolment of students in schools. “Though enrolment of students in schools has increased significantly, quality education is still an issue of concern. Ensuring quality education to every child is one of the major challenges before us.”

Quality education and advanced learning techniques in a school can collectively ensure progress of a child to attain a better future, she added. Kareena also advocated for facilities like separate toilets for girls in schools, availability of clean drinking water for students and improving access to schools.

On the occasion, Chief Minister Raman Singh launched a mobile mobile-cum web-based application `CG Edutrack’ jointly developed by Unicef and School Education Department.
		</body>
	</article>
	<article>
		<title>
			Award wapsi to defame India: Anupam Kher leads march against intolerance protests
		</title>
		<body>
			New Delhi: Countering the protests by writers and artistes against "rising intolerance", Bollywood actor Anupam Kher on Saturday led a march to Rashtrapati Bhavan alleging that the "award-wapsi" campaign was to defame the country by projecting a "wrong" picture of the situation.

"India is a very tolerant country. Some people have coined the term 'growing intolerance'. They are very few. Not every Indian thinks like that. We are secular people. We do not believe in pseudo-secularism, selective outrage or selective patriotism," Kher, who is the spouse of BJP MP from Chandigarh Kirron Kher, told reporters.
Anupam Kher. PTI

Anupam Kher. PTI

"We had a meeting with a lot of writers, artistes, filmmakers and they also believe that there is no intolerance in the country... This march is a symbolic gesture on part of a lot of people over here who say India is one and free of intolerance," the 60-year-old said.

Many filmmakers and artistes from the fraternity including Madhur Bhandarkar, Ashoke Pandit, Priyadarshan, Manoj Joshi, Abhijeet Bhattacharya and writer Madhu Kishwar joined the march to hand over a memorandum signed by more than 40 personalities including actress Raveena Tandon to President Pranab Mukherjee.

Bhandarkar, a National Award winner, alleged that those involved in the protest over intolerance had opposed Prime Minister Narendra Modi before he was elected, which raised questions about their intention.

"The projection that is happening for the past few days is very sad. The people who were against Modiji during elections are the same people who are coming out right now.

"The whole projection and narrative that is going abroad is wrong. It is a diverse country and of course there are incidents but we all condemn them. There is no two ways about it," he said.

Kher asserted that they were not associated with any organisation or political party. "This march is led by Indians and for Indians."

Film-maker Priyadarshan said the act of returning the awards is "childish".

"People returning awards are doing a childish act. They should use the power of pen. Instances of intolerance have always been there. It is not something that happened yesterday. Shah Rukh Khan never said he is returning award," Priyadarshan told PTI.

"They are respected people but behaving like school children," Priyadarshan said.

He, however, disapproved of those critical of Khan who had said that there was extreme intolerance in the country.

At least 75 members of the intelligentsia have returned national or literary awards in an escalation of protests by writers, historians, filmmakers and scientists over "growing intolerance", voicing fears that the country's robust democracy might be "coming apart" in the current atmosphere.


		</body>
	</article>
	<article>
		<title>
			Delhi HC seeks Centre's reply on plea claiming award wapsi 'tarnishing India's image'
		</title>
		<body>
			The Delhi High Court on Wednesday sought a response from the Centre on a plea seeking a direction to frame guidelines that if Sahitya Akademi awardees return their awards, they should also return the prize money and royalties they may have earned through sale of their books.

A bench of Chief Justice G Rohini and Justice Jayant Nath also issued notices to the Ministry of Tourism and Culture and
Sahitya Akademi and sought their replies before 15 February on plea which contended that the "action of returning awards has the effect of tarnishing India's image".

The court was hearing a public interest litigation (PIL), filed by advocate Haji Mohammad Majid Qureshi and a religious
organisation, which said "the present system whereby writers are allowed to retain royalties earned by them through sale of copies of their books despite returning the award is arbitrary and illogical."
Sahitya Akademi. Representational Image. IBNlive

Sahitya Akademi. Representational Image. IBNlive

While mentioning the name of eight persons, including writer Nayantara Sahgal, who have returned their awards recently, the petition sought a direction to the ministry and Sahitya Akademi to frame guidelines with respect to the award instituted by the respondents with retrospective effect.

"..So that reasonable remedial action can be taken against such authors who impair the country's dignity," the plea said.

It further said that this plea was to ensure that strong punitive action is taken against those who return such awards
as Sahitya Akademi Puraskar, a solemn token of appreciation conferred upon deserving writers on behalf of the Indian
public.

Several writers, poets and artists had recently returned their awards protesting against the Akademi's "silence" on the
murder of fellow writer and Sahitya Akademi board member M M Kalburgi as well as against the atmosphere of "intolerance and communalism" in the backdrop of the Dadri lynching incident.
		</body>
	</article>	
	<article>
		<title>
			Beef ban extremism in Dadri: Someone’s dinner is now part of a criminal probe
		</title>
		<body>
			The rumour of beef and pig tallow greasing cartridges is supposed to have spawned what the British called the Indian mutiny. That was 1857.

Now in 2015 rumours of eating beef can get you killed.

The Indian Express story about a 50-year-old man beaten to death and his son critically injured in UP’s Dadri after rumours spread that they were eating and storing beef has divided us on predictable lines.
Representational image. AFP image

Representational image. AFP image

Folks on one side see this as another sign of growing intolerance towards minorities in the acchey din India of Narendra Modi. Those on the other side see it as another case of selective outrage because it’s not like such incidents have not happened in pre-Modi India. If a Dalit and Muslim were stripped for skinning and eating a cow in Karnataka allegedly by Bajrang Dal activists in 2008 did anyone point fingers at the UPA sarkar?

What’s lost in the din is the essential point in the story. Whether it happened before in 2006 or 2008 or 2015, someone has died because someone else did not like the food they ate.

The most poignant part of the entire story was this excerpt.

Akhlaq’s daughter, Sajida, said the family had “mutton in the fridge” and not beef. "Can they bring my father back if it turns out it was not beef?"

Cow slaughter is banned in UP but that someone needs to say this, in order to plead for their lives, is what is truly shocking, truly horrendous.

“We have collected meat samples from Akhlaq’s house and sent it to the forensics department for examination,” said the Senior SSP Kiran S to IE.

Someone’s dinner is now part of a criminal investigation. That is the reality that cannot be captured in the language of a law that bans the slaughter of a particular animal or puts limitations on it.

This is not about whether this is a new phenomenon or an old fault line. As Akhilesh Yadav is the chief minister this is his faultline now. As Narendra Modi is the prime minister it is his faultline. Not what happened in Dadri per se but the larger polarization happening around food as a way of defining the “other”. It does not matter if this polarization is an old one. It does not matter if it’s not really part of a great conspiracy. This is now something he has to grapple with.

Narendra Modi also knows that his party is held to higher scrutiny and will always be when it comes to minority issues because it is perceived as a Hindu nationalist party. The Congress too would be held to higher scrutiny by its opponents when it came to accusations of pandering to minorities as Rajiv Gandhi found out with the Shah Bano case. That is why something a group of Bajrang Dal activists did in 2008 is viewed differently than what the same group does in 2015. The accusation, which the PM has to constantly guard against, is that his being in power at the centre has emboldened these groups. The fringe thinks it has impunity now.

That might be a blatant falsehood but the PM has done little to squelch these accusations. He has mostly just ignored the issue. When Obama was accused of following a church leader alleged to have extreme views he came forward to confront the touchy issue of race head-on in a speech that could not have been easy for him. That is precisely what an Arun Shourie was getting at when he told Karan Thapar “If Modi tweets on Sania Mirza’s victory and wishing on somebody’s birthday and then he doesn’t say a word on critical issues like Ghar Wapsi, Churches and Love Jihad, it will draw an inference." The PM says saracastically that children welcome him by reciting Sanskrit shlokas in Ireland but it would have raised questions about “secularism” if it had been done in India. But when food bans actually test our ideas of secularism, the PM is conspicuously silent. The silence does not douse flames, it fans conspiracy theories.

That silence is interpreted as loaded because as Mukul Kesavan has pointed out in The Telegraph, while the BJP election manifesto consigned Ram Mandir to Page 41, Modi on the election trail gives speeches that press religious hot buttons.

"In Bihar, Modi made speeches where he re-mixed the cow-slaughter theme song under a new title, the ‘Pink Revolution’. The lyrics of his cover version went like this: the Congress government had subsidized cow-slaughter, butchers had grown rich on the back of meat exports, did Yadavs really want to make common cause with people who killed the sacred cow?"

The story is not about timelines and tu tu main main. The Maharashtra cow slaughter ban might date back to 1976 but extending the ban to bulls and bullocks happened under Devendra Fadnavis’ watch. Jammu and Kashmir’s cow slaughter ban dates back to 1932 even though it was rarely enforced but because a high court orders enforcement now, it’s the current government’s problem.

Indulging in a fight about dates really dodges the main issue. And it bears repeating. Even as the Prime Minister wows Silicon Valley with his vision of a digital India of superfast i-ways and connected villages and farmers on WhatsApp, someone has been killed because a mob did not like what they thought he was eating.

That should be hard to digest for all of us.
		</body>
	</article>	
	<article>
		<title>
			Beef ban deepens Maharashtra rural distress, farmers have a beef with PM Modi's BJP
		</title>
		<body>
			A ban on the sale of cattle for slaughter in India's richest state is threatening to push millions of farmers into penury, deepening distress in the countryside and fanning resentment against Prime Minister Narendra Modi's ruling party.

Slaughter of cows, considered sacred in Hinduism, has historically been banned in most states but was rarely enforced in India, the world's largest exporter of beef.

But over the past year, states ruled by Modi's Bharatiya Janata Party (BJP), such as Maharashtra, have broadened the ban to include other types of cattle, like bulls and bullocks, and Hindu vigilantes have stepped up attacks on traders to enforce the prohibition.
Reuters

Reuters

The stricter rules come as Modi and the nationalist BJP lay greater stress on India's Hindu faith, to which the majority of the population belongs. Minority groups, including around 180 million Muslims, have expressed concern over the implications.

The impact of the beef ban has been significant. Prices of cattle have fallen across the country, India's meat exports fell 13 percent in the April-December period and rival beef supplier Brazil is gaining from India's loss.

It has also left millions of farmers, already reeling from bad harvests due to back-to-back droughts and unseasonal rains, struggling to sell animals they can no longer feed or water.

"I wonder what the government wants - our survival or the cattle's?" said farmer Revaji Choudhary, standing next to a pair of bulls he has been trying to sell for weeks in a cattle market in Maharashtra.

Traditionally, farmers have sold cattle in a drought year to butchers, mostly Muslims, and bought new ones when their earnings rise after monsoon showers.

That cycle has been broken and could leave farmers with little money to buy seeds or fertiliser ahead of the next sowing season, starting in June. Farmer suicides have nearly doubled in the drought-hit Marathwada region of Maharashtra.

TO BAN OR NOT TO BAN?

Their predicament is causing concern within the BJP, which has been trying to bolster its credentials in the countryside, where most of India's 1.3 billion people live.

Rural distress contributed to an embarrassing defeat for the party last year in a state election, and more state polls are due over the coming year.

In the annual budget last month, Modi's government pledged nearly $13 billion on rural development, aiming to double farmer's incomes by 2022.

Maharashtra BJP legislator Bhimrao Dhonde said the government's priority should be to support farmers, and they should be allowed to sell their cattle to whomever they want.

"It is time to withdraw the ban," Dhonde told reporters.

Madhu Chavan, a spokesman for the BJP in Maharashtra, said Dhonde's view did not reflect that of the party.

"The party thinks the ban is necessary," he said, adding that more money would be made available to alleviate the effects of drought if needed.

MILLIONS OF COWS

Maharashtra, home to India's financial hub Mumbai, has been particularly badly hit by drought.

In one district the government imposed rules that prevent assembly of more than five people around a water tanker or borewell to prevent riots. Cows and buffalos need 70 litres of water per day.

Many farmers are simply abandoning their cattle.

The state has opened hundreds of temporary shelters to house around 250,000 heads of cattle until their owners are ready to take them back, but experts say at least another 4 million animals need to be looked after in Maharashtra.

Hindu groups such as the Vishva Hindu Parishad (VHP) that had promised to build shelters said they, too, were short on cash and the government should do more.

Laxmi Narayan Chandak, head of the Maharashtra unit of VHP's cow protection committee, said his organisation has been able to start only one facility that holds 150 cattle.

"Nearly 700,000 cows and bulls ... will starve to death or will be smuggled to slaughter houses. We have to save them," said Chandak.

He added that only pure Indian breeds "that are worthy of worship" should be sheltered.

Every Monday, hundreds of farmers like Choudhary travel to a weekly cattle market in Belhe village, around 200 km (124 miles) east of Mumbai, but with so few people buying, it is more in hope than expectation.

Cattle prices in the state have fallen 40 percent to 60 percent.

Choudhary, who earns around Rs 200,000 ($3,000) in a good monsoon year, said he has incurred losses as his crops wilted due to drought.

He paid Rs 40,000 for his pair of bulls a year ago, and is willing to sell them for Rs 20,000 now. He still cannot find a buyer.

"We are forced to depend on tankers for drinking water. How can we supply water to cattle?" Choudhary asked.

Reuter
		</body>
	</article>
	<article>
		<title>
			Nirbhaya rape case: Ahead of juvenile offender's release, human rights body issues notice to Centre
		</title>
		<body>
			New Delhi: The National Human Rights Commission has issued notices to the Centre and to the Delhi government on a complaint by the parents of the 16 December gangrape victim, apprehending threat to society from the juvenile convict in the case who is set to be released next month.

The Commission has taken cognisance of the complaint by the parents of the girl, who was brutally gangraped and murdered in Delhi on 16 December in 2012.

"They have stated that the juvenile, who was largely responsible for the death of their daughter and was the most brutal amongst all the offenders, is supposed to be released sometime in December.
Representational image. Reuters

Representational image. Reuters

"They have submitted that such persons are threat to the life and liberty of the common man. There should be a mechanism to keep a strict check on them so that people are not subjected to any risk of being harmed. The complainants have also stated that the rate of recidivism (committing crimes again) is fairly high," said an NHRC statement.

The parents have requested the Commission to recommend to the Government to prepare a plan to protect the citizens from such delinquent juveniles post their release and also to strengthen the extant laws on the subject.

The complainants have also cited that similar laws like SORNA (Sex Offender Registration and Notification Act) that requires states to monitor and track convicted sex offenders following their release into the community and operates in countries such as USA, Canada and others should be implemented in India.

The Commission on its part observed that "There is no doubt that the complainants have undergone extreme agony and pain after the incident of rape and murder of their daughter. The fears expressed by them need to be looked into".

The parents have also made a representation to the Home Minister on the same and submitted the copy of the representation to the Commission along with the complaint.

Accordingly, the Commission has issued notices with a copy of the complaint to the Secretary, Delhi, the Commissioner of Police, Delhi and the Secretary, Ministry of Home Affairs and sought reports in the matter within two weeks.

The Commission has further asked the Chief Secretary in Delhi government to inform whether any pre-release and post release plan as per Rule 17(3) of the Juvenile Justice (Care and Protection of Children) Rules, 2007 has been prepared in the case of the juvenile. If yes, copies of the same may be furnished to the Commission.

The Chief Secretary has been asked to inform whether the juvenile has been recently subjected to psychological or psychiatric assessment for assessing his mental health. If yes, a copy of the psychological assessment report shall be furnished.

The Secretary in the Ministry of Home Affairs has also been asked to inform about the action, if any, taken on the representation submitted by the complainants.
		</body>
	</article>
	<article>
		<title>
			Where is Rs. 2000 cr Nirbhaya Fund, AAP questions BJP over women's safety
		</title>
		<body>
			New Delhi: The Aam Aadmi Party (AAP) on Tuesday targeted Bharatiya Janata Party (BJP)-led National Democratic Alliance government at the Centre over women's safety, questioning about allocation of Rs.2,000 crore Nirbhaya Fund for that purpose.
Representational image. PTI

Representational image. PTI

AAP leader Dilip Pandey in a press conference alleged: "BJP is taking revenge of its failure in elections by compromising with safety of women in Delhi."

"Rs.2,000 crore fund was allocated for women's safety after Nirbhaya case but nobody knows where that money has gone," he said, adding that the Centre had promised to open 660 rape crisis centres across the country but only 36 were operational.

The party targeted Governor Najeeb Jung over deployment of 4,000 Home Guards in Delhi Transport Corporation (DTC) buses.

Pandey said a file regarding deployment of around 4,000 marshals in DTC buses to ensure security for women in public transport, was lying pending with Jung's office.

"The AAP has given one week's time to the Lieutenant Governor to release it and if he failed to do so, the women wing of the party will meet him," Pandey said.
		</body>
	</article>
	<article>
		<title>
			Delhi gangrape: Release of juvenile rapist opens old wounds, 'not justice' says Nirbhaya's mother
		</title>
		<body>
			The juvenile convict in the infamous Delhi gangrape of Nirbhaya on December 16, 2012, is due for release next month after serving his three-year sentence opening up old wounds and old debates.
The convict, now 20 years, old was a juvenile in 2012 when the crime was committed, and the court found him guilty of raping and assaulting the victim along with five accomplices — among whom main accused 35-year-old Ram Singh was found dead in his Tihar jail cell in 2013 — in a private moving bus in Delhi.
File image of the convicts of the 2012 Delhi gangrape being taken away after sentencing. AP

File image of the convicts of the 2012 Delhi gangrape being taken away after sentencing. AP

Nirbhaya’s mother told CNN-IBN that allowing the 20-year-old from Badaun, Uttar Pradesh to leave the reform home ‘sends out a wrong message’. “Juveniles will now think they can do whatever they want, and get away with it,” she added. PTI quoted her as asking, “But did he reform? Thousands of girls are being raped across the country. What has changed?”

Making a strong plea to the government to ensure he remained in custody, in jail if not in a juvenile home, while being tried (it is not clear what she meant because he was tried and sentenced by a juvenile court), Nirbhaya’s mother said: “They say that his rights as a juvenile have to protected. What about us? Are we not citizens, don’t we have rights? And what about Nirbhaya’s rights? Doesn’t she deserve justice? Don’t we deserve justice? I appeal to the government to not allow this to happen. If he roams free we will be sending a wrong message to others."

Meanwhile, Nirbhaya’s father is quoted by PTI as warning that “He may go out and commit another crime and if he does, it will be due to shortcomings on the government's part”.

This is a concern that does not appear to be lost on Union Women and Child Development Minister Maneka Gandhi, who advocated the need to keep a ‘close watch’ on the youth. “He is a person who should be kept under watch. We can't just let him go and wait for him to do something else,” she cautioned.

However, Gandhi also added that justice should not be confused with the law. “The law said that he could only go to children’s home. That's the anomaly we are trying to correct. So, he served his sentence and in according to the law he is coming out. And there is nothing we can do about it until or unless he commits another crime.”

Amid reports that the convicted juvenile has become a model inmate — offering namaaz five times a day and fasting during Ramzan — who is afraid of being ‘lynched’ upon his release, major questions about whether the process of reform is truly complete have been raised. This debate is likely to intensify over the days leading up to the end of his sentence.

Here are some reactions from the Twitterati:
Why do we continue to call her Nirbhaya? What’s wrong with saying Jyoti Singh Pandey?
Yes, the law prohibiting the media from mentioning a rape victim’s name is fantastic (though not always followed). But when a victim, or her family, wants to reveal her name and the media refuses to call her by it – that’s a different story.

The late Jyoti Singh Pandey’s parents have been publicly using her name since 2013, have told us they want her name published. And yet the media insists on calling her Nirbhaya. This week, on the third anniversary of the gangrape that led to the Criminal Amendment Law Act of 2013, her mother Asha Devi told the media:

    “My daughter's name was Jyoti Singh and I am not ashamed to name her. Those who commit heinous crimes like rape, their heads should hang in shame, not the victims or their families. You should take her name too.”

This isn’t the first time either. In January 2013, not even a month after his daughter was gangraped and tortured, Jyoti Singh’s father told the UK media her name, saying,

    “We want the world to know her real name…My daughter didn’t do anything wrong, she died while protecting herself…I am proud of her. Revealing her name will give courage to other women who have survived these attacks. They will find strength from my daughter.”

Why does the media insist on calling Jyoti Singh “Nirbhaya” then? Has “Nirbhaya” become a brand that we don’t want to let go of, despite her parents’ wishes? Are we, the media, too satisfied with the story that weaves itself around a name that means “fearless”?

Nirbhaya-case-parents_PTIDespite being in a world of pain, Jyoti Singh gave a full statement to the police. That takes courage, yes. But what if we have taken that amazing show of courage too far? What if the name “Nirbhaya” doesn’t allow her to be human in our eyes, doesn’t allow her to be scared? She had a right to be scared if she wanted to. Would we respect her less if she had been scared, even for a moment, during the painful medical procedures she went through? Or is the very thought blasphemy?

Have we, as a nation, processed Jyoti Singh in the familiar way we process many women, by turning her into a goddess, while her parents, to whom she is all too human, protest on the sidelines? We’ve named her Jagruti, Damini, Amanat, Delhi Braveheart, India’s Daughter. Some of these names smack of deification. And have we done this because a goddess or a daughter/sister is the only kind of woman (or rape victim) we can respect? Is it so unthinkable that a woman should be treated as a human being, just like a man?

Another frightening aspect of our calling her Nirbhaya, against her parents’ wishes, is how convenient it is for us. It lets us forget the brutality of her rape, the brutality of many, many women’s and children’s rapes. It lets us forget the iron rod. It lets us forget that her intestines had to be removed. It lets us flippantly refer to “the post-Nirbhaya political climate,” as we tell each other knowingly. It’s a clean, whitewashed name that suits us. It lets us summarize millions of rapes in one neat word. If that word had a first name and a surname, we’d have to remember that she was a person like you and me.

If we call Jyoti Singh “Nirbhaya”, maybe we can tell ourselves that she didn’t feel fear at all, the entire time from when she was first attacked – as perhaps a goddess wouldn’t feel fear. Maybe, therefore, her suffering is diminished for us, since we can’t keep the horror of her rape in our minds for more than a few years before we have to move on with our lives. And maybe it helps us think of the gang-rape of Jyoti Singh as an isolated incident.

Because that’s just it – this terrible, terrible incident in December 2012 woke us up to the ugly reality of sexual assault in India. And now we just want to hit the snooze button and go back to sleep. We don’t want to read the newspapers, and look beyond the newspapers, to understand the magnitude, the massive scale on which rapes of women and children take place in our country, because that would mean we’d have to change our worldview. That would mean we’d have to do something about it.

The most important thing that a clean, whitewashed name and brand lets us forget is that you and I, too, are complicit in Jyoti Singh’s gang-rape. Yes, you. Yes, I. We didn’t actually rape her. Our DNA wasn’t found at the scene. But we’re responsible for creating/contributing to/allowing what we call a ‘rape culture’ – which can be defined as a culture that uses rape as a tool to oppress its women. The December 2012 rapists aren’t extraordinary monsters from a nightmare that will go away. They’re real, and they’re everywhere (that means our homes too), raping, beating, harassing women – and we better be careful that we don’t allow them into our hearts and subtly condone their actions by turning Jyoti Singh into a neatly packaged, one-word bra
		</body>
	</article>
	<article>
		<title>
			TRAI says no to differential pricing! Rules in favour of Net Neutrality
		</title>
		<body>
			TRAI is finally out with its notification on differential pricing. In the meeting held today, TRAI has made its stand clear that “no company to offer/charge discriminatory tariffs for data on basis of content”. This move is a big win for net neutrality.

TRAI said that anything on the Internet cannot be differentially priced and no operator shall charge discriminatory pricing on content, source and application. The existing plans in operation will not be valid in 6 months. Along with the ban on differential pricing, TRAI will determine if attempts are being made to violate regulations. TRAI is essentially attempting to put everything on the Internet on an agnostic platform.  Internet companies, however, will not fall under TRAI’s domain.

Only exception in the TRAI ruling is regarding emergency services. “Reduced tariff for accessing or providing emergency services, or at times of public emergency has been permitted,” said the ruling.

The regulation will be effective immediately and disallows any programs that allows discriminatory data tariffs. A penalty of upto Rs 50 lakh will be applicable for each day of violation of regulation.

For those uninitiated, it began with TRAI floating a consultation paper seeking views if differential pricing should be allowed, amidst the whole net neutrality debate. The regulator wanted to know what steps should be taken to ensure principles of non-discrimination, affordable Internet access, competition and so on if differential pricing is allowed. After some media coverage connecting differential pricing to net neutrality, Trai quickly put out a statement saying the paper issued is not on net neutrality, but on a specific matter about differential pricing.

However, there is no denying that both are co-related. Now, differential pricing means, different prices for different content aka apps, which violates net neutrality. So, differential pricing and net neutrality go hand-in-hand. And, we can say the same about Free Basics or any other similar platform. Differential pricing won’t just change the way we’ve always used Internet, but blatantly unfair and discriminating.The paper floated by TRAI received 24 lakh responses.

Telcos had written to TRAI, explaining differential pricing is essential for promoting innovation and growth of data services, and find support from Facebook. On the other hand, most voices out there, from startups to netizens, are against differential pricing. Most reports pointed that TRAI will be in favour of net neutrality.

Here is the complete TRAI release:

Press
		</body>
	</article>	
	<article>
		<title>
			After Zuckerberg’s Delhi townhall, Savetheinternet questions Facebook's internet.org platform
		</title>
		<body>


Oct 30, 2015 12:43 IST

#facebook   #IIT Delhi   #Internet.org   #Mark Zuckerberg   #Net neutrality   #Savetheinternet   #savetheinternet.in   #Shareworthy   #TheySaidIt   #Townhall  
0 Comments

    81

    0

New Delhi: Even as Facebook founder Mark Zuckerberg expressed commitment to net neutrality, volunteers of savetheinternet.in have raised questions over the internet.org platform.

In an open letter to Zuckerberg, the savetheinternet team said it's "a matter of distress" that Facebook through its internet.org platform and lobbying on regulatory consultations, has sought to undermine net neutrality in India.
Mark Zuckerberg at his townhall at IIT Delhi. PTI

Mark Zuckerberg at his townhall at IIT Delhi. PTI

During his townhall address on Wednesday, Zuckerberg said his company is committed to net neutrality, but supported zero-rating plans which have been criticised by many as violative of the principles of a free Internet.

"Even today, internet.org has restrictions that those services which compete with telecom operator services will not be allowed on it," the letter said.

The letter said its concern with internet.org/Free Basics is that it will create a new digital divide: those who access Facebook and its partner services, and those who access the open Internet.

The letter said Internet.org is not an open platform and "all we are asking for is for you to ensure that any such effort to bring access to the Internet ensure that users get access to the entire Internet, and not through a pre-determined menu or filter, which primarily benefits those who are selected for the platform".

The letter flagged worries that data for all the websites on internet.org will be with Facebook and restrictions on them publicly disclosing usage of their sites and services by users on internet.org.

"Facebook, along with its intention to connect billions to the Internet, should support and advocate Net neutrality and permissionless innovation in India, the way it has done in the US," the letter argued.

Internet.org, which aims to bring free Internet access to the developing world, has faced a backlash, with activists alleging that it violates net neutrality, an idea which means that all online traffic should be treated equally.


		</body>
	</article>	
	<article>
		<title>
			Net Neutrality debate: Will India end up going the way of the US?
		</title>
		<body>
			The deadline set by the Telecom Regulatory Authority of India (Trai) for receiving public opinions/suggestions on its consultation paper on Net Neutrality expired on 7 January. To be fair to the Trai, it did not seek expert view on Net Neutrality as such, but ‘on a specific matter of differential policy for data services being offered by the operators’. Nevertheless this ‘specific matter’ is an integral and important part of the Net Neutrality debate.

Unfortunately, the specific consultation process initiated by the Trai was hijacked by the Free Basics debate involving Facebook. As per reports, by 7 January when the deadline expired, Trai had received almost 24 lakh responses out of which 13.5 lakh came through the template of ‘@supportfreebasics.in’ without individual emails and 5.44 lakh comments came along the same lines through ‘@facebookmail.com”.

The major chunk of the opposite view, which countered the Free Basics proposition, came through another template ‘Save the Internet’. It attracted 4.84 lakh responses.
Facebook Free Basics Desktop. tech2

Facebook Free Basics Desktop. tech2

Trai chairman’s exasperated comment was:”It is like we have asked Question X and they have given answer to Question Y”. He went on to add: “Consultations by the Trai are not opinion polls; we are not asking ‘yes’ or ‘no’. We are asking why you think it is ‘yes’ or ‘no’, because that helps us in formulating the guidelines.”

If it were an opinion poll, clearly ‘Free Basics’ would have won hands-down. Since it is not, it has to now be seen what policy Trai formulates in the days to come on the differential tariff issue.

Trai’s dilemma is reminiscent of a similar situation that the Federal Communications Commission (FCC), the regulatory authority in the US on telecommunications matters, faced last year.

Trai, in its consultation paper, had mentioned some plans which amounted to differential tariffs provided by Telecom Service Operators (TSPs). Some of them offered zero or discounted tariff to certain content, websites, applications or platforms.

“The objective of offering such schemes is claimed to be the desire of various service/content/platform providers to enable consumers , especially the poor, to access certain content on the internet free of charge.”

The paper goes on to say that there is a flip side:

“On the one hand, it appears to make overall internet access more affordable by reducing cost of certain types of content. On the other hand, several negative effects might ensue. Differential tariffs result in classification of subscribers based on the content they want to access. This may potentially go against the principle of non-discriminatory tariff.”

The FCC in the US was caught up with a similar dilemma last year as to whether some Internet Service Providers (ISPs) should be allowed to offer a faster track to send content at a higher cost. In May 2014, It deliberated on two options: First, permitting fast and slow broadband lanes which amounted to compromising the principle of Net Neutrality that emphasises a 'free and open internet'. The second option was to reclassify broadband services as telecommunication services (instead of ‘information services’ as it had been designated then) and disallow differential pricing; this would preserve the principle of Net Neutrality.

There was a heated debate in the US. ISPs strongly lobbied for the first option. But over 100 internet companies — including Google, Microsoft, eBay and Facebook — signed a letter urging the FCC to go for the second option, as the first option would constitute a ‘grave threat to the internet’.

Four million Americans sent a petition to President Barack Obama urging him to preserve the principle of Net Neutrality. In November 2014, President Obama made his position crystal clear: “When I was a candidate for this office, I made clear my commitment to a free and open internet, and my commitments remain as strong as ever.”

As regards the deliberations of the FCC, the President said:” The FCC is an independent agency and ultimately the decision is theirs alone.”

Spelling out his own view, Obama said:”I believe the FCC should create a new set of rules protecting net neutrality and ensuring that neither the cable company nor the phone company will be able to act as a gatekeeper, restricting what you could do or see online.”

Whether President Obama’s ringing endorsement of the Net Neutrality principle influenced FCC to reverse its position taken in April 2014 to allow some ISPs like Comcast and Verizon to offer differential tariff is not known, but in February 2015, it voted in favour of the Net Neutrality principle to keep the internet open and free.

The decisive moment has now come for the Trai. Will it go the FCC way and nix any proposal to compromise the principle of Net Neutrality?

Will Narendra Modi, the country’s supreme leader, make his position clear a la Obama, in a hard-hitting message to the Trai?

In any case, Trai is no FCC. It may be ‘indpendent’, but like most regulatory bodies in India, it is subservient to the government. India’s telecom minister has already said that the government would firm up its position after it received the recommendation of the Trai. Clearly, unlike the FCC, Trai can only recommend; the decision-making authority lies with the government.

The question is: Will the Indian government decide to go the US way and preserve the principle of Net Neutrality?

PS — An intetesting anomaly: Facebook was on the side of Net Neutrality activists in the US; it is in the firing line of Net Neutrality activists in India.

To read why Free Basics isn’t all it’s cracked out to be, check out FreeBasics: Nothing Free or Basic in this bargain of Privacy and to read why Free Basics isn’t the demon it’s made out to be, check out Free Basics: Regulatory principles versus Ideology
		</body>
	</article>	
	<article>
		<title>
			Save the Internet: AIB’s new video reveals how Facebook’s Free Basics violates net neutrality
		</title>
		<body>
			Finally, AIB is out with the third video in their #SavetheInternet series. This time around it is over Facebook’s aggressive marketing to push Free Basics in India and gather support by misleading users.

The comedy group has simplified Free Basics and explained how it is the same old Internet.org that is being repackaged in a new form to attract audiences. Free Basics is noting but Internet.org, which is nothing but the death of the way we’ve known Internet so far.

The video urges people to support net neutrality by sending an email to TRAI through SavetheInternet.in before December 30. Recently, TRAI had asked Reliance Communications to put Free Basics on hold too.

Net neutrality has been a heated topic for months now. Triggered by Airtel’s zero platform that faced public outcry and compelled its partner Flipkart to walk out of the partnership, Facebook has also been facing criticism and many companies like NDTV and Cleartrip decided to part ways with it too.

While Airtel clearly called it a marketing platform, Facebook founder Mark Zuckerberg has repeatedly called his pet project Internet.org a way to help bring the world (especially emerging markets with remote areas without Internet access) online.

Besides India, Internet.org has also been launched in other emerging countries like Colombia, Zambia, Tanzania, Kenya and Ghana. Well, the least he could do is stop calling it a noble cause as its simply shrewd business. After facing criticism in India, the company rebranded Internet.org to Free Basics. It’s like packaging old wine in a new bottle and is against net neutrality in India.

		</body>
	</article>	
	<article>
		<title>
			Panama papers leak: What's with the silence, Amitabh Bachchan?
		</title>
		<body>
			As many as 500 Indians have been named in a massive leak of 11.5 million tax documents revealing offshore assets, through an investigation helmed in collaboration with India by Indian Express.
Amitabh Bachchan. Getty Images

Amitabh Bachchan. Getty Images

Among other Indians, Amitabh Bachchan and Aishwarya Rai have found place in the list that was gathered from the secret files of Mossack Fonseca, a law firm based in tax haven Panama.

And while a spokesperson for Aishwarya Rai has denied this claim, calling it 'totally untrue and false', there has been radio silence on Amitabh Bachchan's side.

What's the big deal, you ask? Well, we did the tedious task of finding out the last time Amitabh Bachchan's social media had no post in 24 hours, and as it turns out, there isn't a single day when he hasn't been active on social media. Infact, he updates his social media every couple of hours, regardless of what time zone he is in. Despite going all the way back to November 2014, we couldn't find  a single instance where Bachchan had stayed silent on social media for a day-long duration.

Bachchan either updates a status, or a facebook post (usually with pictures) or updates his blog, or at the very least, re-tweets a couple of tweets on his timeline. However, a quick glance through his social media and there has been no update in the last 18 hours.

This was his last tweet:

Why the silence, Mr. Bachchan?


		</body>
	</article>	
	<article>
		<title>

			All you need to know about the Panama Papers row
		</title>
		<body>
			The Panama Papers have set off a tornado that has so far swept many countries across the globe, current and former heads of state, the rich and famous in films, sports, their family and associates besides criminals in its wake.

What are the Panama papers?

On April 3, 2016, the International Consortium of Investigative Journalists (ICIJ) put out an in-depth, investigated and analysed report that blows the lid off tax evasion and secret offshore dealings of the powerful, rich and famous across the globe in 21 offshore jurisdictions such as Nevada, Niue, Samoa, British Anguilla, Hong Kong, Tortola, Seychelles and the British Virgin Islands. The 12 current and former heads of state from Iceland, Ukraine, Pakistan, Saudi Arabia, Russia and Argentina also figure on the list.  It also provides data on some 214,000 companies.
Mossack Fonseca headquarters. AFP

The Mossack Fonseca office in Panama City. AFP

The whopping 11.5 million confidential Mossack Fonseca documents were leaked, revealing 2.6 terabytes of data, covering nearly 40 years of records.

“It allows a never-before-seen view inside the offshore world providing a day-to-day, decade-by-decade look at how dark money flows through the global financial system, breeding crime and stripping national treasuries of tax revenues,” the ICIJ said.

Why is it called the Panama Papers?

The tax evaders stashed funds in Mossack Fonseca, a law firm and corporate service provider based in Panama.

The Republic of Panama is located between North and South America.

Mossack Fonseca, founded in 1977 by German-born Jurgen Mossack and Ramon Fonseca, specializes in commercial law, trust services, investor advisory and international structures. The law firm’s website claims it is one of the largest firms in the corporate services industry and has over 40 offices globally. It also offers intellectual property protection and maritime law services.

The Munich-based daily, Sueddeutsche Zeitung, which got the secret papers and shared it with ICIJ, says in its report that Mossack Fonesca sells anonymous offshore companies around the world. These shell firms enable their owners to cover up their business dealings, no matter how shady.

Mossack Fonesca is the world’s fourth biggest offshore law firm.

Why would anyone invest in a shell company?

It is not illegal to own a shell company. Usually, the world’s famous people who do not want to be seen as the real owners of assets prefer to invest in a shell company anonymously. However, that is not legal. Buying a shell company is a good source of stashing away money that you don’t want anyone to know– bankers, government, the taxman, and also your wife or husband. If the money is ill-gotten wealth, all the more reasons to invest in a shell company. A lawyer is a brilliant cover to buy a shell company, if you don’t want to do it yourself.

Who leaked information?

The story has the pulsating adrenalin rush of a James Bond film. The Munich-based daily Sueddeutsche Zeitun received 11.5 million data spanning a time-frame of 40 years (1997 to 2015) through an encrypted channel. Bastian Obermayer, a reporter of the daily,  says the whopping information was given gratis with a request for security in return.

After receiving the records of  214,488 offshore entities through emails, financial spreadsheets, passports and corporate records, the ICWJ put 370 journalists from across 80 countries on the job of tracing the hidden offshore assets of a roster of people in over 200 countries.

What is the India link?

The Panama Papers have a few Indian names from business families, well-known lawyers and family members, Bollywood actors and also criminals.

    Amitabh Bachchan
    Aishwarya Rai-Bachchan
    Kushal Pal Singh, DLF owner and 9 members of his family
    Sameer Gehlaut, Chairman & Founder, Indiabulls Group
    Vinod Adani, industrialist Gautam Adani’s elder brother
    Shishir K Bajoria – promoter of SK Bajoria Group and politician from West Bengal
    Anurag Kejriwal, former chief of the Delhi unit of Loksatta Party
    Onkar Kanwar, chairman of Apollo Group
    Anil Vasudeva Salgaocar , Goa-based mining baron and former MLA
    Mohan Lal Lohia, chairman emeritus, Indo Rama Synthetics, Chairman – Indo Rama Holdings Ltd
    (late) Indira Sivasailam, wife of Anantharamakrishnan Sivasailam, chairman of Amalgamations Group. Her daughter, Mallika Srinivasan – chairman and CEO of Tractors and Farm Equipment Ltd
    Harish Salve, former Solicitor General of India (1999-2002)
    Tabasum and Abdul Rashid Mir, Founder and CEO, Cottage Industries Exposition
    Zavaray Poonawalla, head, managing committee, Royal Western India Turf Club (RWITC) and brother of Dr Cyrus Poonawalla
    Rajendra Patil owns medical and engineering colleges in Davangere. He is the son-in-law of Congressman and Karnataka horticulture minister Shamanur Shivashankarapppa
    Jehangir Soli Sorabjee, honorary consultant physician, at Bombay Hospital. He is the son of former attorney general Soli Sorabjee
    Iqbal Mirchi, underworld don, now dead

Who is the global who’s who?

    Mauricio Macri, President, Argentina
    Vladimir Putin (to be fair, his name does not appear in the records) but his inner circle including his family and best friend and professional musician, Sergei Roldugin
    Sigmundur Davíð Gunnlaugsson, Prime Minister, Iceland
    Salman bin Abdulaziz bin Abdulrahman Al Saud, King of Saudi Arabia
    Sheikh Khalifa bin Zayed bin Sultan Al Nahyan, president of the United Arab Emirates and emir of Abu Dhabi– one of the wealthiest man in the world
    Pavlo Lazarenko, former PM of Ukraine, one of the world's 10 most corrupt politicians by Transparency International,
    Petro Poroshenko, President of Ukraine and billionaire ‘chocolate king

Fifa players

    Lionel Messi and his father who was his agent
    Michel Platini
    Leonardo Ulloa, a top scorer for Leicester City
    Gabriel Iván Heinze from Argentina who played with Manchester United and Real Madrid

Who are the other beneficiaries?

    Li Xiaolin, the second child and only daughter of former Chinese Premier Li Peng
    Ian Cameron, father of British Prime Minister David Cameron. He died on September 8, 2010
    Mariam Safdar, daughter of Pakistan Prime Minister Nawaz Sharif and his sons Hasan and Hussain
    Alaa Mubarak,  a wealthy Egyptian businessman, is the eldest son of ousted former Egyptian President Hosni Mubarak
    Mounir Majidi, a businessman and entrepreneur, who was the personal secretary to the King Mohammed VI of Morocco, in 2000.
    Clive Khulubuse Zuma, nephew of South Africa’s president Jacob Zuma.

Where were the intermediaries set up?

Fonseca worked with over 14,000 banks, law firms, company incorporators besides other middlemen to set up companies, foundations and trusts for customers. The top preferred 10 countries are: Hong Kong, United Kingdom, Switzerland, United States, Panama, Guatemala, Luxembourg, Brazil, Ecuador and Uruguay

Reactions from Mossack Fonseca 

"This is a crime, a felony," Ramon Fonseca, one of the founders of the Panamanian firm Mossack Fonseca, told AFP, describing the data that was leaked as a 'limited hack'. He was an advisor to Panama's President Juan Carlos Varela until last month. The company washed its hands off the expose and said that the role of the firm was limited to that of an intermediary.
		</body>
	</article>	
	<article>
		<title>
			Panama Papers fallout: Investigators end search at Mossack Fonseca
		</title>
		<body>
			Panama City: Prosecutors have wrapped up their search at Mossack Fonseca's offices, looking for evidence of any illegal activity in the company at the center of a document leak that revealed details of offshore financial accounts.
Law firm Mossack Fonseca. Reuters

Law firm Mossack Fonseca. Reuters

Lead organised crime prosecutor Javier Caraballo emerged from the offices after 27 hours of searching to say investigators had seized 100 computer servers that they would begin reviewing. "We cannot so far establish if we have elements that show some kind of tie (to illegal acts), but we are satisfied with the quantity of information that we have been able to collect," Caraballo said.

Earlier in the day, Attorney General Kenia Porcell said it was too early to talk about what might have been found in an investigation that she described as very complex. She said investigators were checking the firm's computers and noted it had servers in multiple locations. Prosecutors are also checking the server of the telephone company that provided the firm's service. "I'm not saying there is a crime," Porcell stressed. Mossack Fonseca has denied any wrongdoing.

The search started on Tuesday, 10 days after news reports began emerging about the document leak known as the Panama Papers. Stories reported that the millions of documents contained details on secretive offshore accounts and shell companies set up by Mossack Fonseca for wealthy clients around the globe.

About 30 demonstrators gathered outside Mossack Fonseca's office on Wednesday to demand a thorough investigation. "We demand justice. We cannot allow that a law firm cast doubts on the country," said Luis Gonzalez, leader of the country's powerful construction workers union. "Investigate these scoundrels and lock them up."

Some legal observers questioned the government's delay in investigating the offices. "The day after the revelations came to light, the public ministry should have intervened immediately in Mossack Fonseca, should have collected the data, the computer, gotten all of the evidence," said Italo Antinori, an expert in constitutional law at Complutense University in Madrid. "A lot of evidence could have been diluted, altered," he added.
		</body>
	</article>
	<article>
		<title>
			IAS officer DK Ravi's death confirmed as suicide: Karnataka officials slandered him, female batchmate, says CBI
		</title>
		<body>


FP Politics  May 21, 2015 17:02 IST

#CBI   #CID   #ConnectTheDots   #death   #DK Ravi   #IAS   #India   #Karnataka   #Siddaramiah  

    57

    1

Months after outrage over his death, the CBI has reportedly confirmed that IAS official DK Ravi's death was a suicide. It has also found he did not, in fact, make multiple phone calls to a female batchmate before committing suicide, and such reports may have been leaked to the media purely to slander him.

Ravi was Joint Commissioner in State Commercial Taxes Department when he was found dead in his Bengaluru residence on 16 March after allegedly hanging himself. The probe into the death was initially conducted by the CID of the state police and was later transferred to central agency CBI under intense pressure from the deceased IAS official's family, public and opposition parties.
PTI image

PTI image

A lot of the outrage over Ravi's death centred around the mysterious circumstances of his death given that a suicide note wasn't found, and the fact that the IAS official was seen as an upright officer who had been taking on powerful corporate lobbies.

However, reports on Wednesday said that the CBI has found no evidence of foul play and is set to declare his death as a suicide.

According to an Ibnlive report,  the CBI has dismissed the theories of murder or abetment to suicide and the preliminary enquiry seems to have concluded that his suicide was sparked by a failed real estate venture.

The investigating agency found that Ravi and a friend called Hari had collected Rs 5.5 crore from various sources to purchase land in Chikkabalpur under a company called R and H properties. However, the venture fell through after it was discovered that the land was owned by scheduled castes and tribes, and he was under pressure from investors to return the money.

The Indian Express quoted unnamed sources as saying that in the days before his death Ravi had told his friend to withdraw Rs 2 crore from the company's bank account and give it to his wife. The report also said that he had also received a deposit of Rs 10 lakh from the married female batchmate who became embroiled in the controversy surrounding his death.

However, the bigger problem for the Karnataka government is the fact that the CBI has reportedly revealed that the false leaks about Ravi making multiple calls to a married female batch mate may have been done purely with an intent to slander the dead IAS official.

A Times of India article quoted an unnamed CBI official as saying that they had found no evidence that the IAS officer had made 44 calls to the woman batchmate on the day of his death as claimed by some anonymous Karnataka officials in earlier media reports. Even Whatsapp messages that he had exchanged with his batch mate had been leaked to the media in an attempt to paint Ravi as a lovelorn man who planned to take his own life since the woman wasn't reciprocating.

The CBI has said it hasn't found any reason for such information to be leaked to the media when there was no evidence to support it and may question Karnataka officials in the coming days over the leak.

But this isn't even the first time that the Karnataka officials have been caught trying to deflect attention from the questions being raised about Ravi's death. The Karnataka High Court had in March imposed a stay of the government making public its findings into Ravi's death when the state government had suggested it would make unveil an interim report of the CID.

As Firstpost columnist Aravind Kamal had pointed out at the time, the effort to highlight Ravi's personal relations were seen by many at the time as an attempt by the state government to distract from the threatening calls that the IAS official had been receiving from real estate interests.

The CBI's findings in the case are yet to be made public, but if true, action should be taken against officials who attempted to malign the IAS official's reputation -- and of his batch mate -- merely to deflect heat. While the Siddaramaiah government can breathe easy about the fact that the IAS official's death has no real connection with any of corruption issues, it will face continued embarrassment if the CBI probe reveals wrongdoing on the part of its officials. As the saying goes, it's not the crime, it's the cover up that gets you in the end.
		</body>
	</article>
	<article>
		<title>
			A tale of three 'suicides': Politicians, media needs to handle deaths with sensitivity
		</title>
		<body>
			When 34-year-old DK Ravi, an additional commissioner of Commercial Tax (Enforcement) in Bengaluru was found hanging on 16 March, 2015 at his residence, the alleged suicide sparked off a political furore. It was the sand and real estate mafia which killed him, shrieked politicians in the opposition parties in Karnataka. The Chief Minister must resign, they demanded.

Barely a few days after the young life was snuffed out, rumours began to circulate of a love affair, at times one-sided and at times jilted, of DK Ravi with a batchmate, another IAS officer. Finally the case was handed over to the CBI on 23 March, as a raucous opposition and an even more strident media hollered for justice.

On the western coast, in 2010, a 26-year-old IAS officer Raja Murugan was found hanging from a tree outside his residence in Daman. He too was of the same 2009 batch as was DK Ravi. At the time, the Chief of Police of Daman had told reporters – “Primarily, it seems family problems may be the reason for the suicide,” stated RP Mina.
DK Ravi. File photo. PTI

DK Ravi. File photo. PTI

Almost a year after DK Ravi’s death, yet another young officer of the 2009 batch allegedly took his own life. N Harish, 32 years old, was found dead in his quarters at Egmore, Chennai on 18 February. Sources within the police department say that liquor bottles were strewn around, indicating that he was likely inebriated before his death.

Chief Ministerial hopeful and the scion of the Dravida Munnetra Kazhagam (DMK) MK Stalin announced on his Facebook page that the ruling All India Anna Dravida Munnetra Kazhagam (AIADMK) government was to be blamed for a string of what he called “mysterious deaths” of officials in the state. “When all his other batchmates had been promoted to the rank of SP, this 2009 batch officer Harish alone did not receive a promotion,” stated Stalin. “Other IPS officers themselves are wondering why Harish alone was not promoted.”

The Aftermath

While N Harish’s alleged suicide did not see the kind of national media and political frenzy as in DK Ravi’s case, accusations are inherent in the political rhetoric. Harish’s batchmates and colleagues though cast some light on what went on in his life for a number of years. “Harish had a lot of problems even during his NPA (National Police Academy) days,” said a police officer who took him under his wing in Tamil Nadu. “He was depressed, bordering on insubordination. Imagine a subordinate who doesn’t speak to you, doesn’t listen to orders and is absent most of the time,” said the officer. Even then, say his colleagues, he was not hassled by his seniors. One report was sent up the hierarchy about Harish’s erratic ways and chronic absenteeism. No action was taken on that either.

“Harish failed exams even at the NPA and recently failed his regional language paper, due to which he was not promoted,” said another friend of Harish’s. A departmental inquiry launched into a complaint of alleged misbehavior with a woman constable has been pending for a couple of years now.

As the news broke, media reports, based on anonymous WhatsApp forwards began to point the finger of accusation at a former Director General of Police, K Ramanujam, as being responsible for harassing the young officer and denying him a promotion. On 19 February, Ramanujam issued a response via WhatsApp questioning the allegations. “It is sad that Harish was not able to get promotion, but it was because he did not pass the test in Tamil language,” stated Ramanujam. “One has to clear the test for getting senior scale in this cadre. I had nothing against him personally. I retired more than a year back and I do not know whether he cleared the examination or not afterwards.” This response was subsequently not reported by the media which had reported the allegations in the anonymous WhatsApp forwards.

The tragic twist in this tale perhaps is that the initial postmortem reports now appear to show that Harish likely choked to death on food particles while in a drunken state.

“The media did not realize or maybe did not bother that unsubstantiated allegations like this will not just sully reputations of individuals but also cause legal issues for them,” said a senior journalist in Tamil Nadu who did not wish to be named. “It is the job of journalists to verify before making any information public. That was not done at all in this case,” he said.

Neither was this done in another “suicide or murder” case that hogged the headlines in September 2015. This case was that of young policewoman Vishnupriya who allegedly ended her life while in the midst of investigations of a high profile murder case. The CB-CID which is probing the suicide-murder theory confirms that the young officer in fact committed suicide. The reason, they say, is likely to be a combination of events – work pressure, stress and possibly a love affair gone wrong. In any case, it does not appear to be the state’s conspiracy that it was originally made out to be by political parties and the media alike, and the unwarranted baying for blood of Vishnupriya’s senior officers.

DK Ravi’s case was probably even more tragic. His batchmate, who was alleged to have rejected his displays of affection towards her, continues to be spoken of poorly. This, despite the facts of the case being that Ravi committed suicide due to his inability to repay loans taken for a real estate project that he was personally dabbling in. Even the tragic love theory has now been proven wrong.

“It is really very sad for the lady IAS officer,” said a senior journalist in Bangalore. “She is a fantastic worker and has a great track record. But now she is spoken of derogatorily by politicians and other bureaucrats. It is very unfair,” he said.

Politicians and the media would do well to focus on the lack of support for civil servants suffering from mental health issues. Tamil Nadu has been amongst the top three ranks in the list of states with highest suicide rates for the past four years. Chennai has topped the suicide charts for the past four years, amongst all metros in the country.

State governments must be prodded into implementing projects to address the issues of stress and mental health amongst civil servants and the police force. A pilot project conducted by the Tamil Nadu police in Madurai district in 2013 to provide counselling and techniques to cope with stress in policemen and their families showed that “56% of the police personnel, below the rank of sub-inspector, who participated in the five weeks training, suffered emotional disturbances. 46 per cent of them had disorders like insomania, hypertension or diabetes. 53 per cent of them experienced high level of stress,” according to the report. This report though recommended for implementation across the state, gathers dust in the seat of power, Fort St George.

In the heat and dust of elections round the corner, politicians too might be considerate in checking facts thoroughly before pronouncing statements and judgments at will. As for the media, truth must be the ultimate goal. Burying it under a cacophony of sensationalism is not an option.
		</body>
	</article>
	<article>
		<title>
			DK Ravi's death: Karnataka CM Siddaramaiah says yes to CBI probe into IAS officer's case
		</title>
		<body>
			ts been a week since IAS officer DK Ravi was found dead in his Bengaluru apartment under mysterious conditions and on Monday the Congress government in Karnataka finally bent to pressure from various quarters and said he would recommend a CBI probe in the case.

Speaking at the Karnataka Assembly, Chief Minister Siddaramaiah gave into the demands of Opposition, activists and the family members of the dead IAS officer and decided to handover the ongoing investigation of the case to the Central Bureau of Investigation (CBI).
IAS officer DK Ravi. PTI image

IAS officer DK Ravi. PTI image

"I understand the feelings of Ravi's parents.... We respect public sentiments..," Siddaramaiah said, adding that the government was keen that the truth should be brought out and culprits punished.

He also asserted that the government never wanted to hush up the case nor did it intend to protect anyone.

"...We believe in people's power. We believe in respecting public sentiments," said the Chief Minister who was facing rising public anger and growing clamour for a CBI probe.

The death of DK Ravi, who took on land mafia and realtors, spiralled into a major controversy after Siddaramaiah refused to seek a CBI probe in the case. The case was being probed by Karnataka CID. Opposition parties and activists have maintained pressure on the state government and have been demanding that the investigation in the case should be carried out by the CBI.

Amid major uproar in the Karnataka Assembly on Monday, CM Siddaramaiah defended the Karnataka CID and said that he had nothing against the CBI.

He said in the Assembly that the government had faith in the police and they hadn't criticised the CBI. Siddaramaiah also said that the CID had also been functioning independently, just like the CBI.

The decision to transfer the probe came after Congress president Sonia Gandhi on Monday wrote to Ravi's wife promising a fair and transparent probe into the incident. This came after Ravi's mother reportedly wrote an open letter to her seeking an impartial probe.

Siddaramaiah said he had planned to table the CID interim report but could not do so because of the High Court order.

Maintaining that his government never brought pressure on any officer and believed in providing a conducive working atmosphere for them, he said, "We believe in our system, judiciary and democracy... we will never show disrespect to
judiciary....we believe in the rule of law.."

Siddaramaiah also said there had never been a case where an incident had straightaway been referred to CBI immediately after its occurrence. With the federal set-up in the country, the Centre could not refer a case suo motu to CBI and could do so based on a state's request, he said.

He taunted the BJP, saying it had not referred even a single case to the central agency during its five year rule in the state.

The Chief Minister said the state CID was also efficient and handing over the probe to another agency would affect their morale, which was why he had been saying that they should be allowed to carry out their investigation first.

He had also assured the parents of Ravi that after receiving the report of CID and post mortem, he would take a decision on handing over the case to CBI.

The CM said Ravi was an honest and efficient officer and that was the reason why he transferred him from Kolar to Bengaluru as Additional Commissioner of Commercial Taxes (Enforcement)based on the request of his father-in-law.

The government has maintained so far that Ravi's death prima facie seemed to be a case of suicide, but the opposition parties and the family of the IAS officer have refused to accept the theory.

Ravi's family raised doubts over the police's claim that he committed suicide, saying that he was under "political pressure".

"My son wouldn't have committed suicide. He is not like that. He was strong hearted. My son was not a coward. I had not given birth to a son who could commit suicide," Gowramma, the mother of DK Ravi, had told PTI earlier.


		</body>
	</article>

</articles>