<articles>
	<article>
		<title>JNU, and the idea of India</title>
		<body> The Jawaharlal Nehru University (JNU) imbroglio has produced two important issues for public discussion. The first focuses on the limits that sedition (patriotism?) places on freedom of speech. It asks, for example, whether shouting anti-India slogans, by unknown persons as the First Information Report says, constitutes a ground for booking the students’ union president under sedition laws. If fine distinctions were to be made between slogans, protests, speeches, dissent, and incitement, and further between fuzzy and definite consequences of such actions, would not only some (very few) free speech expressions be considered seditious? These are crucial issues for our constitutional democracy today, and the JNU case has presented our courts with a great opportunity to give us a doctrine on the limits to free speech in India. Will we see in the court’s judgment its finest hour, as when, in the Kesavananda Bharati case, it set out the Basic Structure doctrine which places limits on the amending power of Parliament, or will it be its darkest hour, as in the Habeas Corpus case where unrestricted powers of detention under the Emergency were permitted? Will Justice H.R. Khanna be the court’s guide, or will it be Justice P.N. Bhagwati?

The second issue, entangled in the first, is with respect to the place of JNU in the postcolonial nation’s public life as the university nears its 50th year. I belong to the first decade of JNU, a magical period during which we gained perspective and learned the power of ideas and of democratic deliberation. It was a time when we became passionate about causes and when no tyranny was fearful enough to suppress our dissent. It covered the period of the Emergency and of the years immediately after, when a traumatised nation delved deep into its inner resources to discover what it stood for and what it stood against. It was a time for serious reflection.

Campus life in the heady 1970s

The 1970s was a period of ferment both globally and in India. The students’ movement was shaking up the Western world as was the peace movement and the challenges to orthodoxy in the form of music, fashion, poetry, and films. Demands for a New International Economic Order (NIEO) and a New World Information and Communication Order (NWICO) were being made. ‘Make love, not war’ was the slogan of the young who wanted to be unshackled from social conservatism. At this time the women’s movement was being seeded in JNU, as were many non-party political formations. The Emergency was on and JNU students had been picked up, including the students’ union president, and were languishing in jail. Yet the university was a magnet for students from across the country, from different backgrounds, and from different disciplines. Students who had graduated in the natural and applied sciences were flocking to the social sciences to understand what was happening to the nation.

In this turmoil JNU was able to give its education a national character by the points system it had developed, and by the examinations held across the country, to produce a level playing field. Students from socially and economically disadvantaged backgrounds, and regions, would be compensated for their disadvantage and thereby could face the competition. Soon after my joining in 1976, I recall taking out morchas to the surrounding areas shouting ‘Tanashahi nahi chalegi, nahi chalegi (down with despotism)’, and then rushing back into the sanctuary of JNU before the police came. The Emergency was on. We shouted slogans against the Maintenance of Internal Security Act (MISA) in the Mavalankar auditorium. We debated the articles of the People’s Union for Civil Liberties (PUCL) constitution on the lawns of the Gandhi Peace Foundation. We deliberated on an Agenda for India at the India International Centre. We collected funds for national tragedies such as the supercyclone in Orissa (now Odisha) and the Yamuna floods in Delhi.

But India alone was not our theatre of politics. The world was. Looking back I find it funny that we had to face the lathis of Delhi Police for protesting against the regime of the Shah of Iran or the sell-out of Palestinian interests by the Camp David accords. We campaigned for India to send foodgrain to Cambodia (then Kampuchea) which was just emerging from the genocide perpetrated by Pol Pot. In these heady days of politics we also saw art films from across the world and learnt to perform street plays. We were the earliest supporters of the Society for the Promotion of Indian Classical Music And Culture Amongst Youth (SPIC MACAY). In JNU we discovered voice and what it meant to stand up against tyranny. We became political.

Steady stream of who’s who

But this article is not about nostalgia. It is about the public legacy of this great university. It is about the place of JNU in the national imagination. JNU gave the students who entered it many things. It gave them opportunity. If we were to do a roll call of bureaucrats, journalists, artists, translators, writers, activists, professors, vice chancellors, heads of important institutions, and politicians, JNU would have a fair share of the leading members of these groups. It is not for nothing that in the last two years the heads of the Intelligence Bureau, Research and Analysis Wing, Central Bureau of Investigation, and the Foreign and Cabinet Secretaries have been from JNU. They do not look like anti-nationals to me. So where does all this ‘anti-national university’ stuff come from? What I have presented are the facts. Will those who have benefited from JNU please speak up in its defence?

Ask any of them what JNU gave them, and they will tell you it broadened their perspective, introduced them to ideas, even dissenting ones, prepared them for competition, gave them self-confidence, and fired them up with the making of a just India. It made them realise that dissent could be a virtue. In addition, JNU gave them networks. Anyone who understands success will know that networks are as important for success as merit and scholarship. That is why the Ivy League universities in the U.S., and Oxbridge in the U.K., and the Indian Institutes of Management and Indian Institutes of Technology in India have the reach they enjoy within state and society.

Crucible of the alternative

In addition to opportunity, self-confidence, personality development, and networks, JNU also gave a student perspective about the nature of the world, not just in terms of the global order, but also in terms of the structures of power, dynamics of society, drivers of change, and aspirations of citizens. We learnt how peasants became citizens. We learnt how elite capture was a problem for democracy. These ideas enriched our public discourse. At JNU we produced and reproduced the idea of an India that was inclusive, anti-discriminatory, gender-just, environmentally sustainable, artistically creative, cosmopolitan and socially redistributive.

There were many things wrong with JNU. For example, the liberal persuasion was not allowed the space it should have been given by the Stalinist Left. The political spectrum was wide but it could have been wider. Analytical thinking was feeble, and ideological camps gave protection to the less capable. But it was possible to question these ideological hegemonies. To dissent, experiment, collaborate, this is the signature of JNU. Debate was polemical but it was peaceful. There was no violence. By providing personnel to the civil services, academic institutions, civil society organisations, and media, JNU has been a significant incubator for the task of nation-building.

In addition to being an incubator of personnel to the state and civil society, JNU has also been an incubator of dissenting ideas. For a nation to cope with the pressures of modernity and the challenges of globalisation it needs to have an army of intellectuals who can prepare the nation for this new world that is upon us. It needs to engage with these new ideas. Go to a seminar in JNU, and you will be delighted by the intensity of the questions and the earnestness of the search for answers. It is one of the few places in the country where interdisciplinarity is a habit and where conversations between aestheticians and political scientists do not raise an eyebrow. Nor do dialogues between the cosmologies of the East and of the West.

A cosmopolitan university is a precious resource, for it continuously feeds the public sphere with questions and answers, with challenges to accepted truths and alternative readings of canonical texts. This is under threat today. Censorship of ideas and social relationships is being demanded by outsiders to the idea of JNU. Incidentally, the University of Chicago has issued the following statement on freedom of speech: “It is not the proper role of the university to attempt to shield individuals from ideas and opinions they find unwelcome, disagreeable and even deeply offensive… Concerns about civility and mutual respect can never be used as justification for closing off discussion about ideas, however offensive.” This represents the idea of JNU. Let us protect it from the hecklers who are knocking at the door. 
		</body>
	</article>
	<article>
		<title>JNU row: What is the outrage all about?</title>
		<body> The debate around Afzal Guru

Earlier, students from the Jawaharlal Nehru University organised an event on Parliament attack convict Afzal Guru who was hanged in 2013. This was to be done the day after Guru’s third death anniversary.

The event organisers had pasted posters across the campus inviting students to gather for a protest march against “judicial killing of Afzal Guru and Maqbool Bhat” and in solidarity with the “struggle” of Kashmiri migrants at the Sabarmati dhaba in the campus.

Afzal Guru, the mastermind behind the Parliament attacks in 2001, was hanged in 2013.

The programme called “A country without a post office — against the judicial killing of Afzal Guru and Maqbool Bhatt”, was supposed to showcase the protest through poetry, art and music.

This set off the row, with the Members of the Akhil Bharatiya Vidyarthi Parishad (ABVP) staging a protest to demand expulsion of the organisers.

The university administration ordered a “disciplinary” enquiry and said the event organisers “went ahead without permission.”

‘Anti-India’ slogans

ABVP members alleged that the protest march consisted of students shouting ‘anti-India’ slogans. A purported video from the event shows students shouting anti-India and pro-Pakistan slogans. Students in the video are heard saying slogans like: “Kashmir ki azai tak bharat ki azadi tak, janh rahegi jari”.

Students say:

The students who were part of the committee that organised an event to mark the death anniversary of Afzal Guru said that none of them were part of the group that was shouting slogans.

A student who was a part of the event organising committee, told The Hindu: “The programme was a cultural evening organised to question the working of the Supreme Court. It was also meant to bring the grievances of the Kashmiri citizens to light. The struggles of ‘self-determination’ must be openly spoken about. Considering this is a democratic republic, why should dissent be suppressed?”

Members of the ABVP protest against JNU's event on Afzal Guru. Photo: AP

Sedition charges

A case of sedition against several unknown students was lodged at Vasant Kunj (North) police station. It was registered under IPC Sections 124A (sedition), 120B (criminal conspiracy) and 34 (acts done by several persons with a common intention).

The university also initiated action, barring eight students from academic activity pending an enquiry, though they would be allowed to stay as guests in the hostels.

Arrest of Kanhaiya Kumar

JNU Students Union president Kanhaiya Kumar was arrested on sedition charges after allegations of ‘anti-national’ sloganeering against him surfaced. He was ordered to three days of police custody.

JNUSU president Kanhaiya Kumar. Photo: Sandeep Saxena

Why did the police take action?

The police struck after videos of the alleged protest went viral. Home Minister Rajnath Singh talked to Delhi Police Commissioner B.S. Bassi and released a statement: “If anyone raises anti-India slogans, tries to raise questions on the country’s unity and integrity, they will not be spared.”

Students protest ‘police raj’ within campus

Students of JNU gave a shutdown call, saying that they will not allow classes to be held on the campus till students’ union president Kanhaiya Kumar is released. JNU teachers too, joined the students in boycotting classes and said they would take classes on “nationalism” in the varsity lawns.

The university teachers had earlier rallied behind its protesting students and questioned the administration’s decision to allow the police crackdown on the campus even as they appealed to the public not to “brand” the institution as “anti-national” but they had not joined the strike earlier.

Police personnel guard the entrance of JNU. Photo: PTI

‘Fake’ Twitter handle

Rajnath Singh alleged that JNU students had the backing of Jamaat-ud-Dawah (JuD) chief Hafiz Saeed. But, his statement was based “fake tweet” from an unverified Twitter account. The account has posted funny messages in the past, with many on the social media considering it as a parody account. The account @HafeezSaeedJUD is no longer in use.

When contacted, a senior officer who handles the Delhi Police Twitter account said, “What proof is there that it was a parody account? Our domain is not to check parody accounts but to red-flag any incendiary content on social media. The law is very clear on this, Internet is just a medium of communication. Idea was to caution young people and students to not get carried away by such messages.”

Journalists, activists attacked in front of Patiala Court

A student gets assaulted at the Patiala House court complex on February 15. Photo: PTI
On February 14, the Patiala House courts witnessed violence as a mob, wearing lawyer’s robe, slapped and kicked supporters of Kanhaiya Kumar. The attacks began when Mr. Kumar was scheduled to appear before metropolitan magistrate Loveleen and continued for about 45 minutes during which whoever ran into the mob looking young and carrying a mobile was slapped, kicked and chased away from the premises. Journalists and students bore the brunt of the violence, while the older men and women were intimidated by the mob.

O.P. Sharma’s comments

The BJP MLA O.P. Sharma who was also in Patiala House Courts during the scuffle, got embroiled in the controversy when a video of him started surfacing. The video showed Mr. Sharma beating up a CPI worker outside the court’s gate number 4.

“As I was leaving the court I saw a man raising anti-India and pro-Pakistan slogans. I lost my cool, like any patriot, and asked him to shut up. And when I turned, he attacked me with an object.”

Mr Sharma doesn’t know what he was hit with, but the people around him got “offended seeing the MLA being attacked” and started beating up the attacker, read “anti-national”. “The problem of this country at present is that terrorism and being anti-national are considered being progressive. And JNU is promoting this kind of ideology and producing anti-nationals. JNU should be sealed,” Mr. Sharma said.

Rahul Gandhi’s role

Congress vice-president Rahul Gandhi criticised the BJP government, accusing it of “bullying” the prestigious institution. Soon after visiting the JNU campus Mr. Gandhi called an emergency meeting at his residence where he discussed ways to “tie up” every compelling issue the students are facing in India today and place them in its anti-BJP narrative.

Rahul Gandhi met President Pranab Mukherjee over the JNU row and the alleged targeting of students in various parts of the country. Accompanied by senior leaders and also the young MPs of the party, the Congress vice president highlighted the “lawlessness” in Delhi in the wake of Patiala House court attacks and the way the government has handled the JNU row.

Kanhaiya Kumar thrashed

In a shocking sequel to the incidents of February 15 in the Patiala House courts complex, violence was unleashed barely moments before a hearing on sedition charges against JNUSU president Kanhaiya Kumar was to start at 2 p.m.

The Delhi Police again filled the role of a “silent spectator” as attackers defied the Supreme Court’s order for restricted entry to the trial court complex, bashed up Mr. Kumar en route to his court hearing and hurled the choicest abuse, gravel and a jagged end of a flowerpot piece at a six-member team of senior advocates, including Kapil Sibal, hand-picked by the Supreme Court to verify and report back on the ground situation in the court complex.

Three ABVP members resign

Three members of the RSS student wing, Akhil Bharatiya Vidhyarti Parishad (ABVP), have resigned from their positions in the Jawaharlal Nehru University (JNU) unit of the party, citing ideological differences. In a letter jointly issued by the three students, they have “dissociated themselves” from any further activity of ABVP. The letter adds that they cannot be the “mouthpiece” of a government that has unleashed oppression on student community.

Kanhaiya Kumar released from Tihar

A court in New Delhi ordered release of the JNUSU president from the Tihar jail after he furnished bail bond of Rs. 10,000 in the sedition case, a day after he was granted six months’ interim bail by the Delhi High Court.

Mr. Kumar was granted interim bail for six months by high court which had observed that FIR lodged in connection with an on-campus event that led to his arrest on sedition charge suggested it “is a case of raising anti—national slogans which do have the effect of threatening national integrity“.

'We want freedom in India, not freedom from India'

Addressing a huge gathering of students on the campus, soon after release from Tihar Jail, Mr. Kumar said: “It is not azadi from India, it is azadi in India [we want]... from the corrupt practices that are going on inside the country.” Mr. Kumar made his fiery speech at the same place where he had addressed students just a day before his arrest. 
		</body>
	</article>
	<article>
		<title>JNU students Umar Khalid, Anirban Bhattacharya surrender to police</title>
		<body> Jawaharlal Nehru University students Umar Khalid and Anirban Bhattacharya, who are facing charges of sedition, surrendered before the Delhi Police late on Tuesday night after the Delhi High Court directed them to give themselves in earlier in the day.

The two left the campus in a university vehicle escorted by guards around 11:45 p.m. and were take into custody by a police team waiting outside one of the exit gates of the varsity.

Special Commissioner of Police (Law and Order) Deepak Mishra confirmed the arrest.

In the morning, Umar and Anirban moved the High Court seeking protection in order to surrender but the court, while directing the students to surrender, adjourned the hearing for protection till Wednesday.

Refusing to grant interim protection against arrest for a day, the Delhi High Court asked Umar and Anirban to inform it about the date, time and place where they wish to surrender.

The five students — Ashutosh Kumar, Anant Prakash, Rama Naga, besides Umar and Anirban – are wanted by the police in a sedition case.

Ashutosh, a former JNUSU president, said: “We have always maintained that we are not going to go anywhere in the campus. We are in the campus, if the police want they can call us for joining the probe. However, none of us have heard from them so far.” 
		</body>
	</article>
	<article>
		<title>Redefining Indian nationhood</title>
		<body>
The crackdown on JNU is in keeping with the right-wing project to ensure its world view becomes India’s as well. Constructing the premier university as a space for anti-national thinking is crucial, for it gives this project a famous address and a justification to step in.

The stand-off at Jawaharlal Nehru University (JNU) after some students earlier this month organised a meeting to discuss recent instances of capital punishment has occupied centre stage. The high-handed police action, the arrest of the elected president of the students’ union, Kanhaiya Kumar, on charges of sedition, and the battering of students, faculty and the media by a mob of lawyers in Delhi’s Patiala House courts, some with professed sympathies for the Bharatiya Janata Party, represents a new escalation of government overreach and meddling that has undermined the autonomy of institutions of higher education. It also indicates that violence in the name of nationalism is acceptable.

A crackdown on critical thinking

The shocking events that have gripped the nation are significantly different from the routine controversies surrounding campus politics in India. This was a deliberate and calculated attack on the democratic culture of JNU — synonymous with sharp critical thinking and vibrant debate.

JNU is India’s finest university. Its contribution to scholarship is well known and widely recognised; its importance to national intellectual life is undeniable. It has produced social scientists who are highly rated the world over. Its former students have been and are in the higher echelons of the government, bureaucracy, policy institutions and media; many vice chancellors, directors of research institutes and chairpersons of important academic institutions are drawn from JNU. The latest in this long list is the newly appointed vice chancellor of Delhi University. Importantly, many of JNU’s students now teaching in hundreds of universities and colleges have made a significant contribution to curricular reform and modern thinking in these institutions. The JNU course structure has served as a model for syllabi of several Central and State universities. So, why this attempt to destroy one of the finest universities at a time when most public universities are not exactly in the best of health and private universities are yet to take off?

That the attack on JNU was part of a larger design by right-wing forces to capture universities to impose a singular political discourse in institutions of higher learning is now obvious. This systematic pattern is clearly visible in the unrest in the Film and Television Institute of India, University of Hyderabad leading to the tragic suicide of Rohith Vemula, the controversy over the Ambedkar-Periyar Study Circle in the Indian Institute of Technology (IIT)-Madras, the furore over a film screening in IIT-Delhi, and now the protests in Jadavpur University. The Akhil Bharatiya Vidyarthi Parishad (ABVP) has become the instrument for political deradicalisation of various campuses which are fast emerging as major sites of conflict between the broadly secular left and the Hindu nationalists. This is a plausible explanation of the disquieting developments in JNU in the last two weeks. But the events also indicate that there is a larger agenda at work.

State power to silence dissent


So, what is really the issue here? The key issue is the use of state power to silence dissent and using a narrow nationalist discourse to put all critics of the government on the defensive. The immediate provocation for the police action and the sedition charge was the alleged shouting of anti-India slogans at a public meeting on February 9. The JNU students’ union (JNUSU) has categorically denied any involvement with the controversial event. The identity of those who allegedly chanted the slogans is still unknown. And yet, on February 12, the JNUSU president was picked up by the police for “anti-national” behaviour and for violating the sedition laws without ascertaining specific factual details about who shouted the slogans. This was a political decision taken at the highest levels of government except that in taking this decision, the Home Minister and the Delhi Police seem to have gone by evidence that was later found to be doctored and on the basis of a video supplied by a television channel. Commenting on the crackdown, Pratap Bhanu Mehta notes that the government is using “legal tyranny to crush dissent” and “the arrest was an open declaration by government that it will not tolerate any dissent.” JNU, famous for its culture of radical dissent, was purposely chosen to send a message to all those who disagree with this regime that dissent is unwelcome. This institution had to be contained specifically because it was producing a critique that does not always conform to the national consensus about major issues, be it capitalism, nationalism, caste, class, community or gender.

Also read: JNU row: What is the outrage all about?

Pushing its nationalist project


The crackdown on JNU and the arrest of Mr. Kumar on sedition charges is not surprising; it is in keeping with the hyper-nationalism promoted by the right wing. It testifies to the Right’s insistence on changing the public discourse in the country and ensuring its world view becomes India’s as well. It betrays an intention to create an atmosphere of general fear among students and teachers and scare those who do not agree with the government’s cultural project. At a time when the Modi government has not been able to deliver on the economic front, it is consistently finding ways to aggravate polarisation. For now, it is doing this by branding everyone who disagrees with it as anti-national. However, the issue here is not nationalism or patriotism, or who is or is not anti-national.

Rather, the BJP is using the crisis produced by its botched-up handling of the JNU events to widen and polarise public opinion across the country around its nationalist project. Modern India was formed in 1947 on the basis of a broader concept of non-ethnic, civic nationalism. By adopting this nationalism, India intended to set itself apart from Pakistan — which effectively committed itself to being a state for Muslims. The original concept of India as a nation based on civic rather than ethnic identity is being redefined sharply by the BJP’s rise, with much greater political space for the affirmation of Hindu identity, which according to its advocates cannot be separated from Indian nationhood even as this undermines secularism, one of the pillars of Indian democracy since Independence.

The original concept of India as a nation based on civic rather than ethnic identity is being redefined sharply by the BJP’s rise, with much greater political space for the affirmation of Hindu identity.

Constructing JNU as a space for anti-national thinking is crucial for it gives this project a famous address and a justification to step in to show its constituency that it can eradicate such anti-national people. They are also trying to use it as a springboard for the campaign to redefine nationalism. The rhetoric of ultranationalism, they believe, resonates strongly with its core base even though there is little evidence to suggest that it has a wider appeal. Comparing the impact of the notion of the national/anti-national during the Emergency and now, historian Gyan Prakash points out: “Like now, the Emergency regime also labelled dissent as anti-national, but it carried no weight with the public at large.” Nonetheless, sections of the media have been giving a helping hand to this phoney enterprise by letting the question of nationalism frame the terms of debate to polarise and confuse the population by constantly debating nationalism when the issue is the foundational right to dissent in a democracy. Smriti Irani, Minister of Human Resource Development, introduced Bharat Mata into this discourse. Thereafter, if this is a debate about nationalism, then the issue is not just any nationalism but one specifically of the right-wing kind, by which we mean a narrow nationalism rather than an inclusive and capacious one — a category of exclusion that regularly suspects a section of its own citizens.

Mr. Kumar had reminded his audience in his speech a day before his arrest that the forces of “Hindu India” now most vociferous in laying claim to true patriotism were not only absent in the freedom struggle but were often collaborating with the British. This puts in perspective the shape of the struggle between those who would lay claim to India as a democratic, heterogeneous, inclusive and potentially egalitarian national project, and those for whom nationalism is principally an aggressive religious assertion and unbridled pursuit of growth, where neither violence nor widening inequality matters.

Following the arrest of Mr. Kumar, the Modi government finds itself facing huge protests from the liberal-left and progressive opinion within and outside JNU. The police crackdown has drawn criticism worldwide from universities and academics. It has succeeded in bringing together a range of intellectual and political forces which fear threats to the exercise of their democratic rights. In particular, JNU has shown that it has the ability and the willingness to put up stiff and broad-based resistance to the extraordinary attack on the university. This has set off the largest nationwide protests by students in decades and provoked an equally unrelenting response from supporters of the Modi government who say the actions against students are justified. This face-off between state repression and intellectual freedom may well turn out to be a watershed moment for the country and for this anti-intellectual government too. Far from containing JNU, the debate over dissent and tolerance has got a new lease of life and is likely to overshadow everything else. 
		</body>
	</article>
	<article>
		<title>Wife suggested moving out of India: Aamir on intolerance</title>
		<body>
The actor said he also felt that the sense of insecurity and fear had been growing in the past six or eight months.

Actor Aamir Khan on Monday joined the outcry against intolerance, saying he was “alarmed” by a number of incidences and his wife Kiran Rao even suggested that they should probably leave the country.

He also supported those returning their awards, saying one of the ways for creative people to express their dissatisfaction or disappointment was to return their awards.

“As an individual, as part of this country as a citizen, we read in the papers what is happening, we see it on the news and certainly, I have been alarmed. I can’t deny. I have been alarmed by a number of incidents,” he said while speaking here at the Ramnath Goenka Excellence in Journalism Awards.

The actor said he also felt that the sense of insecurity and fear had been growing in the past six or eight months.

“When I chat with Kiran at home, she says ‘Should we move out of India?’ That’s a disastrous and big statement for Kiran to make. She fears for her child. She fears about what the atmosphere around us will be. She feels scared to open the newspapers every day.

“That does indicate that there is this sense of growing disquiet, there is growing despondency apart from alarm. You feel why this is happening, you feel low. That sense does exist in me,” Mr. Khan said.

The actor said for any society, it was important to have a sense of security and sense of justice.

Taking potshots at politicians, he said: “People who are our elected representatives, people who we select to look after us for five years, State or centre... when people take law into their hands, we look upon these people to take a strong stance, to make a strong statement, speed up the legal process, when we see that happening there is a sense of security but when we don’t see that happening there is a sense of insecurity.”

Endorsing the move by scientists, writers and filmmakers to return their awards to register their protest against the atmosphere of growing intolerance, he said for creative people it was important to voice what they feel.

“A number of creative people — historians, scientists — increasingly had a certain feeling in them, which they felt they need to express. For creative people, one of the ways of expressing their dissatisfaction or their disappointment is to return their awards. I think that’s one way of getting your point across,” he said.

When asked whether he endorsed the protests by the people, Aamir said he would as long as it is non-violent as “all individuals have a right to protest and they can protest in any manner that they feel is right as long as they are not taking the law into their hands.”

The actor criticised the political statements made after the Dadri incident, saying any act of violence — be it against individuals or a collection of people — was condemnable.

“It does not matter who the ruling party is... it does not matter who is in power... In TV debates we see, BJP is currently ruling and they are accused of various things but they say what about 1984. That does not make it right. 1984 was disastrous. It was horrendous,” Aamir said, adding that people look up to leaders to make reassuring statements.

Asked why was it that many politicians visited Dadri after the lynching incident whereas only the Defence Minister was there at the home of Colonel Santosh Mahadik, who lost his life in a terrorist attack last week, he said: “every act of terror and violence should be condemned with same ferocity”. 
		</body>
	</article>
	<article>
		<title>Aamir may have been under someone's influence: Mukhtar Abbas Naqvi</title>
		<body>
"Tolerance is in the DNA of this country. Neither is he going anywhere nor will we let him go," he said.

The Union government responded to film actor Aamir Khan’s view that intolerance had risen in the country in the last few months, by attributing the comments to having been made “under someone else’s influence.”

Minister of state for minority affairs, Mukhtar Abbas Naqvi said, “The country has given him (Aamir Khan) so much love and respect. I am sure he said it in a hurry or maybe under influence from others.”

“Tolerance is in the DNA of this country. Neither is he going anywhere nor will we let him go,” he added. The reaction was in contrast to previous reactions to such comments on intolerance by other celebrities, where BJP MPs would promptly issue statements on dispatching people to Pakistan.

BJP MP and Bhojpuri film star Manoj Tiwari however expressed strong sentiments of “disappointment” over Mr. Khan’s comments. “I am deeply saddened and shocked by his statement,” he said. “Aamirji should reflect on this statement that gives a wrong impression of the country,” he added.

Another film-star MP from the BJP, Paresh Rawal, urged Mr. Khan to fight it out in India saying he owed it to the country if he believed it was his motherland. “Aamir is a fighter so he should not leave but change the situation in the country. Jeena yahan marna yahan (to live and die here) a true patriot will not run away and leave his motherland behind in turmoil or in troubled times (if any). If I believe this is my motherland then I will never talk about leaving it, but I would if I believed otherwise,” he said.

PTI adds:

The ruling party also reminded Mr. Khan that his last movie ‘PK’ was a resounding box office success despite protests by some right wing outfits, stressing that it was an example of how tolerant Indian society is.

“Some isolated examples, however, extreme are exceptions to India’s inherent tolerant nature. It would be unfortunate to let isolated examples be taken as a norm that define India. Our Constitution guarantees freedom of expression and Aamir Khan like any citizen is entitled to his personal opinion. And any one who disagrees with him also enjoys the same freedom,” BJP spokesperson Nalin Kohli said.

Taking a dig at Mr. Khan’s comment at an award ceremony yesterday that his wife Kiran Rao had wondered if they should move out of India, he said many people chose to settle abroad for various reasons, including education, career, business and taxation.

“This is an individual choice. There is no constitutional bar on it,” he said.

Mr. Khan had yesterday said that he has been “alarmed” by a number of incidents and his wife even suggested that they should probably leave the country. He also supported those returning their awards, saying one of the ways for creative people to express their dissatisfaction or disappointment is to return their awards.

Security at Aamir's Khan's house after Hindu Sena threatened to demonstrate against his comments on intolerance. Photo: Vivek Bendre

'Aamir Khan provided ‘adequate’ security'

Five Hindu Sena activists were detained from outside the actor's house. Khan was provided with adequate security, a senior police official said on Tuesday.

“We have provided adequate police security to the actor.

There hasn’t been any protest by anyone in the city or at Khan’s house, but we have information that some outfits may hold a protest,” DCP (Detection) Dhananjay Kulkarni told PTI. 
		</body>
	</article>
	<article>
		<title>FIR against Aamir Khan, wife Kiran Rao over intolerance remark</title>
		<body> An FIR was on Friday lodged against Bollywood star Aamir Khan and his wife Kiran Rao in Bihar’s Muzaffarpur district on a court directive for their controversial remarks on “intolerance.”

Advocate Sudhir Kumar Ojha lodged the FIR against the actor and his wife at Town police station in Muzaffarpur district under sections 153 (Wantonly giving provocation with intent to cause riot), 153A (Promoting enmity between different groups on grounds of religion, race, place of birth, residence, language, etc), 153B (Imputations, assertions prejudicial to national-integration) and 154 (Sedition) of IPC.

The FIR was registered on the direction of the chief judicial magistrate, Muzaffarpur district, Sushma Trivedi, on a complaint filed by Mr. Ojha last week charging the actor with hurting the sentiments of the people by claiming that an atmosphere of intolerance prevailed in the country.

Khan had, during a function in Delhi recently, courted controversy by saying that Kiran Rao was considering whether to move out of the country with their child due to the prevalence of an atmosphere of “intolerance.”
	</body>
	</article>
	<article>
		<title>What Aamir Khan is saying, whole world is saying: Congress</title>
		<body> Coming in support of Bollywood star Aamir Khan’s remarks on intolerance, Congress today said what the actor is saying, the whole world is saying and asked the current dispensation to pay heed to the message.

“What Aamir Khan, one of the most respected actors, has said in the presence of many senior BJP people is what the whole world is saying, all of India is saying, all right-minded people are saying,” Congress spokesperson Abhishek Singhvi said here. Mr.Khan, at an award ceremony yesterday, had said that he was “alarmed” by a number of incidents and his wife Kiran Rao had wondered if they should move out of India,

He also supported those returning their awards, saying one of the ways for creative people to express their dissatisfaction or disappointment is to return their awards.

Taking a dig at BJP, Mr. Singhvi said Mr. Khan should not be branded as a Congress man for raising the intolerance issue. “I only hope and trust that he will not be referred to as a Congress man. I will only hope and trust he will not be referred to in derogatory terms,” the Rajya Sabha MP said.

“These are the people whose conscience is speaking. Instead of criticising them, heed should be paid to the message, not shooting the messenger,” he added. 
		</body>
	</article>
	<article>
		<title>Returning awards only way to protest: Gulzar</title>
		<body>
"A writer just speaks from his heart, mind and soul. They are the conscience keepers of the society", says the noted lyricist.

Noted lyricist Gulzar has come out in support of authors returning their Sahitya Akademi awards in protest of the growing religious intolerance in the country, saying this is the only way a writer can register protest.

Many writers have returned their Akademi awards to protest the killing of Kannada writer M M Kalburgi and other growing instances of attacks on intellectuals.

Gulzar, 81, said while the killing was not Akademi’s fault, the authors wanted the institution to recognise and protest against the incident.

“The murder that has hurt us all is somewhere the fault of the system or government... Returning the award was an act of protest. Writers don’t have any other way to register their protest. We have never witnessed this kind of religious intolerance. At least, we were fearless in expressing ourselves,” Gulzar said.

Expressing concern over the growing instances of communal intolerance, he rubbished claims that the writers decision to return the award was politically motivated.

“Never thought that a situation like this would come where a person’s religion is asked before his name. It was never like this... What politics can a writer do? A writer just speaks from his heart, mind and soul. They are the conscience keepers of the society. They are the keepers of the soul of the society,” he said.

In the wake of the authors’ protest, the Sahitya Akademi finally passed a unanimous resolution on Friday appealing to state and central governments to take steps to prevent such incidents and asked authors to take back the awards they had returned to protest against “rising intolerance”. 
		</body>
	</article>
	<article>
		<title>Govt: 39 writers returned Akademi awards</title>
		<body> Forty artists and writers have returned their awards to protest against “recent mishappenings against the writers” and the Sahitya Akademi has requested them to reconsider their decision, the Lok Sabha was informed on Monday.

In response to a question on many literary writers returning awards, Culture Minister Mahesh Sharma said in his written response that “the return of the awards is stated to be in protest against the recent mishappenings against the writers, etc.”

According to the reply, 39 writers have returned their awards to the Sahitya Akademi while one artist has returned his award to the Lalit Kala Akademi.

Several writers, poets and artists had recently returned their awards protesting against the Akademi’s silence on the murder of fellow writer M.M. Kalburgi as well as against the “communal” atmosphere in the backdrop of the Dadri lynching incident. 
		</body>
	</article>
	<article>
		<title>Why we returned Sahitya Akademi awards</title>
		<body>
Sahitya Akademi award winner poet Ashok Vajpeyi explains why he returned his award.

We are now four writers, from three pan-Indian languages i.e. Hindi, Urdu and English, belonging to four generations, who have returned our Sahitya Akademi Award in protest. We are not alone: there are many in most languages and other artistic and intellectual vocations and locations who are feeling equally agitated, angry and anxious. None of us belong to any political party though we have views on politics. But we are extremely worried at the way the India polity is moving. All spaces of liberal values and thought, all locations of dissent and dialogue, all attempts at sanity and mutual trust are under assault almost on a daily basis. All kinds and forms of violence, whether religious and communal, consumerist and globalising, caste-based and cultural, social and domestic, are on the upswing. An ethos of bans, suspicions, hurt feelings is being promoted by many forces that are active and have been emboldened by powers that be, without the slightest fear of law. Democratic rights of expression, faith, privacy etc are being looked down upon and curbed or disrupted without provocation or fault.

A new political hypocrisy has emerged centre-stage: make all the constitutionally correct statements on freedom, liberty, secular fabric, tolerance but keep quiet or dilute or take no action against those who blatantly violate both spirit of the constitution and the rule of law. A citizen almost does not have a fundamental right to life, freedom etc. You can live or be free if they allow you to be so.

A lot of this is being done in the name of Indian tradition and culture. There cannot be a bigger insult or greater damage to the Indian tradition than this. One of the most ancient in the world, this tradition belongs to a civilisational enterprise called India. It is perhaps the largest in the world, unique in its plurality of language, religion, custom, cuisine, costume, craft etc. Nothing in India has remained singular for long, everything sooner or later turns plural or becomes part of a large plural. Not god, nor language, not system of philosophy and reflection, nor faith and worship, not to speak of belief and value. There have always been forces amongst us who do not like this deeply enriching plurality and who would see it replaced by some kind of uniformity which they believe would be more manageable. Our tradition has not only been one of plurality but also of dialogue and accommodation, interrogation and dissent, of public debate, innovation and scrutiny. The shastraarth, one of the unique institution of public testing of ideas and insights used to take place in public between contesting view points. The Indians have never been afraid or intolerant of dissent or debate.

Even gods have been questioned and some of them have been punished when found to be violating the accepted moral or ethical code. Literature in India, even in its democratic history of more than half a century have remained largely anti-establishment. The Emergency, Sikh Riots, demolition of Babri Masjid, Punjab terrorism, Nandigram violence and naxalite and state violence in tribal areas, Gujarat pogroms etc have all provoked writers and artists to protest against and condemn the damage done to social fabric, communal harmony and creative life. They would be failing in their duty if they did not do so. For, good or bad, the creative and reflective community is also believed to be the conscience-keepers of the country. Some of us are only adhering to our own noble tradition of 'speaking truth to power'. So we decided to return the Sahitya Akademi award by way of protest, also to bring to the notice of the public that assaults to our freedom are increasing and we the writers, artists, intellectuals are extremely worried and concerned. 
		</body>
	</article>
	<article>
		<title>Beef ban</title>
		<body>The cow is a very useful animal. Many Indian households, irrespective of their religion, shelter cows for a sustainable income. However, when it becomes unproductive due to old age, its disposal is a difficult choice. Sentimentality apart, there is no denying that for those who cannot afford mutton and other forms of meat, beef is a cheap source of protein. However, against this reality, a myth is being created that in India, millions of cows are being reared just to be killed for the purpose of meat. The resulting hate and mistrust are invariably exploited to reap political dividends. If their sentiments are genuine, the opponents should come up with solutions to deal with unproductive animals. Why not create a mechanism to ensure that every unproductive cow is bought by them at a price and cared for till its natural death? Often, these abandoned animals die a desolate death and their carcasses are eaten away by vultures and wild animals. 
		</body>
	</article>
	<article>
		<title>Holy cow, unholy violence</title>
		<body>
The cow has been converted aggressively into a symbol for a religious orthodoxy demanding its place in a secular nation state.

If you love cows and care for them, you have three choices:

Choice A: Build goshalas or cow shelters where the animals can be taken care of. But this is an expensive proposition. There is heavy investment and no returns whatsoever, despite all the talk of the great medicinal value of cow urine and cow dung.

Choice B: Ban beef, stop farmers from selling cows and bulls to butchers, outlaw the culling of cattle, punish cow smugglers, declare all slaughter houses illegal, lynch people who eat beef, and justify all this using complex arguments. This results in a large number of cows (which can no longer give milk) and bulls or oxen (that are too weak to be draught animals), being abandoned to simply wander the streets eating garbage and plastic or just starving to death since Choice A is unavailable. It also destroys industries and creates widespread unemployment.

Choice C: Build local slaughterhouses near farms so that commercially unviable cattle can be humanely culled nearby, without their having to endure great suffering while being transported in horrible conditions to distant slaughterhouses. This controversial suggestion was made by none other than N.S. Ramaswamy, founder-director of the Indian Institute of Management, Bangalore, and noted animal rights activist.

Guess which is the preferred option of the rising multitude of go-raksha vigilantes? Not A, as it is too expensive and tedious, and involves too much work. Not C, because we are conditioned to believe that violence can do no good. So it is Option B, which has the advantage in that it gives people power. It allows them to terrorise and dominate Muslims and liberals. It gives them global attention and makes them the focus of a controversy-hungry media. It is this rather than cow protection that the go-rakshaks really seek.

There is no love for cows in the go-raksha brigade — an idea systematically and meticulously unravelled in the essay ‘Why is the Cow a Political Animal?’ by Sopan Joshi, a Research Fellow at the Gandhi Peace Foundation, published in Yahoo! in May this year. It is all about power, a yearning to dominate. So, all the talk about the economic reasons for saving cows, and the importance of cow milk, cow urine and cow dung are just a rationalisation for that one single goal: to dominate and reclaim masculinity, following the perceived emasculation by the Muslims, the British and now the liberals.

Devdutt Pattanaik

New form of Hinduism

A new form of Hinduism is emerging around the world: one that is tired of being seen as passive and tolerant, like a suffering docile wife. It wants to be aggressive, violent. So it prefers Durga and Kali to the demure Gauri; Shiva as Rudra and Virabhadra and Bhairava rather than as the guileless Bholenath or the august Dakshinamurthy; and the Krishna of the Mahabharat to the affectionate Bhagavata Krishna. It visualises Ram without Sita. It wants its Ganesh to lose that pot belly and sport a six-pack ab. All this while insisting, with violence if necessary, on the values of vegetarianism and seva and ‘giving up the ego’, which is the principle of ‘sanatana dharma’ — not just a religion but a way of life.

This new form of Hinduism is what we call Hindutva. We can call it a sampradaya, a movement within the vast ocean of Hinduism that has many such movements, traditions, forces and counterforces. Hindutva sampradaya, like all sampradayas in history, insists it is the true voice of Hinduism. Like all sampradayas, it rejects all alternative readings of Hinduism.

And so, when you direct them to an article, ‘The Hindu View on Food and Drink’ by S. Ganesh and Hari Ravikumar on IndiaFacts.com, which draws attention to the fact that while Vedic scriptures do value the cow, they have no problem with the consumption of bulls and oxen and barren cows, members of the Hindutva brigade will question the credentials of the authors and their Hinduness, invariably in language that is hyperbolic, rhetorical and violent. There is no room for discussion or nuance here. The only language is force and bullying. Where is this coming from?

It comes from institutionalised paranoia: a belief that innocent Hindi-speaking rural Bharat needs rescuing from an evil English-speaking India that favours Nehru, from the liberals who equate Hinduism only with casteism, and from Euro-American scholars who insist Shiva is a ‘phallic’ god. And, to be fair, there is a modicum of truth in their argument.

In his book Rearming Hinduism, Vamsee Juluri expresses outrage at the way Hinduism is being projected in the U.S. That outrage and anguish is genuine, and can be felt in the NRI community that has increasingly become more and more vocal, even aggressive. When ‘liberals’ deny this outrage and anguish, it seems to consolidate the paranoia of the Hindutva sampradaya. When the liberal press dismisses the book by Sita Ram Goel, Hindu Temples — What Happened to Them, as right-wing propaganda, and gleefully declares that the Hindu memory of Muslim kings destroying thousands of Hindu temple is just not true on the basis of Richard Eaton’s Temple Desecration and Muslim States in Medieval India, you start wondering if the scientific and historical method is simply designed to mock all things that a traditional Hindu simply assumes to be true. When the banning of radical literature does not meet with the same outrage as the banning of Wendy Doniger’s Hindus: An Alternative History, a section of the population starts feeling that they are alone, isolated and rejected, by the people who claim to be fair and just and liberal.

How do you strike back at those who simply invalidate your memories and beliefs by constantly quoting science and facts? You simply create your own narrative and dismiss theirs. And this is what is happening in the beef-eating discourse. It is a symbolic attack on the ‘educated Indian’ who did not stand up for Hinduism in the international arena. And the Muslims, sadly, are the tragic collateral damage.

In the 1980s, we saw how the then Congress government tried to appease the Muslim orthodoxy in the Shah Bano case by diluting even a Supreme Court judgment that gave maintenance rights to divorced Muslim women, but did not bother to appease the Hindutva sampradaya in the Roop Kanwar sati case when the court declared sati a crime and not a religious act. In these cases, women were simply symbols in a fight where religious orthodoxy was demanding its place in a secular nation state. Now, it is the turn of the cow to be that symbol.

When the secular nation state tilts in favour of one religion and seems to be persecuting another, there is bound to be a backlash. And that is what we are facing now: a karma-phala (karmic fruit) of karmic-bija (karmic seed) sown by the Congress on the one hand, when it unashamedly appeased Muslim religious orthodoxy, and the liberals on the other, who endorsed their secular and rational and atheistic credentials by repeatedly projecting Hinduism as only a violent and oppressive force. Let us ponder on our contribution to the rising tide of ahimsa terrorism, while the still starving ‘rescued’ cow wades through garbage in Indian towns and villages, eating plastic. 
		</body>
	</article>
	<article>
		<title>Standing to reason and reason alone
		</title>
		<body>
While the government and citizens must uphold the Constitution, every law, every statute and every clause is and ought to be subject to public reasoning and re-examined in the court of the latest knowledge and understanding of the world

Soon after the ongoing controversy over the ban on the consumption of beef erupted, we had the ironical situation of its proponents seeking legitimacy by pointing to the Indian Constitution and its opponents seeking credibility through arguments from religious and social traditions.

The framers of the Constitution recommended that the future governments of the Indian republic strive to prevent cow slaughter, largely because the issue was too politically charged for them to settle in the late 1940s. If the creation of a enlightened Constitution upholding liberty and equality was a remarkable achievement for the times, the insertion of the clause — involving hypocrisy and subterfuge, as Frank Anthony put on record in the Constituent Assembly — on cow slaughter was not its finest momoment. On this issue, they effectively passed the buck.

Nitin Pai

As long as it is in our Constitution — and it will probably be there for a long time, given the basic structure doctrine — every generation of Indian citizens will have to deal with the question of cows and their slaughter. To be sure, nothing in the Constitution penalises the possession or consumption of beef, as lynch mobs and politicians would have you believe. Yet those who seek to prevent the slaughter of cows have no less an authority than the Constitution of India on their side.

Then as now, arguments purporting to protect the cattle wealth are sophistry. The only reason there is a Directive Principle concerning cow slaughter is the consideration for Hindu sensibilities.

Invoking tradition

Therefore, perhaps, the opponents of “beef ban” have energetically offered Hindu religious tradition and practice to demonstrate that the slaughter of cows prevailed during Vedic times and that consumption of beef was not uncommon even among brahmins. The great Upanishadic sage Yajnavalkya is reported to have consumed beef only if were tender. Both the Ramayana and Mahabharata mention the consumption of beef. Charaka, Sushruta and Vagbhata, known for their treatises on medicine, refer to the therapeutic uses of beef.

K. T. Achaya, a delightful scholar of Indian food, writes that “beef was freely eaten: there are four names for this meat in the early Tamil language, showing that it was a common and well-liked food. He also notes that by the time of Al-Biruni’s visits to India in the 11th century CE, social attitudes had turned against the eating of beef. Even so, many communities in different parts of India continue to eat beef — not all Hindus share the same sensibilities. There is no hard and fast rule against beef within the parameters of the broad Hindu faith.

However, whether or not the ancient Hindus ate beef is beside the point. The question of whether the Indian republic ought to be concerned with cow slaughter is not a sectarian one. It should be answered from the ground of reason. For our Constitution is not grounded on theology or tradition but firmly in the Enlightenment values of reason, individualism and liberty. There was no precedent for equality of citizens, fundamental rights and universal franchise in Indian tradition, until the Constitution came along in 1950. The Indian state is a Republic of Reason, not an altar at which the tenets of the many faiths and spiritual paths of the Indian nation are worshipped.

Democratic imperative

So the arguments for and against the beef ban must be based on reason. If democracy is not to become an instrument to impose majoritarian mores on the entire population, the only way is to use reason for public persuasion.

Of course, it is hard to single out the cow for special protection on any rational ground, but there is a case for vegetarianism Michael Pollan, who considers some of the ethical dimensions of our diet in The Omnivore’s Dilemma: A Natural History of Four Meals, contends that “were the walls of our meat industry to become transparent, literally or even figuratively, we would not long continue to raise, kill, and eat animals the way we do.” It is possible to persuade people of the merits of vegetarianism without recourse to sanctimony.

Similarly, the case against the beef ban ought to rely on science, public health, nutrition and economics. There is enough evidence that beef is a relatively inexpensive way for the poor to have access to dietary protein, and thus is useful in tackling the widespread malnutrition in our country.

Now many prominent participants in the beef controversy are engaged in it solely to reap dividends of the politics of bigotry. Yet the issue of cow slaughter and beef consumption is an unsettled question of public policy that we, for the reason that it is in our Constitution, must find ways of setting to rest. The more we use public reasoning to argue the matter, the less space we give to divisive politics by cow.

It is popularly argued that solutions can be found within the religious framework — all we need to do is empower the moderates and they will persuade the extremists. In societies where the effects of the European Enlightenment have been indirect or peripheral, this seldom happens. For instance, in countries where Islam is dominant, it is unlikely that moderate Muslims will be able to prevail over their less moderate counterparts.

Liberal fallacy

As Sam Harris (founder of Project Reason) puts it, “ [while] moderation in religion may seem a reasonable position to stake out...it offers no bulwark against religious extremism and religious violence. The problem that religious moderation poses for all of us is that it does not permit anything very critical to be said about religious literalism. We cannot say that fundamentalists are crazy, because they are merely practicing their freedom of belief; we cannot even say that they are mistaken in religious terms, because their knowledge of scripture is generally unrivalled. All we can say, as religious moderates, is that we don’t like the personal and social costs that a full embrace of scripture imposes on us. This is not a new form of faith, or even a new species of scriptural exegesis; it is simply a capitulation...”

We must not, therefore, play the game according to the rules and out-of-bounds markers set by a religion, or indeed, by all of them.

While our modern Constitution enjoins us to do so, the use of reason and critical inquiry in public policy is not something that started in 1950. The Arthashastra is a strong advocate of the use of reason in politics, holding that the “study of critical inquiry is always thought of as a lamp for all branches of knowledge, a means in all activities, and a support for all religious and social duty”.

It is unambiguous in placing reason and critical inquiry above other considerations: “Investigating by means of reasons, good and evil in the Vedic religion, profit and loss in the field of trade and agriculture, and prudent and imprudent policy in political administration, as well as their relative strengths and weaknesses, the study of critical inquiry (anvikshiki) confers benefit on people, keeps their minds steady in adversity and in prosperity, and produces adeptness of understanding, speech and action.” (Arthashastra, 1.2.11).

This tradition of reason in our politics is too precious to be allowed to fall victim to dogmatic assertions of the primacy of tradition, theology or indeed clauses in the Constitution.

Narendra Modi, first as candidate and then as Prime Minister has stated that the Constitution is the government’s only holy book. In doing so, he was trying to reassure the world that his government will not engage in discrimination on the basis of religion, caste or creed.

While we can appreciate the sentiment behind the Prime Minister’s words, we must remember that the concept of a ‘holy book’ is antithetical to a society that organises its public affairs around reason.

Of course, government and citizens must uphold the Constitution and live by its lights. That said, every law, every statute and every clause is and ought to be subject to public reasoning. For instance, the criminalisation of homosexuality, the existence of multiple personal laws, the low bar to what is considered sedition and indeed the advice against cow slaughter — to name a few contemporary issues from our penal code and Constitution — must be re-examined in the court of the latest knowledge and understanding of the world.

They should stand only when they stand to reason.


		</body>
	</article>
	<article>
		<title>Leaving beef bans to the States
		</title>
		<body> Even as some of its State units — within and outside government — have shown a zeal in seeking to toughen laws on cow slaughter, the Bharatiya Janata Party (BJP) has nationally been more guarded about the issue. The BJP government in Haryana announced that it is instituting a law that provides for a 10-year prison sentence for those caught slaughtering cattle. In doing so, it has taken its cue from its counterpart in Maharashtra which extended the ban on cow slaughter to all cattle, even as two other BJP-ruled States, Jharkhand and Rajasthan, are considering similar legislation. Reports also suggest that in West Bengal — a State that permits cow slaughter with a “fit for slaughter” certificate — the BJP State unit is seeking to deploy vigilante groups to prevent the ferrying of cows to Bangladesh for slaughter. This activist zeal by the BJP in the States contrasts with the party’s national position. While Prime Minister Narendra Modi had attacked the “pink revolution” — the export of cattle meat — during last year’s general election, his government has not changed its meat export policy since then. That policy prohibits the export of the meat of cows, bulls, calves, any milching bovine or calves less than four months old. Only the meat of non-milching buffaloes, along with that of goats, is allowed to be exported.

Even though most States, except Kerala and parts of the northeast, have laws of varying degree banning cow slaughter, it is a sensitive subject. Beef and buffalo meat are sources of cheap protein not just among sections of the minorities, but also for poor Hindus. The BJP has also not forgotten a speech made in the Lok Sabha by the late G.G. Swell, an MP from Meghalaya, in 1996 during the party’s 13-day tenure in government. On that occasion, Swell spoke about the intolerance of the BJP and its inability to accept that in parts of India, including large swathes in the northeast, beef is a cultural, culinary preference. More recently, in Kerala, leaders belonging to the Congress and the Communist Party of India (Marxist) have described the efforts by BJP-ruled States as a “sign of increasing encroachment of personal liberty and democratic freedom”. While Central ministers have ruled out a Central law as livestock is a State subject, even hardline Hindutva-oriented BJP MPs like Yogi Adityanath say that it is important to let the government focus on development for some more time. The national executive of the BJP has remained silent on the issue since its government came to power. Clearly, the party will calibrate its position on the issue in the long run, not letting it distract attention from its reforms agenda. 
		</body>
	</article>
	<article>
		<title>Juvenile could walk free on December 20
		</title>
		<body>
High Court declines to issue any direction to continue the stay of the juvenile, who is now an adult, in the observation home beyond Dec. 20

The juvenile convict in the December 16, 2012 Nirbhaya gang rape case moved closer to freedom on Friday after the Delhi High Court refused to stop his release on his completing the three-year sentence. The court cited existing provisions of the law while holding that no direction could be issued to prolong his stay in the observation home beyond Sunday.

A Division Bench of the High Court, hearing a writ petition moved by BJP leader Subramanian Swamy, said the maximum stay that could be directed in the observation home under Section 15 (1) of the Juvenile Justice (Care and Protection of Children) Act was three years. The juvenile, who is now an adult, will be completing three years on December 20.

Also read: Crime has won and we have lost, says mother of victim

However, the Bench, comprising Chief Justice G. Rohini and Justice Jayant Nath, directed the Juvenile Justice (JJ) Board of Delhi to interact with the juvenile, his parents and guardians and the Delhi government’s Women and Child Development Department officials for his post-release rehabilitation and “social mainstreaming.”

For this, the JJ Board, which had sentenced the juvenile to three years’ detention, will pass appropriate orders in accordance with the provisions of the Juvenile Justice Act and Rules. The court in its seven-page order referred to legal provisions for individual care plan, periodic review and follow-up, social investigation and reducing the juvenile's vulnerability.

The petition, seeking a stay on the release, said the boy had been “radicalised” by another youth accused in the Delhi High Court blast case of 2011 lodged in the same observation home. In response to the petition, the Centre had sought extension of his stay in the observation home at Majnu Ka Tila here, till all aspects, including his mental health and post-release rehabilitation plan, were considered by the authorities. The court had also sought an Intelligence Bureau report, in a sealed cover, about him having been radicalised. The court pronounced the order in the presence of Dr. Swamy and the rape victim’s parents and posted the case for further hearing on March 28, 2016.

Social activist Shabana Azmi consoles Narbhaya's Mother Asha Devi at a programme to observe the third anniversary of Nirbhaya gang-rape case as 'Nirbhaya Chetna Divas' at Jantar Mantar in New Delhi on Wednesday. (PTI)

Centre told to file response in 8 weeks

While asking the Union government to file its response within eight weeks on the issue of reformation of juveniles, the Bench directed that the Delhi government be impleaded as a respondent to the petition.

The court pointed out that Rule 17 (3) of JJ Rules provides for individual care plan, reviewed from time to time by the management committee set up under Rule 55, while Rule 65 provides for restoration of juvenile to the family and follow-up action. The rule also provides for submission of a quarterly follow-up report to the JJ Board for two years, said the court.

The brutal incident of the gang rape of a 23-year-old girl by six persons, including the juvenile, in a moving bus here on December 16, 2012 had shocked the nation. Four of the accused were awarded the death penalty by the trial court, which was later confirmed by the Delhi High Court, while one accused allegedly committed suicide in Tihar Jail. 
		</body>
	</article>
	<article>
		<title>Will SC seek proof of reformation?
		</title>
		<body> On Monday, the Supreme Court will have the opportunity to declare the law on whether it was injustice to release a juvenile convict involved in a brutal crime in compliance with the written law and without proof to show he has reformed.

The court may take a call on whether it should adjudicate within the narrow limits of the Juvenile Justice Act and release the juvenile convict or demand his mental assessment reports to show three years in a special home has reformed him and that he is no longer a threat to society.

If the court prima facie believes the contention of Delhi Commission for Women (DCW) chairperson Swati Maliwal that the juvenile convict is a “serious threat to society,” a Bench of Justices A.K. Goel and U.U. Lalit can use extraordinary powers under Article 142 to do “complete justice.”

The Bill prescribing that juveniles aged 16-18 and accused of heinous offences, as in this case, should be tried as adults, is stuck in the Rajya Sabha.

The Juvenile Justice Act, as it stands now, only requires juvenile offenders to spend three years in a special home. It is somehow expected by this law that they would reform within this time and be ready to be assimilated back into society.

The statute does not distinguish between juvenile offenders guilty of heinous crimes and those in care homes for lesser offences. The statute banks on the legal fiction that all juveniles commit crime without mens rea (intention) and need to be reformed.

The Supreme Court itself had recently poked holes in the juvenile law. “There can be a situation where a commission of an offence may be totally innocuous or emerging from a circumstance where a young boy is not aware of the consequences. But in cases of rape, dacoity, murder, which are heinous crimes, it is extremely difficult to conceive that the juvenile was not aware of the consequences,” Justice Dipak Misra said in a recent order.

Legal experts argue that there is no other choice but to release the juvenile convict as there is no clear statutory backing to continue his detention. But the DCW’s petition contends that there are other alternatives to releasing the convict. One of them is Rule 32 of the Delhi Juvenile Justice (Care and Protection of Children) Rules, 2009, which envisages long-term institutional care as a last resort in serious cases like the present one. The convict should not be released from institutional care until his mental assessment finds him fit for social reintegration and rehabilitation, the DCW argues.

Again DCW lawyers intend to interpret a proviso in Section 16 of the Juvenile Justice Act, 2000 (Amendment in 2006), which says a juvenile offender can be kept in “protective custody” by the State government for whatever period it thinks fit.

“There is a serious apprehension considering the heinous nature of the crime committed by the respondent [the juvenile convict] as well as his behaviour and attitude in a special home confirmed by the government agencies that the respondent may continue to have criminal/perverse bent of mind, which poses a serious threat to women in particular and society at large,” the DCW contends.

The petition contends that the juvenile has shown no remorse and quotes from an Intelligence Bureau report that he has even been “radicalised.” It further says his release now will also spell danger to himself: there is a possibility that he may be lynched. This would further muddy the waters for a justice administration system, which believes that rule of law reigns supreme. 
		</body>
	</article>
	<article>
		<title>‘Unsure if justice done in Nirbhaya case’
		</title>
		<body> Ahead of the release of the juvenile convict in the Nirbhaya gangrape case next month, Union Minister Maneka Gandhi has expressed helplessness in extending punishment to him. While the law was adhered to, she was not sure whether justice was done in this most gruesome case.

She advocated that a “close watch” be kept on the accused after he is freed on his completing the sentence. She would raise this issue with the authorities.

“Let us not confuse justice with the law. The law said that he could only go to a children’s home... That’s the anomaly we are trying to correct. So he served his sentence and, in accordance with the law, he is coming out. And there is nothing we can do about it until or unless he commits another crime. So that is all we can do.

“I don’t know whether justice has been served, but certainly the law has been adhered to,” the Minister said. “Yes, I am afraid we are,” she said when asked if the government was waiting for him to commit another crime.

“He is a person who should be kept under watch. We can’t just let him go and wait for him to do something else,” she said.

The juvenile found guilty in the 2012 Delhi gangrape will be released on December 15. He has turned 21 and will complete his three-year term at the prohibition centre.

At 17-and-a-half, he was the youngest of six men who raped and brutally tortured the 23-year-old medical student on a moving bus in the capital.

The victim died 13 days later in a hospital in Singapore, where she was taken for treatment by the government.

Four other men found guilty in the case are on death row. 
		</body>
	</article>
	<article>
		<title>Apex Court dismisses plea against release of juvenile
		</title>
		<body> Putting the onus on lawmakers, the Supreme Court on Monday dismissed a plea by the Delhi Commission for Women against the release of the juvenile convict in the Nirbhaya gang-rape case. It observed: “We share your concern, but we cannot go beyond the law.”

“We cannot interpret the law [the Juvenile Justice Act] to curtail his [the juvenile convict’s] freedom without legislative sanction. We share your concern, but we cannot go beyond the statute,” observed Justice U.U. Lalit, one of the judges on the Bench led by Justice A.K. Goel.

When the government said that it supported DCW chairperson Swati Maliwal Jaihind’s plea that the convict not be released until he was reformed, Justice Goel said: “You are saying [this] without the law backing you...go first make the law.”

Are you for detention or rehabilitation, asks court

The Supreme Court, which dismissed a plea by the Delhi Commission for Women against the release of the juvenile convict in the Nirbhaya gang-rape case on Monday, posed the question whether the period of detention would have to be extended if the reformation takes more time.

“Suppose the reformation takes another seven or ten years. Do we have to extend the period of his detention every now and then without any legislative sanction,” Justice U.U. Lalit, one of the judges on the Bench led by Justice A.K. Goel, asked senior advocate Guru Krishnakumar and advocate Devadutt Kamat, appearing for DCW chairperson Swati Maliwal.

Mr. Krishnakumar quoted provisions in the Juvenile Justice Act and the Delhi Juvenile Justice Rules to argue for an independent committee to review the convict’s mental status and keep him under protective custody till he was reformed and was not a threat to society. “Are you for the rehabilitation of the child or for the detention of the child,” Justice Goel asked.

Mr. Krishnakumar quoted Rule 38 [after care organisation] of the Delhi Juvenile [Care and Protection] Justice Act, 2009, which allows for care and monitoring after release. “He need not be considered outside the realm of law on release. This provision can be used for two years till he attains the age of 21,” he said.

But the court said the provision was available only to convicts who had no place to go after their release. “Sorry Mr. Kumar, you don’t have a case here,” Justice Lalit said, concluding the hearing.

The much-publicised last-ditch attempt to prevent his release began on the eve of his release on Saturday night when DCW members knocked on the doors of the Supreme Court. The petition made the overnight journey from the residence of Chief Justice of India T.S. Thakur to the vacation Bench of Justices Goel and Lalit. The Bench decided to hear it on Monday as item number three on their cause list.

Meanwhile, the Delhi Police, acting on the fact that the convict’s release was not stayed by the Supreme Court, released him to an NGO on December 20. He is now being kept at an undisclosed location, reportedly near his village in U.P. 
		</body>
	</article>
	<article>
		<title>Internet power to the people
		</title>
		<body>
TRAI’s vigorous endorsement of net neutrality safeguards the Internet against platform monopolies, retaining the ability for users not only to be consumers but also creators of content

The regulations issued by the Telecom Regulatory Authority of India (TRAI) barring differential pricing of data based on content have created a global impact. A friend, who runs a major international software company, called it the most important victory for the people in the tech space in the last 20 years. India has joined a select few countries that have protected net neutrality and barred zero-rating services.

What makes this “victory” even more surprising was the complete asymmetry of the two sides involved. On one side was Facebook, a company whose market cap is greater than the GDPs of 144 countries, allied with a bunch of big telecom companies (telcos). They had already “won” easy victories for their platform in a number of countries, and felt India would be no exception. They had an ad campaign that estimates put at Rs.400 crore. On the other side was a motley group of free software and Internet activists, with unlikely allies such as comedy group AIB, a bunch of start-ups, and some political figures and formations.

The argument that Facebook was using appeared simple. Why should anybody deny the poor getting some access to the Internet — even if this was limited? Isn’t something better than nothing? Mark Zuckerberg not only wrote articles terming his opponents “Net Neutrality fundamentalists”, but also appeared in advertorials in the electronic media to push Free Basics. Some commentators wrote plugs for Facebook in the guise of opinion pieces, all more or less posing different variations of the broad theme that Zuckerberg’s heart beats for the Indian poor.

To beat back such an offensive, backed by the full power of Facebook’s media blitz, was no ordinary event. So why did Facebook’s campaign fail?

People’s campaign prevails

First is, of course, the energy and the creativity of the groups fighting Free Basics. They not only ran an innovative and creative campaign, but were also able to bring tech activists on to the streets. What surprised even them was the response of the people.

I am convinced that Facebook and their ad agencies completely underestimated the Indian public. Even if all of them do not use the Internet, they understand the difference between having access to the full Internet, with nearly a billion websites, and the so-called Free Basics platform that provides Facebook and a few other sites. They are sophisticated enough to know that Free Basics would not offer them any of the things they really want to access. No search, no email, no access to various services; no pictures or video clips for entertainment either. No access to the rich diversity of views and material on the Internet. Only a sterile walled garden where, at best, you can see what your friends are doing.

A level playing field

What is the flip side of such a platform? Other people who want to have the full Internet could still access it, so why is Facebook’s Free Basics harmful?

TRAI has correctly pointed out that the tariff principle at play is whether we can have differential pricing of data based on the content we see. If we accept this principle, what then prevents telcos from charging various websites and Internet services for accessing their subscribers? Accepting that one form of price discrimination is okay opens the door to all other forms of discrimination as well.

This is where Net Neutrality comes in. The most important characteristic of the Internet is whether it is the richest corporation in the world or an individual writing a blog, both are treated identically on the Internet. If the blogger had to negotiate with the Internet service providers (ISPs) — in today’s world the telcos — to reach the telco subscribers, she would have to negotiate with thousands of such ISPs. Telcos would then be the gatekeepers of the Internet. Only the biggest corporations could then survive on the Net. This is how the cable TV model works; for their channels to be carried, the TV channels have to negotiate with all the platforms such as Dish TV, Tata Sky, etc. If we accept that telcos can act as gatekeepers, we would then lose what has given the Internet its unique power, the ability for us not only to be consumers but also creators of content.

In its nascent phase, the big telco monopolies tried to levy a “tax” on all Internet content providers. The Internet companies were then the new kids on the block. They and the Internet user community fought back such attempts. This was the first net neutrality war, and it established the principle of non-discrimination on the Internet between different types of content or sites.

The scenario has changed dramatically today. We have the emergence of powerful Internet monopolies that are much bigger than the telcos. Not surprisingly, these companies now see the virtues of monopoly. They would like to combine with telcos to create monopolies for their platforms, ensuring that they control the future of the Internet and freeze their competition out.

Today, we have nearly a billion websites on the Internet and 3.5 billion users. This means that nearly one out of three users is both a content provider as well as content consumer. What the Internet monopolies want is that we should be passive consumers of their content, or at best generate captive content only for their platforms. This is why they have joined hands with telcos to offer various forms of zero-rating services.

Future-proofing policies

The two most common forms of zero rating used by telcos are (a) no data charges for a select set of sites, e.g. Facebook’s Free Basics, and (b) a few content providers such as Netflix not being subjected to data caps by telcos. The TRAI order bars both these forms.

The other issue that TRAI dealt with is whether regulatory policies should be crafted to prevent harm (ex ante) or be applied only after harm has been established. The argument of the telcos has been, “prove there has been harm, otherwise we should be allowed to do as we please”. TRAI has again correctly pointed out that not crafting the right policies for the Internet would distort the basic character of the Internet itself. It would then help the well heeled, who would be able to take advantage of a lack of policy. The TRAI order also points out that without the right policies, each tariff proposal would have to be analysed on a case-by-case basis, imposing high regulatory overheads.

The last issue we need to examine is how a powerful monopoly can bend policy by virtue of its control over its users. Facebook not only launched a media blitz but also ran a completely misleading campaign on Free Basics to its 130 million Indian subscribers. Through its various pop-ups and user interface, it pressured its users to send TRAI a boilerplate statement of support for Free Basics. It even painted this as providing basic Internet to the poor, without informing its users that Facebook was the sole arbiter of what constitutes a basic Internet.

The question is, can a platform monopoly — of the type Facebook, Google are — use this monopoly to run a campaign on a country’s policy? Facebook is a foreign entity and has argued before Indian courts that it is not accountable to Indian laws. Should such entities have such power over our peoples’ lives?

A media company is supposed to differentiate between advertisements and news. Facebook did not identify its plug for its Free Basics platform on Facebook as opinion but presented it as truth. How should online media conduct itself in the future on such issues?

TRAI had rebuked Facebook on its attempt to convert TRAI’s consultation on differential pricing to a numbers game. TRAI wanted clear answers to the questions they had posed, not boilerplate emails saying how people loved Free Basics. But it still leaves unanswered the question of what are the rights and duties of such platform monopolies towards their users. With Google and Facebook emerging bigger than many nation states, this is the key question for the Internet in the future. 
		</body>
	</article>
	<article>
		<title>TRAI rules in favour of Net neutrality
		</title>
		<body> “No service provider shall offer or charge discriminatory tariffs for data services on the basis of content,” the regulator ruled in its Prohibition of Discriminatory Tariffs for Data Services Regulations, 2016. It said the prohibition was necessary to keep the Internet open and non-discriminatory.

TRAI said a fine of Rs. 50,000 would be levied per day, subject to a maximum of Rs. 50 lakh, for any violation of these regulations by the service providers. An exemption, however, has been made for offering emergency services.

Ruling out case-by-case approval for plans that might be priced differently, the regulator said a clear policy should be formulated.

No differential rates for data services, rules TRAI

“We had issued a consultation paper just about 60 days ago on differential pricing …We deliberated on the issue for quite some time … Anything on Internet cannot be differently priced. This is the broad point that we have highlighted in the regulation,” TRAI Chairman R.S. Sharma told reporters at a conference.

The regulator and Facebook have been at loggerheads over the issue with the authority terming the social networking giant’s attempt to lobby for its Free Basics initiative a “crude” attempt at turning the consultation over differential pricing of data services into an “orchestrated opinion poll” on Free Basics. Facebook had partnered with Reliance Communications in India to offer Free Basics service. However, the services were put in abeyance, post a TRAI order to this effect.

Disappointed: Facebook

In an emailed statement, a Facebook spokesperson said, “While disappointed with the outcome, we will continue our efforts to eliminate barriers and give the unconnected an easier path to the Internet and the opportunities it brings.”

The TRAI said tariff for data services could not vary on the basis of the website/application/ platform/ or type of content being accessed. For example, a consumer could not be charged differently based on whether she was browsing social media site A or B, or on whether she was watching streaming videos or shopping on the Internet, it added.

It, however, said that to bring more users on the Internet, this prohibition would not apply to other forms of tariff differentiation that were entirely independent of content. “For instance, providing limited free data that enables user to access the entire Internet is not prohibited,” the TRAI said.

While the move was cheered by Net Neutrality activists and industry bodies such as Nasscom and IAMAI, telecom operators, who had been pushing for allowing of differential tariff for data service, expressed disappointment saying the ruling would impact the Narendra Modi government’s ambitious Digital India initiative.

Rajan Mathews, Director-General of operators’ body COAI, told The Hindu: “We are very disappointed with the ruling. Differential pricing is an effective marketing tool and would have helped in bringing online the next one billion people. We are confused as the decision comes at a time when the government is pushing adoption of Internet.”

“It will negatively impact the growth of the industry and the consumers who may need such plans to afford data connections. We are looking at this closely to examine TRAI’s rationale as to how this purportedly hurts customers or negatively impacts markets or even hinders internet access,” he said.

Hemant Joshi, Partner, Deloitte Haskins & Sells LLP, said differential pricing for different levels of services was a well-accepted principle across all industries and the concept inherently recognised the economic principle of paying differently for different levels of service and experience.

“For example, the differential pricing for the 2nd class, 1st AC, sleeper class, etc. based on different experiences and service levels … In the telecom sector there are virtual highways that need to follow the same principle. EU is considering allowing ‘specialised services’ with few priority services having fast lane Internet connection. More awareness and education needed around the economics of differential pricing and its long-term implications on the industry and the consumer,” Mr. Joshi said.

Amresh Nandan, Research Director, Gartner, said while operators might not be happy with this notification, they still have the ability and freedom to create different kind of Internet access packages as long as content was not a parameter to provide or bar access to anyone. “Such practices have already started elsewhere with products such as bandwidth on demand, bandwidth calendaring etc. to create premium products. Obviously it will require changes in network and operations but that’s where the telecom road map goes,” he added.

Positive indication

Meanwhile, Net Neutrality activists see it as a positive indication for future regulations on issues such as regulation of over the top applications such as WhatsApp and Skype.

“The regulations are very progressive. They do not seek a middle ground but take a clear stand …We do expect a positive response on the larger issue of Net Neutrality,” said Karthik Balakrishnan, a member of Savetheinternet.

As per the regulations released on Monday, existing plans which are in contravention of the rules can continue for six months, post which they will need to be stopped. Within few hours of the regulations being released, Net Neutrality was the top most trending topic on Twitter in India. 
		</body>
	</article>
	<article>
		<title>Access at the cost of Net neutrality?
		</title>
		<body>
In the Net neutrality debate, there is a conflict between two core values: ease of access and neutrality. The ease of access promised by applications like Free Basics compromises neutrality and may later morph into a method of predatory pricingIf programs that bring access to a part of the Internet in the immediate future were to entrench themselves, it could eventually lead to telecom companies abusing their dominant positionsIn the absence of a specific law mandating a neutral Internet, telecom companies enjoy a virtual carte blanche to discriminate between different applications. Though they have not yet exploited this autonomy fully, they are certainly moving towards that.

Earlier this year, the social media giant, Facebook, formalised a partnership with Reliance Communications that enabled the Indian company to provide access to over 30 different websites, without any charge on mobile data accruing to the ultimate user. The platform, originally known as “Internet.org,” has now been rebranded as “Free Basics,” Facebook announced last month. Its fundamental ethos, though, remains unchanged. It allows Reliance’s subscribers to surf completely free of cost a bouquet of websites covered within the scheme, which includes, quite naturally, facebook.com. Mark Zuckerberg, Facebook’s founder, views this supposed initiative as a philanthropic gesture, as part of a purported, larger aim to bring access to the Internet to those people who find the costs of using generally available mobile data prohibitive.

Neutrality, an interpretive concept

On the face of it, this supposed act of altruism appears to be commendable. But, there are many critics — some of whom have come together to launch a website “savetheinternet.in” with a view to defending Internet freedom — who argue that Free Basics violates what has come to be known as the principle of network (or Net) neutrality.

While it is clear to all of us that a notion of Net neutrality involves some regulation of the Internet, it is less clear what the term actually means. Like any phrase that involves either a moral or a legal obligation, Net neutrality is also an interpretive concept. People who employ the term to denote some sort of binding commitment, or at the least an aspirational norm, often tend to disagree over precisely how the idea ought to be accomplished. Tim Wu — an American lawyer and presently a professor at the Columbia University — who coined the term, views the notion of Net neutrality as signifying an Internet that does not favour any one application over another. In other words, the idea is to ensure that Internet service providers do not discriminate content by either charging a fee for acting as its carrier or by incorporating any technical qualifications.

In India, there is no law that expressly mandates the maintenance of a neutral Internet. This March, the Telecom Regulatory Authority of India (TRAI) released a draft consultation paper seeking the public’s views on whether the Internet needed regulation. Unfortunately, much of its attention was focussed on the supposedly pernicious impact of applications such as WhatsApp and Viber. “In a multi-ethnic society there is a vital need,” wrote TRAI, “to ensure that the social equilibrium is not impacted adversely by communications that inflame passions, disturb law and order and lead to sectarian disputes.” The questions, therefore, in its view were these: should at least some Internet applications be amenable to a greater regulation, and should they compensate the telecom service providers in addition to the data charges that the consumers pay directly for the use of mobile Internet?

If the government eventually answers these questions in the affirmative, the consequences could be drastic. It could lead to a classification of Internet applications based on arbitrary grounds, by bringing some of them, whom the government views as harmful to society in some manner or another, within its regulatory net. Through such a move, the state, contrary to helping establish principles of Net neutrality as a rule of law, would be actively promoting an unequal Internet.

In any event, as things stand, in the absence of a specific law mandating a neutral Internet, telecom companies enjoy a virtual carte blanche to discriminate between different applications. Though these companies have not yet completely exploited this autonomy, they are certainly proceeding towards such an exercise. In April this year, Airtel announced Airtel Zero, an initiative that would allow applications to purchase data from Airtel in exchange for the telecom company offering them to consumers free of cost.

On the face of it, this programme appears opposed to Net neutrality. But what is even more alarming is that mobile Internet service providers could, in the future, plausibly also control the speeds at which different applications are delivered to consumers. For example, if WhatsApp were to subscribe to Airtel Zero by paying the fee demanded by the company, Airtel might accede to offering WhatsApp to consumers at a pace superior to that at which other applications are run. This kind of discrimination, as Nikhil Pahwa, one of the pioneers of the Save The Internet campaign, has argued, is prototypically opposed to Net neutrality. It tends to breed an unequal playing field, and, if allowed to subsist, it could create a deep division in the online world. Ultimately, we must view Net neutrality as a concept that stands for the values that we want to build as a society; it pertains to concerns about ensuring freedom of expression and about creating an open space for ideas where democracy can thrive. There is a tendency, though, to view those who support Net neutrality as representing a supercilious position. Such criticism is unquestionably blinkered, but it also highlights certain telling concerns.

Telecom companies that wish to discriminate between applications argue that in the absence of an Internet that has completely permeated all strata of society, an obligation to maintain neutrality is not only unreasonable on the companies, but also unfair on the consumer. After all, if nothing else, Airtel Zero and Free Basics bring, at the least, some portions of the Internet to people who otherwise have no means to access the web. What we have, therefore, at some level, is a clash of values: between access to the Internet (in a limited form) and the maintenance of neutrality in an atmosphere that is inherently unequal. This makes tailoring a solution to the problem a particularly arduous process.

The Internet, in its purest form, is a veritable fountain of information. At its core lies a commitment to both openness and a level playing field, where an ability to innovate is perennially maintained. It is difficult to argue against Facebook when it says that some access is better than no access at all. But one of the problems with Free Basics, and indeed with Airtel Zero too, is that the consumer has no choice in which websites he or she might want to access free of cost. If this decision is made only by Facebook, which might argue that it gives every developer an equal chance to be a part of its project as long as it meets a certain criteria, what we have is almost a paternalistic web. In such a situation, information, far from being free, is shackled by constraints imposed by the service provider.

Laudable end, unethical means

This is precisely one of the concerns raised by those arguing in favour of Net neutrality, who, it is worth bearing in mind, aren’t resistant to the idea of a greater penetration of the Internet. Their apprehensions lie in companies resorting to what they believe is an unethical means to achieving, at least in theory, a laudable end. According to them, negating Net neutrality, in a bid to purportedly achieve greater access to the Internet in the immediate future, could prove profoundly injurious in the long run. Yes, Airtel Zero and Free Basics would bring to the less-privileged amongst us some access to the Internet, but the question is this: at what cost?

The worry is that if the programs that bring access to a part of the Internet in the immediate future were to entrench themselves, it could eventually lead to these telecom companies abusing their dominant positions. No doubt, as Pranesh Prakash, policy director at the Centre for Internet and Society, has argued, it might require a deeper analysis to argue convincingly that packages such as Free Basics and Airtel Zero require immediate invalidation in their present forms; significantly, the former does not demand payments from the applications while the latter is premised on such consideration. But, viewed holistically, the companies’ actions could potentially be characterised as a form of predatory pricing, where consumers might benefit in the short run, only for serious damage to ensue to competition in the long run.

It is, therefore, necessary that any debate on the issue must address the tension between the two apparently conflicting goals — the importance of maintaining a neutral Internet and the need to ensure a greater access to the web across the country. Mr. Zuckerberg argues that these two values are not fundamentally opposed to each other, but can — and must — coexist. He is possibly correct at a theoretical level.

But the history of markets tells us that we have to be very careful in allowing predatory practices, devised to achieve short-term goals, to go unbridled. As citizens, each of us has a fundamental right to freedom of speech and expression. If we were to get the balance between these two values wrong, if we were to allow the domination, by a few parties, of appliances that facilitate a free exchange of ideas, in a manner that impinges on the Internet’s neutrality, our most cherished civil liberties could well be put to grave danger.

(Suhrith Parthasarathy is an advocate in the Madras High Court.)

Read more about net neutrality

Net neutrality
Net neutrality is a principle that says Internet Service Providers (ISPs) should treat all traffic and content on their networks equally.
How does net neutrality affect you?

The internet is now a level-playing field. Anybody can start up a website, stream music or use social media with the same amount of data that they have purchased with a particular ISP. But in the absence of neutrality, your ISP might favour certain websites over others for which you might have to pay extra. Website A might load at a faster speed than Website B because your ISP has a deal with Website A that Website B cannot afford. It’s like your electricity company charging you extra for using the washing machine, television and microwave oven above and beyond what you are already paying.
Why now?

Late last month, Trai released a draft consultation paper seeking views from the industry and the general public on the need for regulations for over-the-top (OTT) players such as Whatsapp, Skype, Viber etc, security concerns and net neutrality. The objective of this consultation paper, the regulator said, was to analyse the implications of the growth of OTTs and consider whether or not changes were required in the current regulatory framework.
What is an OTT?

OTT or over-the-top refers to applications and services which are accessible over the internet and ride on operators' networks offering internet access services. The best known examples of OTT are Skype, Viber, WhatsApp, e-commerce sites, Ola, Facebook messenger. The OTTs are not bound by any regulations. The Trai is of the view that the lack of regulations poses a threat to security and there’s a need for government’s intervention to ensure a level playing field in terms of regulatory compliance.

		</body>
	</article>
	<article>
		<title>The Panama paper trail
		</title>
		<body> As the ramifications of the leak of about 11 million secret documents from the Panama-based law firm, Mossack Fonseca, play themselves out, a clear articulation of what the “Panama Papers” hold for the state of global finance today came from U.S. President Barack Obama. Following the joint investigation by the International Consortium of Investigative Journalists and the German newspaper Süddeutsche Zeitung into the leaked papers, Mr. Obama described global tax avoidance as a huge problem. Today, it is perfectly legal in many countries to park money in various kinds of shadowy companies in tax havens. This holds true in India as well, where a lack of clarity persists about the legality of buying offshore companies, a service that is expressly provided by Mossack Fonseca. The lack of clarity exists despite the Reserve Bank of India’s evolving guidelines on offshore remittances and investments since 2004. While the guidelines, such as those of the Liberalised Remittance Scheme, are specific to remittances utilised by residents to service various overseas requirements such as medical treatment and education, they have been modified over time to permit the setting up of 100 per cent subsidiaries and joint ventures within the limit of $250,000 a year. One of the few stipulations is that money cannot be sent to countries identified as “non-cooperative” by the global Financial Action Task Force. (The FATF identified Panama as having taken significant steps to comply with standards related to anti-money laundering and combating the financing of terrorism, in February 2016.) The RBI guidelines have largely been a reactive measure to address flows to tax havens. The investigation into the Panama Papers and the scrutiny of the accounts of Indians named in them should pave the way for yet another tightening of the norms.

The global investigation has revealed large-scale possible tax avoidance and parking of income in shell companies, possibly earned through graft and cronyism by powerful political and governmental actors. The fallout has already begun, with the resignation of one Prime Minister (of Iceland), and a shadow of doubt on the political leadership in countries such as Russia and China. This could be the tip of the iceberg; the leaks relate to just one offshore law firm, even if it is the fourth largest in the world. A global tax avoidance problem requires a coordinated response, and the papers point to the urgent need for much more transparency in the movement of global finance capital. The NDA government has passed the Undisclosed Foreign Income and Assets (Imposition of Tax) Act, 2015 and provided a one-time compliance window to declare foreign assets and income. So far, these steps have yielded little by way of repatriation of transferred assets. The problem of black money stashed overseas has to be dealt with both at the multilateral level, through tightened capital flow norms, and domestically, through a zero tolerance approach to illegal transfers. 
		</body>
	</article>
	<article>
		<title>World figures named in massive offshore tax evasion leak
		</title>
		<body>
A cache of documents has exposed the secret offshore dealings of aides to Russian President Vladimir Putin, world leaders and celebrities, including Barcelona forward Lionel Messi.

An international coalition of media outlets on Sunday published what it said was an extensive investigation into offshore financial dealings of the rich and famous, based on a vast trove of documents provided by an anonymous source.

The International Consortium of Investigative Journalists, a non-profit organisation based in Washington, said the cache of 11.5 million records detailed the offshore holdings of a dozen current and former world leaders, as well as businessmen, criminals, celebrities and sports stars.

In India, The Indian Express was part of the investigation and has reported that many Indian industrialists and celebrities, including actors Amitabh Bachchan and Aishwarya Rai, DLF owner K.P. Singh and Vinod Adani (Gautam Adani’s elder brother), are named in the documents.

A cache of documents has exposed the secret offshore dealings of aides to Russian president Vladimir Putin, world leaders and celebrities including Barcelona forward Lionel Messi. An investigation into the documents by more than 100 media groups, described as one of the largest such probes in history, revealed the hidden offshore dealings in the assets of around 140 political figures, including 12 current or former heads of states.

The scale of leaks

'No monetary compensation'

A Munich-based daily, Sueddeutsche Zeitung, was offered the data through an encrypted channel by an anonymous source who requested no monetary compensation and asked only for unspecified security measures, said Bastian Obermayer, a reporter for the paper.

The data concerned internal documents from a Panama—based law firm, Mossack Fonseca. Founded by German—born Juergen Mossack, the firm has offices across the globe and is among the world’s biggest creators of shell companies, the newspaper said.

Ramon Fonseca, a co-founder of Mossack Fonseca, said the firm had no control of how its clients might use offshore vehicles created for them.

“We are not responsible for the actions of a corporation that we set up,” he told Panama’s Channel 2.

Panamanian govt offers to 'vigorously' cooperate

Panamanian President Juan Carlos Varela issued a statement saying his government would cooperate “vigorously” with any judicial investigation arising from the leak of the law firm’s documents. He said that the revelations shouldn’t detract from his government’s “zero tolerance” for any illicit activities in Panama’s finance industry.

ICIJ said the law firm’s leaked internal files contain information on 214,488 offshore entities connected to people in more than 200 countries and territories. It said it would release the full list of companies and people linked to them early next month.

Obermayer said that over the course of several months Sueddeutsche Zeitung received about 2.6 terabytes of data more than would fit on 600 DVDs. The newspaper said the amount of data it obtained is several times larger than a previous cache of offshore data published by WikiLeaks in 2013 that exposed the financial dealings of prominent individuals.

“To our knowledge this is the biggest leak that journalists have ever worked on,” Obermayer said.

The newspaper and its partners verified the authenticity of the data by comparing it to public registers, witness testimony and court rulings, he told the AP. A previous cache of Mossack Fonseca documents obtained by German authorities was also used to verify the new material, Obermayer added.

Among the countries with past or present political figures named in the reports are Iceland, Ukraine, Pakistan, Saudi Arabia, Russia and Argentina.

The Guardian newspaper, which took part in the investigation, published a video on its website late Sunday showing an interview with Iceland’s Prime Minister, Sigmundur David Gunnlaugsson. During the interview with Sweden’s SVT television, the Prime Minister is asked about a company called Wintris. He responds by insisting that its affairs are above board and calling the question “completely inappropriate,” before breaking off the interview.

Leaks trying to discredit Putin, says Kremlin

In Russia, the Kremlin last week said it was anticipating what it called an upcoming “information attack.”

Russian President Vladimir Putin’s spokesman, Dmitry Peskov, told reporters that the Kremlin had received “a series of questions in a rude manner” from an organisation that he said was trying to smear Putin.

“Journalists and members of other organizations have been actively trying to discredit Putin and this country’s leadership,” Peskov said.

“The main target of this disinformation is our president, especially in the context of the upcoming parliamentary elections and in the context of a longer-term perspective - I mean presidential elections in two years,” Peskov told a conference call with journalists.

“This Putinophobia abroad has reached such a point that it is in fact taboo to say something good about Russia, or about any actions by Russia or any Russian achievements. But it's a must to say bad things, a lot of bad things, and when there's nothing to say, it must be concocted. This is evident to us.”

Peskov said the publications contained “nothing concrete and nothing new” about Putin.

The 10 most popular tax havens in the Panama papers

Argentina president confirms offshore company

The office of Argentina’s president, Mauricio Macri, confirmed on Sunday that the business group owned by his family set up Fleg Trading Ltd., an offshore company based in the Bahamas. But it said Macri himself had no shares in Fleg and never received income from it.

Macri’s office commented after La Nacion, an Argentine national newspaper, reported that he and his family had links to Fleg.

The ICIJ said the documents included emails, financial spreadsheets, passports and corporate records detailing how powerful figures used banks, law firms and offshore shell companies to hide their assets. The data spanned a time frame of nearly 40 years, from 1977 through the end of 2015, it said.

“It allows a never-before-seen view inside the offshore world providing a day-to-day, decade-by-decade look at how dark money flows through the global financial system, breeding crime and stripping national treasuries of tax revenues,” the ICIJ said.

Iceland PM Gunnlaugsson refuses to resign

Iceland’s prime minister insisted on Monday he would not resign after the Panama documents linked him to an offshore company that would represent a serious conflict of interest.

News reports have alleged that Prime Minister Sigmundur David Gunnlaugsson and his wife set up a company in the British Virgin Islands with the help of a Panamanian law firm at the center of a massive tax evasion leak. The reports have prompted calls for a no—confidence vote in parliament against him.

Going on Icelandic television Monday afternoon, Gunnlaugsson said he would not resign and added there was nothing new in the information contained in the Panama Papers data leak.

Iceland’s foreign minister also said on a trip to India that the prime minister had not done anything illegal.

“There is nothing strange there,” said Gunnar Bragi Sveinsson, the minister for foreign affairs and external trade.

Poroshenko denies breaking law

Ukraine’s President Petro Poroshenko insisted he has done nothing wrong and hasn’t managed his assets since being elected.

But Oleh Lyashko, leader of the Radical Party, said Monday the trove of data on offshore financial dealings revealed by an international media consortium has implicated Poroshenko in alleged abuse of office and tax evasion.

Poroshenko promised voters he would sell his candy business, Roshen, when he ran for office. But documents from the Panamanian law firm Mossack Fonseca indicated that instead he set up an offshore holding company to move his business to the British Virgin Islands, possibly saving millions of dollars in Ukrainian taxes.

Lyashko urged lawmakers to initiate impeachment proceedings against the president. Poroshenko, whose faction has 136 seats in the 450-seat parliament, appears protected from the motion, which requires a three—quarter majority to pass, but the scandal stands to hurt him politically.

In a Facebook posting, Poroshenko insisted that he hasn’t managed his assets since taking the office.

“I believe I might be the first top office official in Ukraine who treats declaring of assets, paying taxes and conflict of interest issues profoundly and seriously, in full compliance with the Ukrainian and international private law,” he said. “Having become a President, I am not participating in management of my assets, having delegated this responsibility to the respective consulting and law firms. I expect that they will provide all necessary details to the Ukrainian and international media.”

Global banks hand-in-hand with Mossack Fonseca

According to the media group’s website, global banks including HSBC, UBS, Credit Suisse, Deutsche Bank and others have worked with Mossack Fonseca to create offshore accounts.

“The allegations are historical, in some cases dating back 20 years, predating our significant, well-publicised reforms implemented over the last few years,” HSBC spokesman Rob Sherman said in an emailed response to an AP request for comment.

“We work closely with the authorities to fight financial crime and implement sanctions,” he said.

UBS, Credit Suisse and Deutsche Bank did not immediately respond to a request for comment. 
		</body>
	</article>
	<article>
		<title>D.K. Ravi case: CBI team in Kolar
		</title>
		<body> A team of officers from Central Bureau of Investigation (CBI), which is probing into the mysterious death of IAS officer D.K. Ravi visited the Deputy Commissioner’s office in Kolar on Monday.

The three member team led by Senior Official John visited Kolar in the backdrop of Mr. Ravi serving as Deputy Commissioner here before he was transferred to Bengaluru as Additional Commissioner of Commercial Taxes (Enforcement).

The CBI officers spoke to Deputy Commissioner K.V. Thrilokcnhadra and Additional D.C. S.R. Peddappaiah besides some other staff of the D.C. office.

They inspected Mr. Ravi’s official diary which was maintained during his tenure as Deputy Commissioner here and also went through vital circulars and other documents, sources said.

The visit by CBI sleuths acquired prominence following wide-spread allegations that some politicians and legislators in the District exerted pressure on the State Government for Mr. Ravi’s transfer as the officer was not buckling to the pressures of sand and land mafia.

Mr. Ravi who worked for about 15 months in Kolar had earned the affection of residents in the region through his number of people-friendly administrative measures.

He was transferred in October 2014 amid strong protests.

Mr. Ravi was found hanging in his apartment in Koramangala in Bengaluru on March 16, triggering protests demanding CBI probe.

Kolar was in the forefront in this agitation with people from various sections of society taking to the streets. 
		</body>
	</article>
	<article>
		<title>D.K. Ravi case: CBI initiates probe
		</title>
		<body>
The CBI officials needed certain facilities for the investigations and we have agreed to provide them: Additional Chief Secretary

The officials of Central Bureau of Investigation (CBI) on Thursday visited Vidhana Soudha and met Additional Chief Secretary (Home) to officially initiate investigations into the death of IAS officer D.K. Ravi.

A team of officials, accompanied by Superintendent of Police (Bengaluru CBI unit) Subramanayeshwara Rao met Chief Secretary Koushik Mukharhjee and Additional Chief Secretary, S.K. Pattanaik and discussed the case for over two hours.

“The CBI officials needed certain facilities for the investigations and we have agreed to provide them”, Mr. Pattanaik told The Hindu.

D.K. Ravi, of Karnataka cadre, was found hanging in his official residence in Bengaluru on March 16.

Superintendent of Police, Krishnamurthy arrived in the city on Wednesday and visited the Criminal Investigation Department (CID) headquarters in Carlton House.

The officials earlier met the CID officials and collected the details of the case to initiate the probe. 
		</body>
	</article>
	<article>
		<title>Congress-BJP war of words over D.K. Ravi death disrupts Lok Sabha
		</title>
		<body>
BJP member Prahlad Joshi bills the IAS officer's death a murder, accuses Karnataka government of a cover up.

The death of Karnataka IAS officer D. K. Ravi under mysterious circumstances earlier this week disrupted proceedings in the Lok Sabha on Thursday as BJP member Prahlad Joshi billed it a murder and accused the State government of a cover up as the bureaucrat had initiated action against the real estate lobby.

Mr. Joshi — a member from Karnataka — echoed the demand for a CBI inquiry made by the officer’s family even as Congress members protested against the allegations levelled against the Karnataka government by the BJP MP. Intervening in the matter, Union Home Minister Rajnath Singh said the Centre would order a CBI probe if the State government made such a recommendation.

Further, he informed the House that he had been in touch with the Karnataka Chief Minister on this case and had been told that a detailed report would be sent to the Centre within two days. As the verbal crossfire continued with Congress members protesting in the Well, Speaker Sumitra Mahajan adjourned the House for 15 minutes. 
		</body>
	</article>
</articles>