<articles>
	<article>
		<title>All You Need To Know About The JNU Controversy And The Logical Indian’s Opinion On The Issue</title>
		<body>Over the past few days, we received a lot of emails and messages from our community members for The Logical Indian’s coverage on JNU. As a responsible alternate-media portal, we believe in covering the complete picture of a news and present it with the most rational and genuine opinion. In order to achieve this, we wait for considerable amount of time to observe the developments in the news story and provide our community members an overall perspective on the news.

Sequence of Events at Jawaharlal Nehru University

A group of students on Tuesday held an event on the JNU campus attended by representatives from most of JNU’s political outfits. The event, titled “The Country Without a Post Office”, had been organised to “stand in solidarity with the struggle of the Kashmiri people for their democratic right to self-determination” and, among other things, to protest the ‘judicial killing’ of Afzal Guru, who was hanged in 2013 after being convicted in the attack on Parliament in 2001. This comes a day after Guru’s third death anniversary.

It soon turned into a scuffle between the ABVP and the Left organisations after the slogans were shouted. Some students present said that the slogans included, “Bharat ke tukde honge hazaar” (India will be broken into a thousand pieces) and “Bharat ki Barbadi tak jung zaari rahegi” (Our fight will continue until India is destroyed).

The event occurred despite varsity administration having cancelled the permission following a complaint by ABVP members, who termed the activity as anti-national. The university administration said that it had been misled all through since the organisers had asked for permission for a “cultural programme”.

The JNU Student Union, as well as a number of Leftist campus outfits, had actually condemned the allegedly divisive slogans chanted at that event. The JNU administration has already instituted a disciplinary enquiry as to how the event took place despite the withdrawal of permission and said it will wait for the probe report before taking any further action.

JNU students union president Kanhaiya Kumar was arrested on Friday in connection with a case of sedition and criminal conspiracy. The police told the court that Kanhaiya was also required to be interrogated for the purpose of identification of other accused who were seen shouting anti-national slogans during the event organised in the Jawaharlal Nehru University (JNU) Campus on February 9.

The Left-inclined Students Federation Of India (SFI) have distanced themselves from the protest.

Rajnath Singh &amp; Smriti Irani have conveyed there will be “zero tolerance” towards anti-national activities.

There has been a widespread debate in the Social Media over the issue. Many terms the incident as “anti-national” while some have termed it as “stifling of dissent”.

Q: Why Would Anyone Raise a Voice in Support of a Terrorist?

The group of people who are raising their voice have confirmed that they not in support of Afzal Guru, rather they are raising their voice against the process of “Judicial Killing”.

Looking Back:

On 3 February 2013, Afzal Guru( Prime convict for December 2001 terrorist attack on the Indian Parliament) was secretly hanged at Delhi’s Tihar Jail around 08:00 am on 9 February 2013 and afterward buried inside jail grounds. His family was not informed prior to execution and his dead body was later denied to his family. Guru’s family was informed of his execution two days after by a letter.

The prison took steps to execute Guru in secrecy. The execution was carried out without the family’s knowledge or any form of public announcement. Guru’s body was buried on prison grounds to prevent a public funeral.

Many legal experts and international human rights group including Amnesty International condemned the secret process of execution saying that it indicates a disturbing and regressive trend towards executions shrouded in secrecy. The operation surrounding the execution of Afzal Guru was code named Operation Three Star.

The event at JNU titled “The Country Without a Post Office”, had been organised to protest this judicial killing of Afzal Guru as per reports available in various news portals.
At the same time, Supreme Court’s Judgement on Appeal by Guru on August 5, 2005 says, “As criminal acts took place pursuant to the conspiracy, the appellant, as a party to the conspiracy, shall be deemed to have abetted the offence. In fact, he took active part in a series of steps taken to pursue the objective of conspiracy.”

The Logical Take:

In a democracy, everyone has the freedom of expression. Undoubtedly, freedom of speech and expression comes with responsibility. If few students from JNU had decided to express their disagreement on the Judicial Killing by organizing a discussion/event, this is still acceptable. What went wrong for JNU and is not at all acceptable is the anti-national (destructive) slogans shouted such as “Bharat ke tukde honge hazaar” (India will be broken into a thousand pieces) “Bharat ki barbadi tak jung zaari rahegi” (Our fight will continue until India is destroyed).
It is evident that the sloganeering against India will hurt the collective conscience of the nation and The Logical Indian strongly condemns any destructive slogans/speech against the country by any individual or public representative.

– No matter which country we belong, we should remain grateful to the country we live in. Every country has some issues, you fight until it gets “fixed” and not until it gets “destroyed”.

We also request the investigating authorities to precisely identify the ones who made anti-national comments and ensure proper legal actions. The students given their time and energy could better use their time and resources to raise their voice on more important issues which are faced by more than a billion people across our country. Kudos to the central government in acting quickly and effectively against dissenting voices.

What Could Be The Way Forward?

Let’s face it, JNU is a university within which multiple student organisations are present. It is a prestigious institute known to be a bastion of free speech. The protestors were too minuscule to be even considered as a sane voice to be emulated. ABVP, BJP, the media and the social media could have ignored a protest which was that small. Too often we let small protests like these cloud our imagination and mix up our priorities. We have issues facing in our countries which demand our immediate attention. As vigil citizens of a democracy let us be on our toes, stick together, work and demand for the development of our country.

Here are two suggestions from The Logical Indian, acting on which such incidents in future can be well avoided –

1) Precautionary – IIT Madras recently issued a circular that bans political activities in the campus. One might not agree but certainly something to ponder given the way small political activities tend to spoil the sanctity of an institute which are pillars of India’s development. Such “political groups” in colleges campuses could be derecognised.

2.) Reactionary – The media could avoid protests within the campus, what happens within the campus could be left to the campus unless there are any signs of scuffle snowballing into riots or property damage and loss of lives.

The Logical Indian within its limits of freedom of speech and as a responsible alternate-media portal condemns the anti-national sloganeering. As a nation, we should create platforms for constructive debates where all voices could be placed, heard, responded and condemned. Let us move forward from protests to discussions and solving problems
		</body>
	</article>
	<article>
		<title>Opinion: The Logical Indian Stands With JNU But Not With The Culprits; Sequence Of Events So Far</title>
		<body>(As a responsible alternate-media portal, we believe in covering the complete picture of a news and present it with the most rational and genuine opinion. In order to achieve this, we wait for considerable amount of time to observe the developments in the news story and provide our community members an overall perspective on the news. Here we bring you our second detailed coverage on the JNU row. Before you draw conclusions, whom The Logical Indian supports or stands with, we request you to kindly go through the complete article and read The Logical Indian’s opinion at the end.)

The Logical Indian had covered until the arrest of Kanhaiya in our previous article (Why Would Anyone Raise A Voice in Support Of A Terrorist?)
In this update today, we take you through important developments in the JNU controversy after Kanhaiya’s arrest:

Anti- National slogans

The arrests made were based on the video which showed Kanhaiya and others raising anti-national slogans. However, it has emerged that the video has been fabricated and confirmed by forensic experts. Two videos have been examined where it is found that it was ABVP members who had raised the anti-national slogans.

Academicians, experts and a lot of people said student leader was arrested without any evidence on ‘sedition charges’ and questioned the home minister to disclose the basis of the arrest.
Attacks in the court premises

Lawyers had brutally assaulted media persons from Firstpost, Times, NDTV among others. The police were found to be mere spectators to the incident if not facilitating it.

Untitled-2

(Image Courtesy: Hindustan Times)

The Bar council of India have apologized for the misbehavior of the members of their fraternity and also have setup a three-member committee which will investigate the incident and submit its report

The NHRC has also squarely blamed Delhi police for colluding with the attackers besides many activists and politicians had termed the attacks as “pre-planned”.

The Logical Indian is appalled by the high-handedness exhibited by the lawyers. It was a sad day for democracy to see people who uphold the law of the land to take the law into their own hands. We appreciate the fact that the Bar Council was quick to condemn the incident.

Resignation of ABVP’s top brass

Three office-bearers of JNU’s unit of Akhil Bharatiya Vidyarthi Parishad (ABVP) resigned on Wednesday in solidarity with the ongoing students’ protests against centre’s handling of the row at the university. In a joint statement, the three leaders said have decided to quit ABVP as they have serious differences over the way the NDA government was handling the issue, adding there is a difference between “interrogation and crushing ideology and branding entire Left as anti-national.”

Supreme Court directs Delhi police to provide adequate security

The Supreme Court (SC) On Friday refused to hear the bail plea of Jawaharlal Nehru University (JNU) student leader Kanhaiya Kumar and asked him to first approach the high court on the issue.
SC had ordered the Delhi Police and the government of India to provide adequate security to Kanhaiya Kumar to peacefully carry out the judicial proceedings in the lower courts and high court.

IIT-Delhi stood with JNU

Various Universities and institutions from India and across the world were quick to condemn the way in which the JNU row has been handled. The latest being the faculty of IIT DELHI who have conveyed their serious concerns over the issue.

Irresponsible role played by the media

The media, as the fourth pillar of democracy who shoulder the responsibility of disseminating verified information was a big let down. The media trial with the use of unverified and misleading information did not help in anyway to shape informed opinions for the masses. It instead whipped up passions and hysteria leading to destructive notions about one of the most celebrated universities of India.

Citizens have to be mindful

Many a times even our fellow citizens fell into the misinformation campaign and thereby preventing them from making an informed and rational opinion on the issue. For instance,

01. Ratan Tata – A fake message which claimed Ratan Tata would not hire from JNU was shared by close to 80 thousand people and ‘liked’ by many multiples more. (Read our detailed coverage)

02. Doctored video of the protest in JNU aired by the media channels, confirmed by forensic experts.(more details)

03. Arrest based on fake tweets from Hafiz Saeed. (more details)

04. Morphed image of Kanhaiya showing a divided India map placed behind him, once again being widely shared on social media, enough raise anti-national sentiments and raise millions of eyebrows.

Untitled-1

(Left: The Original Picture | Right: The Morphed Picture)

Please be careful while consuming and sharing stories/information on the social media:

Time and again, The Logical Indian community made an appeal to all the Internet users in India that whatever you come across any news/story especially on social media or messaging platforms such as ‘Whatsapp’, take a moment and put some effort to verify the authenticity of the news so that you don’t become a part of spreading any misinformation. We put all our efforts to verify the news and stories we publish but despite that, we request all of our members to even verify any news and stories we publish at The Logical Indian. 

The Logical Indian’s Opinion on the JNU row:

The Logical Indian hopes this issue draws to close sooner than later so that the debates and discussion on media and other platforms could return to more pressing needs and policy matters.

The Logical Indian once again reiterates its condemnation towards the people who had raised the anti-national slogans. We request the government to identify them and take appropriate action. Few students raised anti-national slogans, whether rigged or not, let the investigation unfold the truth. But this doesn’t call for #ShutDownJNU, the society should have  called for #ShutDownTheCulprits. The Logical Indian stands with JNU but not with the culprits.

The Logical Indian is appalled by how the media handled the whole issue and how the nation got polarised unnecessarily due to the same.

We request both the media and citizens to be cautious before reaching to a conclusion. Kindly be aware that in the new age of social media, wrong information like photoshopped pics and doctored videos could whip up passions which eventually has the potential for collateral damage. We request all of you to be mindful of the challenges and threats in the information age and, more importantly, stay united and stick together.
		</body>
	</article>
	<article>
		<title>The Recent Ratan Tata – JNU Issue Shows How We Failed As Social Media Users, Once Again</title>
		<body>Amid a raging controversy over events at Jawaharlal Nehru University, there are millions of Indian who believed this image stating that the Tata group has refused to employ JNU students in their company.

Imagine the extent of damage and the number of ignorant people present on social media that such a post got over 73,000 likes,  21,000 shares, 6000 comments  and all this from an individual’s profile that too in just a span of 9 hours (the post has been deleted now and is no longer available).
The image was so widely shared that Tata Group has to officially come forward and clarify that they haven’t issued any such notification and has no relation with whatsoever mentioned in the post as per a report stated on Economic Times.
Such incidents have surfaced in the past too, the photoshopped images were spread all over Internet to spread hatred and misinformation. Platforms such as Facebook and Whatsapp have been extensively used for such propagandas and manipulation of the masses.
Time and again, The Logical Indian community made an appeal to all the Internet users in India that whatever you come across especially on social media or messaging platforms such as ‘Whatsapp’, take a moment and put some effort to verify the authenticity of the news so that you don’t become a part of spreading any misinformation. There’s no doubt social media has empowered us, but with power comes ‘responsibility’.

Verifying a news hardly takes a minute and all it requires is a google search. Whenever you come across such instances. Please don’t share the links/tweets/screenshots unless you verify and find it true. In this age of social media, the power lies with us and so does the responsibility. Think twice before you endorse something on the internet with your like, share and tweet.

We put all our efforts to verify the news and stories we publish but despite of that, we request all of our members to even verify any news and stories we publish at The Logical Indian particularly the sensitive and controversial ones and follow the same habit whenever you come across any such news from any other source. Neither Facebook nor the government can stop anyone or any group from spreading misinformation but all we can do is put our individual effort and verify a sensitive news before sharing it. Each share contributes to a pile of shares and thus you become a part of the viral-chain.

There’s more you can do!
Once you find that the news is false and see people falling for it, you can-

Comment on the post stating that this news is perhaps not authentic as you haven’t found any verified news links hence requesting everyone to refrain from sharing this and spreading the information.

Report the post to the respective platform(Facebook,Twitter,etc) choosing the appropriate reason.
		</body>
	</article>
	<article>
		<title>The Intolerance Debate Is Flawed. Here’s Why</title>
		<body>For the past many weeks, there has been a major national debate on whether India is becoming an intolerant nation. The proponents of this argument cite two trends: one, the recent string of attacks on journalists and freethinkers; and two, the extremism of the anti-beef lobby. The opponents of the argument brand the proponents as anti-Government and politically biased.

Controversial statements by certain political leaders have added fuel to the fire. A growing number of celebrities and civil society activists have given their opinions on the topic. Also, many Sahitya Akademi awardees have returned their awards in protest – and others opposed the same in what has come to be known as ‘Award Wapsi’.

While approaching the issue of intolerance, it is important to note a few valid points with a broad mind:
• No country on earth can claim to be fully tolerant; all countries have friction between communities.
• India is not like any other country – we are a staggeringly diverse nation. As such, it is practically impossible to expect zero cases of communal violence in a nation as dynamic as India.
• We are a robust democracy, but still a young democracy.
• It is the right of every Indian to protest non-violently for anything, even if the cause is unnecessary; free speech is constitutionally guaranteed.

Understanding the aforementioned points, let us now try to accept two very important and hard truths:
• There are elements in Indian society which wish to inflict disorder and which are inherently intolerant.
• However, for a democracy of 1.26 billion people, a dozen religions, three thousand castes and countless ideological factions, India is relatively peaceful.

The debate on intolerance is both important and flawed: important because any debate that involves the country is worth having, and flawed because of the direction it has taken. Problems arise when people give it a religious dimension; India has communal elements, but they are fringe elements. The majority of Indians are not driven by religious divisions; our Constitution is highly liberal and so is our legal system. There are loopholes and imperfections, but ignoring the bigger picture would be unwise and agenda-driven. If India was a religiously intolerant country we would not have survived 70 years of being the most diverse democracy on earth.

In conclusion:
• India, like every country, has both tolerant and intolerant elements in it.
• India is not religiously intolerant. We are a diverse nation and we are largely proud of our diversity. A few violent fringe elements do not represent the rest of us.
• Opposing people who return their awards by asking them to “Go to Saudi Arabia or Pakistan,” is uneducated and stupid.
• The media has largely failed in giving people the full picture, leaving them to come to their own, half-informed conclusions.
• Anytime we have a national debate, it is important to approach it in as apolitical a manner as we can. Otherwise, we risk losing whatever we can accomplish by having the debate.
		</body>
	</article>
	<article>
		<title>Shiv Sena &amp; MNS Went Too Far In Protesting Against The Meat Ban, A Shameful Sight</title>
		<body>Recently, the Maharashtra government imposed a ban on meat in view of Jain community festival, Paryushan. Earlier the Mira Bhayander Municipal Corporation imposed 8 days’ ban on the slaughter and sale of meat, but after public outrage, the ban was reduced to two days. Today, the Bombay High Court stayed ban on sale of meat on September 17, which was in place in accordance to a circular issued by the state government on September 7.

Many protested the ban as they didn’t want the state to dictate their eating habits but few went overboard.

To protest against the ban, On 13 September, 2015 a mob of 50 MNS party workers gathered in front of Jain community hall and roasted meat. The Jain community peacefully ignored the protest and walked away from the premises covering their mouths.

Shiv Sena on their editorial wrote “Muslims at least have the land of Pakistan to go to but if such rituals of Jains keep continuing then which land would give them shelter? If you mess with the sons of the soil, you will have to eat dirt”.

The stance taken by MNS and Shiv Sena only shows how intolerant they are.

The ban on meat during Paryushan has been since 2004. But it has not been implemented consistently as far as the ban on sale is concerned.

To try to regulate food choices of citizens is never a good idea. Instead of a ban, an appeal can be made to shut down the slaughter houses and shops. Those who wants to respect the sentiments will do and those don’t, they won’t. It should be left to citizens to decide what they want to eat based on their religion or personal choices.

Most of the political parties in India survive on politics of hatred and believe in the British policy of “Divide and Rule”. They keep stirring the issues that create divides among communities and will fetch votes from a particular section. Their only motive is to divert the attention of public from real issues. These kind of behaviors from political parties will only create an atmosphere of communal tension.

India is a land of diversity with different cultures and practices, it should be left to the citizens to decide what they want to practice and what not.
		</body>
	</article>
	<article>
		<title>Dadri Lynching: Why It Is Not About Beef Or Hinduism</title>
		<body>It actually is not about the beef or the law & order or even the Hinduism belief; It is about the evil that is raising its head to crush sanity and the secular forces. This is about the sick mentality that has refused to come out of its stagnating mindset and still wishes to subjugate every single weak they encounter to prove they are strong and thus superior. Women, poor, minorities are their chief targets and how they love to target practice!

Since they use the shield of Hinduism, let me barge into this chakravhiew of death and destruction by breaking this mythological shield first. Hinduism is one of the most pragmatic religions that have survived centuries because it evolved and grew to encapsulate the needs of the society as and when the changing times so needed. The cow was made a symbol for a mother as she took care of the family needs like a mother did. From providing milk to helping in the farm lands, her dung as manure and after her death also she came in the aid of the family needs; her holy status ensured her a good treatment and a better life span and thus the bounties that she offered. But practicalities have a way of disappearing when the fanatics want a symbol for all their pent up hate and bigotry.

So cow it is and it was the turn of Mohammad Akhlaq to bear the brunt! He was a Muslim, he lived in UP, UP has elections coming soon, the temple priest had a loudspeaker …all the ingredients ready to mix and get the communal pot boiling. The secular Indian fabric was tarred once again and left the dead questions hanging all around of why did this happen, who needed to make this point, how can a mob overtake civilisation so close to the national capital and on the watch of such a strong Prime Minister?

These are the reasons supporters of beef ban usually put forward and the people like sangeet som and sadhvi prachi endorse. See for yourself how they fail the logic test

1. Beef was introduced by the mugal invaders to the Indian cuisine– Absolute myth, as Vedas refer to the Brahmins eating Beef, and even during religious ceremonies. And Vedas pre date Mohammed by some  centuries, as the common knowledge goes.
Ref: Rig Veda 8.43.11: uksánnaya vashánnaya sómaprsthaya vedháse stómair     vidhemagnáye
Translation: Let us serve Agni with our hymns, Disposer, fed on ox and cow, who bears the Soma on his back.Ref: Rig Veda 10.86.14:  uksnó hí me páncadasha sakám pácanti vimshatím, utáhám admi píva íd ubhá kuksí prnanti me v’shvasmad índra úttarah

Ref: Rig Veda 10.86.14:  uksnó hí me páncadasha sakám pácanti vimshatím, utáhám admi píva íd ubhá kuksí prnanti me v’shvasmad índra úttarah
Translation: Fifteen in number, then, for me a score of bullocks they prepare, and I devour the fat thereof: they fill my belly full with food. Supreme is Indra over all. (Indra eating bulls)
Even undisputed Indian scholars like  Swami Vivekanand had this to say Swami Vivekananda writes in “The complete works of Swami Vivekananda (volume-3 page 174) :
(and on page 536)
“You will be astonished if I tell you that, according to the old ceremonials, he is not a good Hindu who does not eat beef. On certain occasions he must sacrifice a bull and eat it”

So it’s not about Hinduism, it’s your turncoat hindutva that drives your sick stupidity. Be a better student of your culture before being the brand ambassadors of a frightening cult.

2. The sanctity of life– well well well, the criminals who have killed a human being over a rumour, should not even be raising this in defense if they have any shame left! But since i know them to be shameless, i will ignore the human life and ask these animals, if the sanctity of life only is the issue, then why is the life of a fragile chicken or equal beneficiary to humans, the buffalo any less? What crime has the goat and sheep done to not deserve the devotion to their sacred life?

3. The bovines are important for agriculture and milk production and thus these industries suffer due to cattle being sold for meat and consumers pay a heavy prices for milk and agricultural produce- The people who believe that the farmers sell the young good cattle for meat must get their head examined and also the others who believe the dairy industry people sell their milking cows to slaughterhouses. The cattle are sold once they are old and not in any capacity to serve the household or farm or dairy.

4. The Govt is doing what they can and we should not target the PM needlessly- The ministers and the party members have spoken and every reasonable person has heard the gross guilt and venom that the Mahesh Sharmas and Sangeet Soms spew! Their comments do not deserve a place here as they fell just short of commending the killers of Akhlaq for not raping his 17 year old daughter, who was ‘available’ at the venue of murder!  We retain the right to ask the PM every question, as he came to power promising, “abki baar, modi sarkar”!

And since your arsenal of excuses must be already empty, let us drive home the real sensible point that should be your benchmark for every debate next time that gets the constitution in the way. In a sovereign democratic secular republic, it’s not enough if majority demands something. The state cannot differentiate on the basis of religion. You don’t like eating beef, you do not eat beef, the constitution permits you that and just that. It is that simple!
		</body>
	</article>
	<article>
		<title>Baying For #JuvenileRapist’s Blood? Look At The Facts
		</title>
		<body>Mob justice

    DCW chief Swati Maliwal wanted to stay the release of the juvenile convicted in Delhi gangrape
    There are efforts to amend the Juvenile Justice Act
    One amendment is to treat juveniles involved in heinous crimes at par with adult criminals

The facts

    There has been no increase in heinous crimes by juveniles
    In 2014, 22.4% of the crimes by juveniles were violent crimes, down from 31.8% in 2012

More in the story

    Why the arguments by those demanding stricter punishment for juveniles make no sense
    Do juveniles who are convicted relapse into crime after release?
    What are the proposed amendments to the Juvenile Justice Act

On 21 December, Swati Maliwal, chairperson of the Delhi Commission for Women, made a series of dramatic statements.

She blamed the Rajya Sabha for “cheating the country” out of stricter laws that would protect women and said, “I think the time for candle marches is over. Women should pick up mashaals (torches) instead to demand justice.”

But it’s not quite justice Maliwal seems to be seeking but vengeance. She is symptomatic of the public hysteria that surrounds the release of the juvenile convicted for the rape and murder of Jyoti Singh Pandey, or Nirbhaya as she is universally known.

Two days earlier, Maliwal had approached the Supreme Court at midnight to try and stop his release. She urged the court to order a report on his “psychological status” and called it a “black day for women” when the court upheld the law and allowed the release.

Maliwal’s sentiments are echoed by frenzied street demonstrators, political parties and television channels who are collectively demanding that this particular juvenile remain in incarceration.

They also want the law governing juveniles to be changed and the age of adult culpability lowered from 18 to 16.

In essence, this means instead of rehabilitation homes, child offenders would be put into adult jails – alongside other hardened criminals — and could also be sentenced for much longer periods.

Delhi chief minister Arvind Kejriwal wants to go a step further and lower the age to 14.

Ironically, one of the strongest backers for the amendment is Maneka Gandhi, Minister for Women and Child Development.

The gap between mob and reason
The Nirbhaya rape was undoubtedly one of the most brutal and tragic in recent memory. The issue of heinous crimes by juveniles is also deeply disturbing and complex.

The problem though is, all space for complexity has been rail-roaded out of the conversation. Over the last three years, the juvenile in the Nirbhaya case has been relentlessly portrayed by the media as a remorseless monster, the “most brutal” in the gang — even though neither court judgment, charge-sheet, or accounts by caretakers at the reform home bear this out.

But set against this aggravated backdrop, when the Juvenile Justice Act amendments are debated in Parliament today, politicians will be governed not by the long-term impacts of their decisions but the mob mood outside.

No party will dare take contrarian positions.

In effect, law-making has become hostage to hysteria.

The stakes in court
At the centre of this burning debate are two opposing approaches to juvenile crime: one believes in giving rehabilitation a chance; the other wants only harsh punitive action.

If the amendments go through today, it would indeed be a black day for both women and children.

As Enakshi Ganguly, co-founder of Haq, a group working with child rights says, “We all want accountability and a reduction in crime. The question is which route is more effective?”

There are other issues at stake: the vulnerability of children; the social-psychological circumstances out of which juvenile crime arises; and the State’s duty to create a safety net around children.

To lower the age of adult culpability, therefore, would merely be a gross abdication: a withdrawal of the State from its duties.

The pros and cons
But before examining the implications of that, let’s look at the arguments people in favour of the amendments are making.

They believe:

    That heinous crimes committed by juveniles are increasing drastically.
    That recidivism is increasing – which means juveniles, who are let off after just three years in a reformative home, are going back easily into a life of crime.
    That juveniles between 16 to 18 years commit a lot of rapes, so treating them at par with adults is only fair.
    That harsh punishment is a deterrent.
    That if they know there is no strong punishment awaiting them, juveniles will only commit crimes with greater impunity, knowing they can get away

What the data says

All these assumptions are fallacious. Here’s why:

For one, contrary to the perception that juvenile crime has jumped by 50% in the last ten years, the percentage of committed by juveniles – out of the total crimes committed by juveniles — has not gone up as drastically as claimed.

Here’s what NCRB data over the last three years shows:

The percentage of juveniles who committed rape in

    4.2% in 2012

    5.9% in 2013
    5.9% in 2014

The percentage of juveniles who committed assault on women with intent to outrage their modesty was

    2.2% in 2012

    4.5% in 2013
    4.7% in 2014

The data for kidnapping and abduction was

    2.2% in 2012

    3.5% in 2013
    4.3% in 2014

The percentage of juveniles convicted for murder showed a similar graph:

    3.5% in 2012

    3.2 % in 2013
    2.5% in 2014

There’s an important qualification to make while interpreting the percentage of juveniles involved in rape.

In 2012, the age of consent for sexual intercourse was increased from 16 to 18. The definition of rape under POSCO – or the Protection of Children against Sexual Offences Act – was also broadened from peno-vaginal penetration to include all forms of anal, oral and digital contact.

This meant many young boys experimenting consensually with their girl-friends or each other were now open to being accused of rape by families hostile to a relationship.

A recent study of rape cases in Delhi’s district courts conducted by The Hindu showed that 40% of the cases dealt with elopement and consensual sex between young couples, and the girl’s parents filing rape charges against the boy.

The assumptions about recidivism are equally wrong when checked with empirical data. In fact, according to the NCRB, recidivism among juveniles is actually on a decline over the last three years and has gone from 11.2% in 2012 to 5.4% in 2014.

Rajesh Kumar, who runs Seva Kutir, an observation home for juveniles in Delhi — and who has worked with hundreds of convicted juveniles — says that, in is experience, the number of juveniles who relapse into crime has been very small.

But the issue is not just about numbers. It is the principles on which a society wants to organize itself. Most juveniles involved in crime come from impoverished backgrounds and have often been badly brutalized themselves. Sending them into adult prisons would only serve to brutalise them further – not reform them.

Doesn’t the State – and society — owe these young people a chance to start over again?

The children beneath the numbers

As Kumar says, “Children start with petty crimes; then move to bigger crimes if they join gangs. We need to ask ourselves basic questions, such as, why are these kids not in schools?

The next question is, if they go at all, what sort of schools do they go to? Can you call a single room stuffed with hundreds of kids a school? Let’s ask ourselves — what do we want more? Schools or jails?”

One of the arguments put forward by those demanding stricter punishment for juveniles is that organised gangs use children to commit murders and rapes because they know the law is not stringent and children will remain protected.

First, there is no empirical data to support this claim. But, even at the level of argument, if children are being used by organised gangs or adults to commit heinous offences, are they not victims themselves? Instead of treating them as victims, should we want to punish them for acts done at the behest of adults?

The assumption that juveniles commit crimes because they know they can get away easily breaks down on other counts too. The first is common sense: juveniles are hardly prone to consult the clauses of the Indian Penal Code before they commit a crime – arising either out of rage, bad influence, character or circumstance.

Justice Leela Seth, who was part of the 3-member Justice JS Verma committee that amended the rape laws in 2013, has succinctly explained why the committee refused to lower the age of adult culpability from 18 to 16.

There are scientific studies that show children’s brains are not fully mature at 16. Also, the committee’s deliberations reaffirmed that putting a juvenile through a normal trial and jail would erase the possibility of rehabilitation altogether. There would be a greater chance of juveniles turning into hardened criminals and repeat offenders.

Spare the rod, spoil the child?

This brings one to the core issue of efficacy. Will a stricter law really be a deterrent? Would punishing 16 to 18 year olds on par with adults for sex-related crimes increase women’s safety?

One only has to look at the alarm figures around general crime committed by adults – and rape in particular – to get one’s answers: stricter rape laws have not reflected in a drop in rapes by adult men. Nor has the possibility of life imprisonment for murder led to a drop in rate of murders.

As far as juveniles are concerned, there are sobering lessons from countries where juveniles are treated as adults.

America is a case in point. Over the last two decades, they have had a provision similar to the amendments now being considered for India’s Juvenile Justice Act. It is called a ‘transfer system’. Basically this allows the transfer of heinous juvenile cases to courts and jails meant for adults.

But the ‘transfer system’ has clearly proved counter- productive in addressing juvenile crime, public safety, and recidivism. Here’s how an Independent Task Force on Community Preventive Services set up by the US Centre for Disease Control, concluded its study:

“..transfer policies have generally resulted in increased arrest for subsequent crimes, including violent crime, among juveniles who were transferred compared with those who remained in the juvenile justice system. To the extent that transfer policies are implemented to reduce violent or other criminal behavior, available evidence indicates that they do more harm than good.”

Valay Singhrai, who works on child and juvenile related issues in India, is scathing about the false presumptions driving the change in the JJ Act.

“Less than 2,000 juveniles are allegedly involved in rape cases in a country of more than 1 billion people. It is downright dumb to target this group of offenders to control violence against women, which by the way, mostly happens inside our homes.”

Ved Kumari, professor of law in Delhi University, substantiates similar arguments. Neuroscientists have presented incontrovertible proof, she says, that adolescent children are the most vulnerable to negative peer influence due to the way different parts of the brain respond to stimuli at this age.

“It has been proved that most juveniles grow out of crime with maturation if kept away from bad company. The last thing they need is to be abandoned and thrown into adult jails.”

“Maneka Gandhi, the Minister for Women and Child Development,” she continues, “has told the media she is waiting for the juvenile in the Nirbhaya case to commit another offence after his release. This means she believes he has not been reformed. If so, since she is in charge of women and child development, why is she not taking responsibility for the failure of the State to implement the law in letter and spirit?”

The State’s derelictions

Contrary to the lust for vengeance dominating public conversation around juvenile crime, the real point of worry lies elsewhere.

India’s adult jails are brutal places – overfull; callous; violent. Justice JS Verma had called them ‘universities of crime’.

But the reformative infrastructure around juvenile crime is not in much better shape.

The shelter homes are bleak places. There are hardly any rehabilitation services available; apart from a couple of vocational teachers who come to the homes twice or thrice a week, little else is done to help juveniles reintegrate into society. There are no psychological counselors or mentors attached to the juveniles.

The state of this social infrastructure in Delhi – the national capital — is a stark comment on things must be in the rest of the country.

According to law, a Juvenile Justice Boards (JJB) is supposed to finish hearing a case within 4-6 months. In every case, the JJB is also supposed to prepare a social care plan – both within the shelter homes and after a juvenile is released back into society.

Probation officers are also meant to prepare social investigation reports — or SIRs — of each delinquent juvenile, after talking to neighbours, family and friends of the juvenile to understand what drove him/her towards crime.

But the facts on ground are very different: the whole system is overburdened. Delhi has just two juvenile justice boards that have to decide a staggering 250-270 cases a month. The number of probation officers available is four.

Do the math: on an average a probation officer has to prepare about 3 SIRs every day. Clearly, not much effort is going into them. Far from the stipulated 4-6 months, a juvenile’s trial can also go on for several years, sometimes 10. During this period, the juvenile remains confined in an observation home, even though the maximum sentence for juveniles is 3 years.

This state of disarray needs urgent attention. The juvenile convicted for Nirbahya’s horrific rape and murder needed to trigger many important conversations. Unfortunately, the fund for women’s safety created in her name is lying unused. While the productive dialogue around juveniles has not even begun.

The only sentiment the case seems to really have triggered is a desire for blind and short-sighted revenge.

The real question being debated in Parliament, therefore, goes much beyond the letter of the law: the House of Elders will decide today whether India wants to be a reformative society or a retributive one.

The caveat worth remembering is that the latter is the least effective from a standpoint of safety.
		</body>
	</article>
	<article>
		<title>This 16 December, Lets Hope There Are No More 16 Decembers
		</title>
		<body>It’s 16 December again.

Three years ago, we were on the streets. Shouting, lighting candles, protesting, demanding, getting arrested. Three years ago.

The protests were massive. We had gathered on the streets to register our protest against the lax laws that did not deter rapes enough. Three years ago.

Today we have a strange situation wherein the rapists can walk around freely but the women are expected to stay indoors for their safety. We have politicians playing down heinous crimes like rape with obnoxious remarks like “Boys will be boys, mistakes can happen”. We have politicians accused of rape getting tickets from major political parties.

This is not what we had promised to #Nirbhaya three years ago.

We had promised to give a safe and secure life to women. We reneged on that promise by doling out hashtags instead. We limited our role to posting and tweeting about these issues, but never rolled up our sleeves high enough and brought about real change.

Even little children are not safe inside school premises, and this just goes on to show how fast we need to put a comprehensive action plan in place. But what can that comprehensive action plan be? What is the solution to this dreadful problem?

•FIRST, we need to make sure that the stronger laws actually act as a real deterrent to crime. Strong laws are useless without a swift investigation and a speedy justice system. Even today a huge number of crimes against women go unreported. When a woman does manage to muster the courage to request for police action, she is often made to feel embarrassed. Despite there being safeguards in place for rape survivors, our police administrators and politicians often ignore them. This calls for a major overhaul of the manner in which law and order is managed by our states.

•SECOND, we need to inculcate strong values in our children, and encourage them to fight evil at every level, because that’s what education is meant for. A child correctly guided today will not only grow up to become a responsible individual, but also inspire others to fulfil their responsibility. That’s the kind of citizens our country needs.

•THIRD, our politicians must realise that taking issues like rape and molestation lightly is no longer acceptable to the common man. The world is getting closer each day with the advent of technology, and a closer world has resulted in a more aware, a more vocal citizen. This citizen knows how to make all the right noises, because he desperately wants to be heard. The only way to make our politicians listen is through the ballot. DO NOT VOTE ON THE BASIS OF CASTE, RELIGION, LANGUAGE or any such fickle criteria. Vote on the basis of the candidate’s actions and words. Never forget the names and the faces of the unscrupulous politicians who rant derogatory comments about women and sexual harassment.

Lighting candles just for the sake of it is not enough. What we need is an illumination of our hearts and minds.

This 16 December, let’s work towards an India where we don’t have to keep such dates in mind.

Jai Hind!
		</body>
	</article>
	<article>
		<title>What is Net Neutrality? What We Should Do to Save Internet in India?
		</title>
		<body>Would you pay an extra Rs 200 to get access to this article on thelogicalindian.com? Or even just Rs 20? What if you could access Facebook for free, but LinkedIn cost a little more? If people were charged extra to watch Vimeo videos, what are the chances you would upload your short film there instead of YouTube? It might be somewhat simplistic to reduce the entire net neutrality debate to a matter of rupees, but the point these situations illustrate is pertinent: without net neutrality, your internet is not going to be the same.

India’s telecom regulator is gearing up to change the relationship between the internet and its users. In a paper it put out last month, the Telecom Regulatory Authority of India made it clear that it is all set to allow telecom companies to turn the internet from an all-you-can-eat buffet into an a la carte menu. Read Medianama’s useful distillation of the paper here.

But the decision hasn’t been made yet. TRAI’s consultation paper also includes 20 questions posed to the industry and the general public, asking for comments on what India’s internet regulation should look like. Since you are reading this on the internet, and probably want to continue using it, here’s a primer on this policy that will affect all of our lives.
How Consultation Process Works

The public has been asked 20 questions based on above 2 points. You have to send mail to a TRAI email ID with answers to these questions. You can do this till April 24, 2015. Time will be provided for counter comments from April 24th to May 8th.

To make sure that anti net neutrality rules aren’t formed in India, we need your help.You need to send a mail to TRAI mail id advqos@trai.gov.in in support of net neutrality and against differential pricing/speeds

If TRAI does not get enough public mails in support of Net Neutrality, this is what you can expect:-
You will have different packages for accessing internet.

    1 GB data for Rs 252 + Rs 50 for Google + Rs 25 for facebook and so on.
    1 GB data pack would be like the base pack of your DTH.

But you will have to add packs for carrier decided pricing to be able to use all apps.

Isn’t this SCARY? Its just the start!
You can make a difference!

You can make a difference.If you choose to stay silent today thinking that things will eventually sort out, they won’t.
You will have to pay for Youtube, Gaana.com etc. like TV packages.

Do you want this? If not, then please support us. Here’s what you can do to help:

Go read the reddit India thread on net neutrality. Visit Netneutrality.in, which will tell you how to lobby the prime minister. Sign thechange.org petition, which already has 80,000 signatures, asking for net neutrality to be enforced. Go assist Medianama in their efforts tocreate responses to the TRAI consultation paper. Or go respond to TRAI yourself.

Go to change.org petition and sign up to save Internet.

Please raise your voice by signing up the petition in large numbers, tweeting about net neutrality and sending mails to TRAI before April 24th.
		</body>
	</article>
	<article>
		<title>Find Out: Is India For Or Against Free Basics? TRAI Receives 24 Lakh Responses
		</title>
		<body>The net neutrality debate in India:

India does not have any laws that enforce net neutrality. Net neutrality became a topic of discussion in the country in November 2014 when TRAI (Telecom Regulatory Authority of India) began investigating Airtel for offering lower data rates for sites like WhatsApp and Facebook. In December 2014, Airtel changed its service charges for voice calls which were excluded from the set amount of free data purchased by the customer. The move instigated a lot of criticism over the violation of net neutrality and that was when TRAI announced that it would be releasing a consultation paper on the issue to avail valuable input from the public on net neutrality. TRAI issued its first consultation paper on Regulatory Framework for Over-the -Top (OTT) services.

Meanwhile, Facebook joined hands with Reliance Communications and launched the Internet.org which aims to provide free access to a few websites including Facebook through an app. This violated net neutrality in principle as only a select part of the internet would be available for free which would favor usage of only the free sites thereby preventing the growth of start-ups and tearing the internet into pieces. Facebook then came up with the proposition of Free Basics which was nothing but Internet.org carrying a different tag. On December 9th, 2015, TRAI asked for the ideas and opinions of people through another consultation paper on differential pricing for internet services that contained four questions which were to be submitted by the 31st of the month.

Video: Know in 2 minutes the journey of Free Basics and lesser known story about Facebook

The consultation paper on differential pricing:

As of 31st December 2015, about 18.27 lakh responses were received by TRAI that included those sent through Facebook. Almost 8.9 lakh responses were supporting Free Basics that only had the phone number of the respondent as it had been sent through Facebook whereas 5.44 lakh comments were received through the Facebook mail. The major reason for a large number of responses emanating through Facebook is that the social-networking site started running a huge campaign with extremely biased and one-sided opinions to propagate support for its new venture- Free Basics. When TRAI issued the consultation paper on differential pricing, Facebook lashed back by getting people to send emails to TRAI with their designed templates that supported Free Basics and in no way answered the questions posed by the consultation paper. A huge number of Facebook users fell for this ploy as Free Basics was posed as a “good cause” that enables the poor of the country. The resulted into an opinion poll of whether people supported Free Basics or not.

This lobbying effort by Facebook was not taken well by TRAI which anticipated comments on specific issues rather than a template provided by Facebook. This led to the extension of the deadline for submission of comments till January 7th, 2016. The Chairman of TRAI, Ram Sewak Sharma, said, “It is like we have asked Question X and they have given an answer to the Question Y.” Sharma also said that they were not sure what to make of the responses that they had received regarding the Free Basics product. They decided not to consider them as they did not answer the specific questions of the consultation paper. Sharma said that the authority had decided to reply to some of the email ids that they had access to from which they had received template responses, asking them to send their answers to the specific questions raised by TRAI. “Consultation by TRAI are not opinion polls, we are not asking if yes or no because that does not help us. We are asking why you think it is yes or no because that helps us in formulating the policy guidelines. To all those whom we can approach, we will try to reach them,” Sharma said.

The reason for the extension of the deadline was to ensure that appropriate answers were received and everyone had a chance to voice their thoughts.

The current numbers and why they don’t tell you the right story:

Currently out of the 24 lakh responses sent to TRAI on differential pricing almost 18 lakh are against net neutrality. Even after the extension of the deadline for submission, the number of responses sent through Facebook is over 18 lakhs which has understandably led to a massive number of people dissenting net neutrality. Most responses still do not contain specific answers to the questions posed by TRAI. The responses to TRAI’s consultation paper fails to give us an idea about the public’s stand on net neutrality as a major chunk of them have taken the form of a template provided by the social media giant.

In fact, a survey conducted by LocalCircles among 30,000 participants from across the country showed that 81% of the participants stood for net neutrality. This means that the public stance is completely different from what is actually being projected by TRAI’s responses.

The positives from the net neutrality debate till date:

The country witnessed one of its most constructive public discourses which was non-violent as well as circumspect. Despite majority of the replies being sent through Facebook there was a considerably large number of replies that came from other forums as well which has not happened before. This consultation paper had one of the largest number of respondents over 24 lakhs which speaks volumes about the quality and reach of the net neutrality debate.

On 11th April 2015, the YouTube comedy channel All India Bakchod(AIB) uploaded a video titled “Save The Internet” which urged people to send emails to TRAI supporting net neutrality. The video was all over social media and was re-shared numerous times by celebrities as well. Cleartrip.com, the Times Group, NewsHunt, and NDTV pulled out of the Facebook initiated Internet.org showing complete support towards net neutrality. On 23rd April 2015, various organizations under the ambit of Free Software Movement of India organized protests in various cities across India. The website savetheinternet.in was instrumental in creating a huge number of responses that were not from Facebook. The Logical Indian has also come out in support of net neutrality from the very beginning and ensured that proper information has reached its readers.

We would like to thank the TLI community members for their contribution to the net neutrality debate as well as the people of India who have actively taken part in the debate and have responded to TRAI in huge numbers.
		</body>
	</article>
	<article>
		<title>How Airtel, Voda &amp; TRAI Are Trying To Screw Indian Internet Users!
		</title>
		<body>Perhaps you’ve heard of this phrase “net neutrality”. And about some tussle over it.

And perhaps you’ve let it slide from your consciousness, because it doesn’t seem like it could concern you, especially in India.

But lend me your eyes for a few minutes and let me tell you how India’s telcos and telecom regulators are trying to pull wool over them.

First, is there a problem now? Actually no. You’ve enjoyed the internet, the way it’s supposed to be – freely and fully, till now. But in 16 days from the day I write this – April 22, 2015, the telecom regulators in India are preparing to recommend that it all change. Against you.

Here’s what the big fight is all about.

Till recently, the telecom companies had enjoyed a great run in India, making tens of thousands of crores in profits over a long run, as India grew to 800 million mobile phone users from virtually nothing.

During this time, they’ve largely focused on selling voice minutes – while at the back end they have been using voice over internet protocol (or VOIP) to connect with other telcos and deliver calls using the internet. And given that the cost of VOIP is a tiny fraction of the cost of traditional voice calls they were charging, they raked in the moolah.

But, now thanks to the likes of WhatsApp and Skype and Google Hangouts, consumers can get the same voice calls delivered at internet prices, direct to their handsets. And this has the telcos running scared. Their margins are eroding.

So now the telcos want to charge for the internet differently, based on how you use it. By now you’re saying – sure, if I use more bits and bytes, I’m ready to pay more. Actually, as bandwidth is infinite, the cost of bandwidth goes down globally all the time, you rarely pay more. But the telcos know this.

No – this is different – they want the right to charge what they want, when they want and how they want, with no logic whatsoever. In effect, if Airtel doesn’t like YouTube but wants to push its own video app Wynk – it wants the right to offer that for free while charging you a bomb to access YouTube.

One of our telcos, Reliance, has already gone ahead with this Facebook-driven evil scheme called Internet.org – where you can access Bing for free, but you have to pay to access Google – and you have access to BabaJobs for free, while you have to pay for Naukri.com. They’ve sold it as a “solution for poor countries” but what they really mean is that it’s a “solution to keep countries poor”.

This breaks the very nature of the Internet.

In the US, this kind of differential pricing at whim has been made illegal. The US government has ruled strongly in favour of net neutrality.

But in India, the telcos have managed to get one person to write a “consultation paper” on behalf of the supposedly-independent TRAI (Telecom Regulatory Authority of India) asking for public opinion on allowing telcos to break net neutrality.

The note -which is terribly written, and deeply biased  is here. If you don’t want to read through 117 pages of shoddily-written propaganda full of deliberately confusing jargon, there’s a much shorter summary by my friend @Nikhil Pahwa of Medianama at Http://Tinyurl.com/TRAIpaper and a set of answers to frequently-asked questions at Http://tinyurl.com/TRAIfaqs

But if you want the really, really, really short summary, here is logic in the TRAI paper: Telcos have invested lots of money to build out the network. They used to make a lot of money off it. But now other people are making money on this network, because they innovated while the telcos did not – so this is a bad thing. So we need to let telcos charge people however they want so telcos can make the money they need. Basically: poor telcos. Sob, sob, sniff, sniff.

This TRAI Consultation Paper is a load of complete bullshit.

For the following reasons. The first fallacy: that the telcos did us a favour. To start with, the airwaves are ours, the people of India’s. Telcos bid for and paid a license fee to our representatives, the government of India, to temporarily license our airwaves to sell their networks on it. So building out the telecom network in India wasn’t a favour someone did for us – we asked these firms to do it and they paid us for it and profit from it. They knew what they were buying, they paid for it, and they got it. Now the world has moved past their fat margins on their outdated technologies, and they’ve failed to innovate. Other people, not telcos, have built WhatsApp and Skype. Their problem. Not ours.

Second fallacy, these firms are hurting financially. Nonsense again. Look at the publicly-quoted revenue figures of Indian telcos – and you’ll find that, like in any other business, some did very well, some did very badly and others did middlingly okay. Like in any other business. And look at them historically – they’ve all more than recovered the amounts they bid for the spectrum. No one is in the poorhouse. And even if they get into the poorhouse in the future, we don’t have any sovereign duty to help them out. Business is Darwinian. They didn’t innovate, we don’t need to bail them out.

Third fallacy, that there is a natural reason we need to be telco-friendly as technology changes. Nope again. Consider this analogy. We own our water. Let’s say we want to license a firm or set of firms to distribute our water to residents across town. Some private and public firms, after open and transparent bidding, get these licenses. They distribute water, charge for it and all is well.

Now, after a little while, one person who gets water decides to use it to make soft drinks. He uses more water, and pays for it, at the agreed-to rate. And he sells the soft drinks. Another uses the water, pays for it, and sets up beautiful water fountains that people pay him to come and see. A third uses the water, pays for it, and opens a water park, where kids come and enjoy themselves.

Now imagine that the water distribution companies could have done any and all of these things all along – but chose not to. Now they get jealous of these other businesses – and want to be allowed to charge soft-drink users and water-park visitors any fee, without any logic, without it being based on water usage.

Another analogy. Imagine if your electricity distribution companies – Tata or Reliance / BSES or whoever would suddenly get up and start charging more for electricity from you if you used efficient light bulbs, or if you were used appliances that consumed less electricity. Because they made less money as a result of your smartness.

You’d say it was ridiculous. It is.

The TRAI paper is trying to make a make-believe case that telcos and ISPs who chose not to innovate should be compensated for their incompetence.

What can we end up with if we allow this to pass?

Once, shoddier products. Like Reliance and Facebook who are together offering Facebook for free and Twitter at a price, or Babajobs free but asking you to pay to access Naukri, or forcing you to use Bing because it is free unlike Google – allowing anti-net-neutrality will make our internet experience worse. And I say this, not because I have any grudge against Facebook, Babajobs and Bing – but because I think we consumers should have the ability to pick whichever social network, job site and search engine we want – and not leave it to some rapacious telco or social network to decide what we should use.

Two, higher bills. It’s one thing to charge for bandwidth – and no one should have a problem with that. The price of that is falling anyway, as it should. Today, I have a 2 mbps connection at home for the same amount that I used to have a 256 kbps connection a few years ago. And I’m happy to pay for 10mbps too, if it comes to my home or my phone and does so at price I can afford. Or I can choose to save money and stay at 2 mbps as it becomes cheaper. It’s my choice.

But it is completely wrong for me to have to pay Airtel or Vodafone or some ISP any money to specifically access YouTube, or Skype, or any particular site that they decide to charge for at their whim and fancy. These folks are the pipe-layers and their job is to push stuff through the pipes – which we can pay for, based on how much of the stuff they push is used by us. They have no other rights.

What we do with the bandwidth must be up to us, not up to some profiteering telecom tycoon in Gurgaon or Mumbai.

So what can you do to help?

The telcos, their cosy cabal, the COAI (Cellular Operators Association of India) and the author of the TRAI paper are trying to push through anti-net-neutrality in India.

My request to you is to do your little bit to stop it, and to ensure net neutrality.

There are a few things you can do. One – sign this petition

Two, write directly to TRAI at “advqos@trai.gov.in“. The author of TRAI’s paper may be biased – but it is a government body after all – and they have to listen to you. Here’s one suggested text of what you can mail them – do modify at will:

    Dear TRAI, I am writing to express my concern against the actions that telecom carriers are taking to restrict fair access to the internet (Net Neutrality). I believe the internet is a vital resource – it helps me communicate, work, and thrive as a citizen. If telecom operators can discriminate internet traffic on the basis of which services pay the most, we are allowing telcos control over a vital and necessary technological resource. By doing so we allow them to define what information we can view; what entertainment we can access; and how companies can innovate.

    This is completely unfair and harms India’s long term role in the global market. I strongly believe the growth of telecoms and the well-being of the internet can go hand-in-hand. I’m asking for a framework to ensure long term and fair access for all services regardless of size. I want my generation and those that come after me to have unfettered access to the Internet, with no telcos or ISPs having the ability to charge for specific services I use on top of it. Please understand that the internet is an important resource and vital to me and to every other Indian citizen. I would like to see it kept free and protected under Net Neutrality to ensure fair and equal access for all and forever. Regards, {Your Name}

Three, if you do have access to Ravi Shankar Prasad, the telecom minister – or anybody else in the ruling party – tell them that you believe strongly in net neutrality and that you expect the government to take a strong stand on it.

I don’t have that access – so I can also suggest a fourth option: share this piece on LinkedIn, or on Facebook or on Twitter, or on email – and get it across to your others. Someone, somewhere who reads it can make a call, make a point, or make a big difference.

We have 2 weeks left. Let’s not allow the telcos to get away with this.
		</body>
	</article>
	<article>
		<title>DK Ravi
		</title>
		<body>#DKRavi was known as an honest and upright officer who dared to stand against the powerful land sharks and sand mafia, but that's not all.

Ravi, a 2009 batch IAS officer himself hailed from a remote village in Tumakuru, Karnataka. Ravi was known as a man with a vision and a wholehearted dedication towards the people. He undertook many progressive works in Kolar district where he was posted as a Deputy Commissioner which helped him win over the hearts of the people and endeared him to one and all.

As reported in Bangalore Mirror, Ravi's major works included -

► A crackdown against land sharks and sand mafia. As per the directions of the High Court, he not only raided and recovered crores of rupees worth government land from land sharks, but also seized illegal mining blocks and stopped the loot of natural resources.

► He also provided a one-stop solution to farmers and the public to get their land records under one roof. This move was accepted by the Chief Minister and extended all over the state.

► Ensuring quality in public works, Ravi himself checked quality of works like roads, drainage by making surprise checks. He filled the parched lakes of Kolar with treated water from Bengaluru, launched 'cleaniversity' (a word he coined for clean-university) across Kolar town to dispose solid waste.

► He introduced 'Our Kolar; Our Contribution' scheme and facilitated easy availability of medicine in all government hospitals. Ravi set an example to other bureaucrats by visiting a dalit's house during Gandhi Jayanthi celebrations.

► Motivating students to take up competitive exams in large numbers, Ravi personally trained IAS/KAS aspirants.

Clearly, DK Ravi was an extraordinary man with superhuman ability and determination. He was an optimistic and enthusiastic man, which is why those who knew him sense foulplay in his death that happened in mysterious circumstances a few days ago.

Various reports in the media have termed his death as a murder and blamed the Karnataka Home Minister for being in cahoots with the mafia. Social media and mainstream media alike have been working overtime trying to connect (and at times, concoct) the dots surrounding his death. The police and the ministry have been on record declaring that prima-facie, the death looked like a case of suicide caused by personal distress. However, activists and supporters of Ravi have reacted strongly to these claims and accused the government of slandering the braveheart and asked for a CBI enquiry into the whole issue.

The Logical Indian salutes this brave officer who set an example for all other IAS officers with his tremendous work. At the same time we urge the Karnataka government to hand over the case to the CBI for an independent enquiry. Refusing a CBI enquiry only incriminates the state government as already there are many question marks put on the way this case has been handled.
		</body>
	</article>
</articles>